<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The immortality of the soul asserted, and practically improved shewing by Scripture, reason, and the testimony of the ancient philosophers, that the soul of man is capable of subsisting and acting in a state of separation from the body, and how much it concerns us all to prepare for that state : with some reflections on a pretended refutation of Mr. Bently's sermon / by Timothy Manlove.</title>
            <author>Manlove, Timothy, d. 1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 232 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51787</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M454</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6833</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12637076</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12637076</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64916</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51787)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64916)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 697:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The immortality of the soul asserted, and practically improved shewing by Scripture, reason, and the testimony of the ancient philosophers, that the soul of man is capable of subsisting and acting in a state of separation from the body, and how much it concerns us all to prepare for that state : with some reflections on a pretended refutation of Mr. Bently's sermon / by Timothy Manlove.</title>
                  <author>Manlove, Timothy, d. 1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 164 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Roberts for Nevill Simmons ..., and sold by George Coniers ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: sides cropped, most page numbers lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bentley, Richard, 1662-1742. --  Of revelation and the messias.</term>
               <term>Immortality.</term>
               <term>Soul.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64916:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>IMMORTALITY</hi> OF THE SOUL Aſſerted, and Practically Improved: SHEWING By SCRIPTURE, REASON, and the Teſtimony of the ANCIENT PHILOSOPHERS, That the SOUL of Man is capable of ſubſiſting and acting in a State of Separation from the Body; And how much it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns us all to prepare for that State.</p>
            <p>With ſome REFLECTIONS on a Pretended Refutation of Mr. <hi>Bently</hi>'s Sermon.</p>
            <p>By <hi>TIMOTHY MANLOVE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <bibl>Plat. in Phaed.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Roberts</hi> for <hi>Nevill Simmons,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Sheffield, Yorkſhire.</hi> And ſold by <hi>George Coniers</hi> Bookſeller at the <hi>Ring</hi> in <hi>Little Britain, London,</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64916:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64916:2"/>
            <head>To the Candid and Impartial READER.</head>
            <p>§ <hi>I.</hi> IT ſeems an Argument (equally <hi>convictive</hi> and <hi>deplorable</hi>) of the monſtrous degeneracy of the Spirit of Man, that it ſhould doubt its own <hi>Spiritual Nature!</hi> and be in ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence unto which <hi>Claſs</hi> of Beings to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerate it ſelf! Whether it be more a-kin to <hi>Mind,</hi> or <hi>Duſt;</hi> and whether, as the latter, it ſhould count it ſelf more ally'd to <hi>this World,</hi> which it is but to paſs through; or <hi>the other,</hi> where it is to deſign for it ſelf an everlaſting abode? that it ſhould ſuſpect its Nature to be leſs ſimilar to the Inhabitants of Heaven, than to Particles of Earth? Or that it ſhould any-where be found debaſed to ſo low a pitch, as to think it ſelf more fit to be ſorted with Clods here below, than with Angels above!</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:64916:3"/>§ <hi>II.</hi> We are indeed carefully to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh, in the conſideration we ought to have of <hi>our ſelves,</hi> between what we are <hi>in natural,</hi> and what <hi>in moral re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</hi> We cannot <hi>upon the latter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi> think too meanly of our ſelves, as <hi>having ſinned, and fallen ſhort of the glory of God.</hi> But <hi>upon the former account</hi> we cannot judge of our ſelves more meanly than our proper rank in the Creation allows, without reflecting injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly upon our Maker. Here a mean Self-deſpiciency, is moſt ingenerous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful. And when, <hi>upon this natural account,</hi> we are God's Off ſpring, and in ſtiling himſelf <hi>the God of the ſpirits of all fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Father of ſpirits,</hi> he intimates our near alliance to himſelf, and calls us <hi>his Sons,</hi> we call our ſelves <hi>Sons of the Earth,</hi> we cannot here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>vilify our ſelves,</hi> without <hi>reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him.</hi> And in this reſpect it might amaze one, to think it ſhould be needful to write <hi>a Book,</hi> to prove that a piece of Clay cannot reaſon! deliberate! lay De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns! form Thoughts! deduce one Thought from another! raiſe Thoughts
<pb facs="tcp:64916:3"/>far above the whole Sphere of Material Beings! even ſo high as to reach unto the <hi>Supream being</hi> it ſelf: Or that it ſhould be requiſite to confute <hi>a Book</hi> that, if it have any meaning at all, muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to mean as abſurd a Paradox as this! Inaſmuch as no mortal man can prove that a Clod of Clay is not reſolvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble into as fine Particles, as any the fineſt Matter whatſoever.</p>
            <p>But ſince ſuch an Antidote was become neceſſary againſt ſo ſtupifying a Poyſon, and that there is reaſon to think too many minds may be prepared to receive ſo poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous Sentiments as the Pamphlet here animadverted on, contains, by a ſtupidity in reading, equal to that wherewith it was writ; we congratulate the Age, that it hath produced <hi>the one</hi> ſo opportunely for <hi>the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we cannot in the mean time but further pauſe, and bethink our ſelves; and with aſtoniſhment cry out,</p>
            <p>§ <hi>III.</hi> Whither is Human Nature ſunk and gone, that any perſons can ſo ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly brutify and degrade themſelves, and
<pb facs="tcp:64916:4"/>be as in pangs of travel, till they have ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked themſelves amongſt thoſe Creatures, which God himſelf hath ſet ſo much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, and ſo evidently hath formed to be ſubjected to their uſe and pleaſure? <hi>2 Pet 2.12.</hi> Souls ſo demonſtrative of the Exiſtence of a God, ſo expreſſive of his Eminencies, ſo receptive of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, ſo apprehenſive of his Works and Will, ſo uſeful and ſignificant in his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo fit to know, to govern and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs themſelves, and to make ſuch great and wonderful improvements of what oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs in the whole frame and courſe of things: Yea, and ſo formed to, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable and ambitious of Immortality, and ſo accommodated for it; Are theſe only or ultimately given to keep a little Fleſh from ſtinking? to do ſome Artificial Feats and Tricks therein, and then to periſh with it? Theſe men are great ſtrangers to themſelves, and inobſervant of their own Faculties and Capacities; and mind not the proviſions which the great Original of all things hath produc'd abundantly, and ſuited to every Faculty, Senſe and Member belonging to them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:64916:4"/>§ <hi>IV.</hi> Eſſences lie deeper than their Principles; and Principles deeper than their Actions or Effects: And every man is nearer to himſelf, than any other Beings are, or can be to him, ſave his God: And he that reads concerning Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Souls, and minds not the powers and actings of his <hi>own Soul,</hi> cannot but be a ſtranger to himſelf, and the more fit to be impos'd upon both by himſelf, and by others. He that forgets, and doth not mind and heed himſelf, whilſt he conſults his Books, can never be ſuch a Proficient in Self knowledge, as otherwiſe he might be. It cannot be denied, but that the Inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinacies and Immoralities of men profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Godlineſs, and zealous in Polemical defending the Soul's Immortality, have miniſtred greatly to the propagation of this dangerous Error. That <hi>the Soul of man is mortal.</hi> And when men are ſunk in guilt, and find their own Convictions troubleſome to themſelves; to make themſelves more eaſy in their courſe of Soul-neglect, they judge themſelves the more concern'd to baffle their belief of the
<pb facs="tcp:64916:5"/>Exiſtence of God, of the Extent and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his Providence, of the Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Soul, and of Eternal Judgment. And when they have extirpated this Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion, they can more eaſily contrive Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and order Practices, to ſerve their own particular purpoſes and turns. But things are not always <hi>what,</hi> and <hi>as</hi> men think they are, or would have them be.</p>
            <p>§ <hi>V.</hi> It is true, ſome of the Patrons and Promoters of this <hi>Fundamental Error,</hi> are Men of admirable Parts and Learning, and fit to make conſiderable Figures, and to do great ſervice to the Publick, and eminently to ſerve their Generations in Conſiſtories, Courts, Camps, Navies, or in other Stations, through their Sagacity, Courage, Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſs, and all the obliging Civilities of Converſation, which the advantages of their Education might diſpoſe them unto. But he that can believe he hath no God to adore and pleaſe, no Soul to ſave or loſe, no final Reckoning to make to a Supream Judge; and ſo no E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Retribution to expect; can have no
<pb facs="tcp:64916:5"/>reverence to his Conſcience, no great and noble end to influence and beautify his Actions, nor indeed any thing fully fit and cogent to ſecure him againſt the moſt accommodate and ſtrong Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in the ſeverities and briskneſs of their aſſaults upon him. His Intereſt, Honour, or Humour, and his adventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious helps from men, are now his ſtrongeſt holds; but when theſe things are likely to be raviſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d from him, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his heart muſt ſink, and break, or he will violate all the Rules of Honeſty and Order, to preſerve himſelf; and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſacrifice the Publick Intereſt to his own Concerns, than act like a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Votary to the Common Intereſt of Mankind. And if that Maxim govern him, <hi>Dulce &amp; decorum pro patriâ mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, aut agere;</hi> yet is it his ambition of being famed in Hiſtory, which mainly prompts him to be ſo heroick: So that in all, it is but his own ambitious and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring Self which is his ultimate end; and all that lies betwixt him and this End, hath but an inferior and ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate contribution thereunto. And hence
<pb facs="tcp:64916:6"/>the Honour, Safety, and Felicity of his King and Country are only valued by him (even as all Creatures ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to him are) merely for his own ſake. So good Security and Service have Kings and Governments from him. And let but this ſelfiſhneſs be every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and every way, the Regent Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, abſtractedly from all ſenſe of, and references to Soul-good hereafter; and then he that hath the ſharpeſt Eye, the greateſt Reach, and the longeſt Sword, will have the moſt undoubted right to all that he can get and keep, though <hi>vi &amp; armis.</hi> And when another ſhall outwit, or conquer him, and call him to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for all, what is the rule and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of this Proceſs, but Selfiſhneſs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to ſatiate Revengeful Thirſt?</p>
            <p>§ <hi>VI.</hi> But what is it that induces Perſons to believe that Souls are mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial and mortal, and ſo to periſh phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally with their Bodies? is it becauſe there is no God? or that God is not able, or not willing to create ſuch Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? is it that either the production of
<pb facs="tcp:64916:6"/>ſuch Beings implies a contradiction, or that God judges it unworthy of, and much below himſelf, to make; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſy and diſhonourable to himſelf to mind them? or to perpetuate their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to their Eternal Happineſs or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, as they behave themſelves, whilſt in this World and Body? Or do they think <hi>(à poſteriori)</hi> that there want Evidences of their Immortality? or that the preſent frame, and ſtate, and courſe of things and Providence, inſinuates the contrary? or that God is too good to eventuate the Eternal Miſery of any Being?</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Exiſtence of a God.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>(1.)</hi> If ever there was abſolutely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, then there never could be any thing exiſtent: For how could ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be produc'd from nothing? What? an Effect without an Action! or an Action without an Agent or Efficient?</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>(2.)</hi> The Eternity of Life, and Light, and All-ſufficiency, is demonſtrably more credible than the Eternity of meer <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> or <hi>Matter:</hi> For Matter in it ſelf is
<pb facs="tcp:64916:7"/>univerſally paſſive and impreſſive from another Nature, and all its Principles and Motions muſt be deriv'd from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and an higher Nature. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that Eſſence muſt be very fine and excellent indeed, which can comprehend and penetrate, and ſo variouſly and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniouſly imprinciple and actuate ſo vaſt a Fahrick as the material <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe. He that could ſo digeſt it into ſuch an excellent and eſtabliſh'd Order as we find it is, muſt needs be Great, Wiſe, Good himſelf, and infinitely ſo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>(3.)</hi> But ſuppoſing there be an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, Infinite Spirit; what greater, more genuine, and apt Evidences, is his Exiſtence capable of, than what conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually face us? <hi>Rom 1.20.</hi> Can Taſte be prov'd to the Eye; or Sounds to the Palate; or Colours and Light to the Ear? All Faculties and Senſes have their proper Objects, and theſe Objects have their peculiar Evidences to their own Nature, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Ends, as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect their different Faculties and Senſes. Things <hi>Viſible</hi> are beſt known by being <hi>ſeen;</hi> things <hi>Audible,</hi> by being <hi>heard.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:7"/>Blind men will know Light much better, if ever their Eyes ſhall be open'd, by one glance thereat, than by all the moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate Diſcourſes upon Light, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were, or could be read to them; and yet before they ſaw, they apprehended there were ſuch things as Light and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but not ſo ſatisfyingly as by their own actual ſeeing of it. Now if ſeeing the vaſt viſible bulk and compaſs of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, the evidently wiſe Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of it, with all the accurate depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies and ſubſerviencies of all the parts thereof, as to their mutual uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs each to other, and all its furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to maintain, aſſiſt, and pleaſe all its Inhabitants ſuit ably to their different Capacities, Stations, and Concerns, be not ſufficient to prove Infinite Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs in exiſtence to the thinking mind, what can!</item>
            </list>
            <p>As to God's <hi>Ability</hi> and <hi>Willingneſs</hi> to produce ſuch Beings as Immortal Souls;</p>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:64916:8"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>(1.)</hi> There is no contradiction in the terms or thing; let them <hi>demonſtrate</hi> who <hi>aſſert</hi> the contrary, if they can.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>(2.)</hi> Souls are produced by God's Creating Power, and breathed into Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Fleſh: And their conſtituent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, their vaſt Capacities, their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Functions, and vivid Operations, the vaſt Proviſions which God hath made for their Entertainment, Employment, and Improvement; (ſuch as the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Treaſures of Nature; the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe and Iſſues of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Providence; the Openings and Advantages of a Goſpel-day; the <hi>even ſenſible</hi> Influences, Impreſſions, and Effects of Providence and Grace upon the Spirits of Men) the Souls apparent Juriſdiction and Dominion over it ſelf, (yet under Law to God and Chriſt, whoſe dealings with it would yet admit of lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Thoughts, did not the Impatient Preſs forbid them) and its Ability to make all Tributary to its own advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, as to Self-conduct, Government, and Poſſeſſion, and to reflect upon, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, approve, or to cenſure its own
<pb facs="tcp:64916:8"/>Actions; yea, and to look beyond what Time and meer Matter can amount unto. All theſe (and much more) make it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, both what Souls are, and will hereafter be conſigned to.</item>
            </list>
            <p>As to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or God-becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingneſs in the Caſe: Why ſhould it be thought unworthy of him, ſeeing it is done ſo evidently by him, <hi>who work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things after the counſels of his Will?</hi> Eph. <hi>1.11.</hi> Is it ſo unbecoming God to create Spirits in his own Image, to impreſs the Signatures of his own Name upon them; to put them into a State of Trial, therein to govern them ſuitably to their Frame and State, and ſo to ſuit their everlaſting State to their preſent Choice, Tempers, and Carriages, and from amongſt the Sons of Men to chuſe and cultivate a Seed for Heaven, and there to take Eternal Pleaſure in all the Accuracies of their compleated Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, their orderly Behaviour and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Satisfactions in himſelf; and in the Triumphs of his Grace and Son over all the baffled Powers of Darkneſs? What
<pb facs="tcp:64916:9"/>Attribute can theſe things diſgracefully affect?</p>
            <p>But how much more than all this, and incomparably better laid together, and more nervoſely argued, and more Pleas to the contrary impleaded with far great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſtrength, will the Impartial (tho' Critical) <hi>Reader</hi> find in the enſuing Treatiſe? To the Ingenious and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Author whereof we think the World greatly obliged, and do offer our hearty Thanks to him, whom (with his Labours, and the diligent <hi>Reader</hi>) we commend to the ſpecial Grace and Providence of God in Chriſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Howe, Matth. Sylveſter.</signed>
               <date>October <hi>14. 1696.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:64916:9"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. I.</label> THE Contrary Hypotheſis laid down, with an Account how far it agrees, or diſagrees with the Philoſophy of <hi>Epicurus, Lucretius, Hobs,</hi> &amp;c. The Method of the following Diſcourſe. <hi>Page 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. II.</label> The Immortality of the Soul proved by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. <hi>Page 12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. III.</label> The Immortality of the Soul proved by ſuch Arguments as are drawn from the Light of Natural Reaſon, and the common Senſe and Experience of Mankind. The Firſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Powers and Faculties where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Soul is endued. <hi>Page 25.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. IV.</label> The Second Argument from the many groſs and dangerous Abſurdities wherewith the contrary Opinion is attended. <hi>Page 49.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:10"/>
                  <label>CHAP. V.</label> Some Subſervient Conſiderations for the further Eſtabliſhment of the Doctrine of the Soul's Immortality. <hi>p. 67.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. VI.</label> The Teſtimony of the Ancient Philoſophers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced for a further Confirmation of this great Truth. <hi>p. 79.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. VII.</label> Our Author's Objections conſidered and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. <hi>p. 93.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. VIII.</label> Of Materiality, or Immateriality as they are aſcribed to the Soul. <hi>p. 103.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. IX.</label> Directions to ſuch as are in ſuſpence as to the Immortality of the Soul, ſhewing how they may arrive at a certainty in that matter. <hi>p. 109.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. X.</label> Directions to ſuch as believe the Immortality of the Soul, ſhewing how they ought to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove ſo important a Doctrine. <hi>p. 131.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Concluſion. <hi>p. 161.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:64916:10"/>
            <head>THE Immortality of the SOUL ASSERTED, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The contrary Hypotheſis laid down; with an Account how far it agrees, or diſagrees with the Philoſophy of <hi>Epicurus, Lucre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Hobs,</hi> &amp;c. The Method of the following Diſcourſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Principles of <hi>ſound</hi> Philoſophy well <hi>tried</hi> and <hi>digeſted,</hi> do great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly improve Humane Underſtandings; the Reaſoning Faculty is cultivated, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced by Exerciſe; by accuſtoming our ſelves to think, we learn in time to think <hi>better,</hi> and <hi>to more purpoſe;</hi> and every Truth which we meet with, and <hi>really</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:11"/>make our own, prepares us for the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of ſome further Truth which is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to it, and depends upon it: And as our Knowledge increaſeth, ſo will alſo the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of our Ignorance.</p>
               <p>Hence it is eaſy to diſcern the Reaſons why, amongſt ſo <hi>many</hi> Pretenders, there are ſo <hi>few</hi> that deſerve the name of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers.</p>
               <p>Some take the knowledge of <hi>Words, Terms of Art,</hi> and <hi>commonly received Forms of Expreſſion,</hi> for the knowledge of <hi>Things;</hi> and theſe they ſwallow without chewing, and upon all occaſions bring up again, as raw as they took them in, and play with them, as Boys do with Bubbles, till Wiſe men laugh at them.</p>
               <p>Others there are, near a-kin to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, who ſuck in Opinions, as the wild Aſſes do the Wind, without diſtinguiſhing the wholſome from that which is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt.</p>
               <p>Others can go no further than they are led by the Noſe. Theſe are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>of a ſlaviſh Nature,</hi> and he that can ſo far get the Aſcendent over them, as to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate himſelf into their eſteem (which is no hard matter to do) may command their Underſtandings, becauſe they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves never knew how to uſe them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:11"/>Others have Imaginations ſo little uſed to government, that they cannot ſix their thoughts upon a ſerious enquiry after Truth, but they quickly give them the ſlip, and go to play with Impertinencies. Some are ſo <hi>dull</hi> that they <hi>cannot</hi> appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend any thing that lies out of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Road, and is not plain, and obvious. Others are ſo <hi>ſloathful,</hi> that they grow weary before they have half accompliſh'd their ſearch. And others ſo fooliſhly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited, that they think it below them to alter their preſent Sentiments.</p>
               <p>But the great hinderance of uſeful Knowledge, is an in-bred, radicated En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in Corrupt Nature againſt thoſe Truths which have a nearer tendency to the reformation of ill Manners, and the exerciſe of ſerious Religion.
<q>Hinc origo mali—</q>
And the Age in which we live, affords many unhappy Inſtances of the <hi>Predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy</hi> of this Corruption, which makes a Learned Gentleman thus to reflect upon it, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>That we are fallen into an Age declining from God, in which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are fond of thoſe things which lead us fartheſt from him, and ſeem moſt to ſecure us againſt him; and the Rabble
<pb facs="tcp:64916:12"/>of <hi>Atheiſtical Epicurean</hi> Notions which have been ſo often routed, and have fled before the World, are now faced about, and afreſh recruited, to aſſault this preſent Generation. <bibl>Sir <hi>Ch. Wolſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi>'s <hi>Unreaſonableneſs of Atheiſm,</hi> pag. 37.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>A like Complaint we have in a late Judicious Philoſopher, who ſpeaking of the Excellency of the <hi>Platonick</hi> Doctrine, becauſe it draws off our Minds from pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Tranſitory things, to the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of more noble Intellectual Beings, further adds, <hi>Quâ quidem in re infinitum propè momentum eſt, &amp;c.</hi> i. e. <hi>which is a matter of infinite moment;</hi> for we are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with a Rout of Philoſophers, who contend that nothing but <hi>Bodies</hi> can be underſtood. <hi>Du Hamel de conſenſ. Vet. &amp; Nov. Philoſ. Praefat.</hi> The like you may find in <hi>Ludovic. Viv. de Veritat. Fidei, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 145.</p>
               <p>The Knowledge of Atheiſts, ſaith <hi>Van Helmont,</hi> wholly depends on a <hi>Brutal</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and they are unapt to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thoſe things which do exceed ſenſe; for that is the cauſe, why they exclude themſelves from the Intelligible World, <hi>pag.</hi> 348.</p>
               <p>And I find that the late Ingenious E. of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> came at laſt to the ſame Apprehenſion, <hi>viz.</hi> that, <q>
                     <hi>That abſurd
<pb facs="tcp:64916:12"/>and fooliſh Philoſophy,</hi> which the World ſo much admired, propagated by the late Mr. <hi>Hobs,</hi> and others, <hi>had undone him and many more.</hi> 
                     <bibl>See his Funeral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <hi>pag.</hi> 26.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>How far theſe Obſervations are perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to the matter in hand, you ſhall ſee more by and by: For my part, I deſire not to make any man's Opinions ſeem worſe than they are; much leſs to charge Atheiſm, or Infidelity upon a Gentleman, who in appearance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> diſowns them. You ſhall therefore hear him ſpeak for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <p>The Opinion which he undertakes to maintain is this, <hi>viz. That the Humane Soul is a material Spirit, generated, growing, and falling with the Body, and riſing again with it at the ſound of the voice of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angel, and the Trump of God,</hi> pag. 1.</p>
               <p>Hereupon he endeavours to perſuade us, that the Soul is nothing elſe but the inflamed glowing Particles of the Blood, called Spirits; <hi>which are,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the Active Principle of Life, Motion, Senſe, and Underſtanding in Man, and Beaſt,</hi> pag. 10. And hence he infers, That the Soul can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſubſiſt, act, or ſuffer any thing in a ſtate of Separation from the Body, but that by Death the man's Faculty of think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is certainly deſtroyed, <hi>pag.</hi> 2, 3, 14,
<pb facs="tcp:64916:13"/>15. And yet he owns the Article of the Reſurrection, and the laſt Judgment ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of God for the diſtributing of Recompences, according to the behaviour which men have uſed in paſſing through the Trials and Temptations of this World, <hi>pag.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>You have here ſuch a medly of <hi>Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rean</hi> Dreams and Chriſtian Doctrines mixt together, as is not commonly to be met with. The one part of his <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> is below the common Reaſon and Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Mankind; the other above the reach of the greateſt Philoſophers, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of Supernatural Revelation, I mean, the Doctrine of the Reſurrection, at the ſound of the Voice of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angel, and the Trump of God.</p>
               <p>The truth is, Our Author hath advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſo far into the Tents of <hi>Epicurus, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretius, Hobs,</hi> and others of our trifling <hi>Atomiſts,</hi> that it is a wonder he went no further; and who knows but he may yet be within call, or, at leaſt, that we may prevent others from being infected with the like Contagion?</p>
               <p>Let us now ſee how far theſe Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers and he are agreed; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. The Soul, ſays <hi>Epicurus,</hi> is certainly a Body conſiſting of thin ſubtil par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and at our diſſolution is diſſipated,
<pb facs="tcp:64916:13"/>and hath no longer the ſame Faculties, no motion, nor ſenſe, <hi>Diog. Laert.</hi> in <hi>Epicur.</hi> pag. 281, 282. The ſame you have over again in <hi>Gaſſendus</hi>'s <hi>Syntagm. Philoſ. Epicur.</hi> pag. 136.</p>
               <p>And moreover, <hi>pag.</hi> 137. <hi>Exortum ergo Anima habet, à quo uſque ut adoleſcit, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſcit que cum corpore, ſic tendat oportet ad In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritum, cum eodem ſeneſcens, ac ſenſim defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciens.</hi> That is, <hi>The Soul riſeth, grows, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cays, and falls with the Body.</hi> It is needleſs to tell the Learned, how much <hi>Lucretius,</hi> and <hi>Hobs,</hi> &amp;c. have endeavoured to cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate, and recommend this ſort of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy. See <hi>Hobs of the Kingdom of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Leviath. part.</hi> 4. <hi>chap.</hi> 44. and <hi>Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſendus</hi> himſelf hath too much encouraged it. Thus you ſee how far they are agreed.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs there are not wanting in our Author's Book ſome Conceſſions, which I think will be ſufficient to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw all that part of his Hypotheſis, which ſavours more of the <hi>Epicurean</hi> than the <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> As for Example.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>He would not be taken for one who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies that there are any Spiritual Subſtances, pag.</hi> 6. but rather ſuppoſeth that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels are <hi>Immaterial, Intelligent Spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> pag. 15. and in this I muſt acknowledge he is more refined than Mr. <hi>Hobs,</hi> who cannot
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64916:14"/>endure to hear of any Subſtances, but <hi>corporeal,</hi> and explodes the reſt as mere <hi>Phantaſmes, and Idols of the Imagination, Leviath. part.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 34. <hi>pag.</hi> 208. and ſo did his Maſter <hi>Epicurus,</hi> ſee <hi>Diog. Laert. in Epicur. pag.</hi> 282. where he endeavours to make us believe, that nothing can be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood as incorporeal, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a <hi>Vacuum,</hi> an <hi>Inanity,</hi> or <hi>Empty Space</hi> for Bodies to move in; and therefore, ſays he, they who ſay the Soul is incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>talk vainly.</hi> Now, thus far our Author agrees with him, that the Humane Soul is corporeal, but yet he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies not the Angels to be immaterial. And this, I ſay, is ſomewhat odd, if we conſider that the Soul of man is made to know, love, and delight in God as the Angels themſelves are, (and indeed what can they do that is higher than this?) yet our Author ſuppoſeth them to be <hi>Immate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial,</hi> but the Soul to be no better than <hi>corruptible matter.</hi> Surely it is much more rational to ſay, <hi>Ex operationum ſimilitudine colligi poteſt ſimilitudo eſſentiae: Anima autem vim intelligendi, &amp; volendi cum Angelis ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet communem, ergo &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>eſſentiae,</hi> as <hi>Alſted</hi> obſerves, from the likeneſs of <hi>Ope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ion</hi> we may gather the likeneſs of <hi>Eſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> &amp;c. which Conſideration will weigh the more with thoſe, who conſider
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64916:14"/>at how great a rate the Soul of man was redeemed by him, who took not upon him the Nature of Angels. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I muſt take leave to conclude with Mr. <hi>B. Nulla mihi obvia eſt ratio, quae pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibere videtur, ne Naturam totam mentalem, nobis notam, Angelorum ſcilicet &amp; Hominum, ad unam ſpeciem in ſenſu generaliore, quaſi in claſſem unam, benè redigam.</hi> Meth. Theol. <hi>part.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 134.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> He owns the <hi>Being,</hi> and <hi>Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> of the Deity, and ſpeaks with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence of our Bleſſed Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> He ſpeaks well of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and cites ſeveral paſſages out of them, which he thinks make for his purpoſe, and moreover is willing that the Point of the Soul's <hi>Immateriality</hi> ſhould be tried by their Authority, <hi>pag.</hi> 19. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I muſt ſay, <hi>(ſans ceremonie)</hi> if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to ſubmit to the determination of the Scripture as to the Soul's <hi>Immortality,</hi> the Appeal which he hath made is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than trifling Prevarication, <hi>ill</hi> becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Philoſopher, and <hi>worſe</hi> a Chriſtian. And beſides, if he imagine that he can prove the Article of the Reſurrection, as laid down in his Poſition, without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e help of Scripture, I think he would do well to give the World a <hi>Specimen</hi> of his
<pb facs="tcp:64916:15"/>Tranſcendent Sagacity in that matter; but if he fly to Scripture-Authority where it is <hi>on his ſide,</hi> it will juſtly be accounted a piece of <hi>Partiality</hi> and <hi>Impiety</hi> too, if he yield not to it, where it makes <hi>againſt him.</hi> In a word, If the Scripture may be Judge in the caſe, it will be eaſy enough to diſprove the former part of his Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>the Soul falls, or dies with the Body:</hi> And again, If he renounce the Scripture, he will never be able to prove the latter part of it, <hi>viz. That the Body riſeth again at the voice of the Arch-angel.</hi> So that the two parts of his Hypotheſis ſeem to mix together like Oyl and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. They want a <hi>tertium quid</hi> to unite them, which yet muſt be neither <hi>Reaſon,</hi> nor <hi>Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe things being premiſed, what I have to ſay, at preſent, upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſhall be digeſted into the following Method.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall evince by plain Scripture-proof, That the Soul of man is immortal, and doth not fall, dye, or periſh with the Body.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2dly,</hi> I ſhall prove the ſame by the Light of Natural Reaſon, for the convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſuch as will not ſubmit to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Authority.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:64916:15"/>
                     <hi>3dly,</hi> I ſhall ſhew, That the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable amongſt the Ancient Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers did aſſert and maintain the Doctrine of the Soul's Immortality.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4thly,</hi> Our Author's Objections ſhall be conſidered.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5thly,</hi> Something ſhall be ſaid to the point of <hi>materiality,</hi> and <hi>immateriality</hi> which our Author harps ſo much upon.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6thly,</hi> Some Directions ſhall be given to ſuch as queſtion the Soul's Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ity, that they may arrive at a certainty in this matter.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>7thly,</hi> I ſhall ſhew how thoſe, who believe the Immortality of the Soul, ought to improve ſo momentous a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64916:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Immortality of the Soul proved by Scripture.</head>
               <p>SO full and clear is Scripture-Evidence in this matter, that he who owns the Authority of thoſe Sacred Records, and yet denies the <hi>ſeparate ſubſiſtence</hi> of the Soul after Death, ſeems to be as incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with himſelf, as thoſe Philoſophers againſt whom <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> diſputes, <hi>Metaph. Lib.</hi> 4. who affirmed, That a thing might be, and not be, at the ſame time.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore under this Head make it appear, That the Scriptures do fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſpeak of the Soul as a Subſtance diſtinct from the Body, and capable of <hi>ſubſiſting, acting,</hi> and <hi>ſuffering</hi> in a ſtate of ſeparation from it; and do further aſſure us, That the Souls of good men ſhall be happy when ſo ſeparate, even <hi>before</hi> the general Reſurrection, and final Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Souls of wicked men mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable. For the proof of theſe things, let us take a view of the following places of Scripture.</p>
               <p>We will begin with the Account of man's Creation at firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:16"/>Gen. 1.26. <hi>And God ſaid, let us make man in our image, after our likeneſs, and let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hem have dominion,</hi> &amp;c. Verſe 27. <hi>So God created man in his own image, in the image of God created he him, male and female crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted he them.</hi> Chap. 2.7. <hi>And the Lord God formed man of the duſt of the ground, and breathed into his noſtrils the breath of life, and man became a living ſoul.</hi> Where you may obſerve,</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>That man was the Maſter-piece of God's Workmanſhip; or the moſt excellent Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all this lower World.</hi> And therefore when all things were prepared for his happy Subſiſtence, a Council, as it were, is held about his Creation, to ſhew us how much the Wiſdom of God is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played, and ſhines forth in ſuch a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who is an <hi>Epitome</hi> of all the World beſides.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly, <hi>He was made in the image of God, after his likeneſs.</hi> Let us therefore conſider wherein this Image may reaſonably be ſuppoſed to have conſiſted; and where ſhall we ſeek for it but in the Soul, which is the nobleſt part of man, and therefore moſt fit to be the Subject of the Divine likeneſs? And there you may find it, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the <hi>ſpiritual, intellectual, Immortal</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Soul; and partly in the <hi>holy
<pb facs="tcp:64916:17"/>rectitude</hi> of its Faculties. The former was the <hi>natural,</hi> the latter the <hi>moral,</hi> or <hi>holy</hi> Image of God in man. This was the health, and perfection of his Nature, ſome way due to it, conſidering the end for which he was made, though not inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable from it. The Fall defaced it, Grace repairs it again, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.24. Col. 3.10.</p>
               <p>It is therefore abſurd to ſuppoſe, that the words ſhould be interpreted of either of theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Natural,</hi> or <hi>Moral,</hi> ſo as to exclude the other. A Soul made of corruptible periſhing Matter, is not fit to be called an Image of the Immortal God; neither is it a capable Subject of thoſe Divine and Holy Qualifications, which all ſpeak an Immortal <hi>Nature</hi> in which they are implanted, and point at a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Immortality as their <hi>end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is another part, alſo, of the Image of God in Man, and that is the Image of his <hi>Supereminence</hi> or <hi>Majeſty,</hi> in that Dominion which God gave him over the Creatures. But this need not ſtop us being altogether diſtinct from the former (which are principally intended) and mentioned as ſuch. Man was firſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Image of God, and then had this Dominion given him. <hi>Let us mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> man in our image,</hi> — <hi>and let him have do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:17"/>The groſs Conceits of the <hi>Anthropomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phites</hi> I paſs by, though the <hi>Epicurean</hi> is as ſtupid as they, who would Circumſcribe the Deity with the finite Figure of a Man. See <hi>Creech</hi>'s Notes on <hi>Lucret. page</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>I only add, If it be Treaſon to impair or debaſe the King's Coin which hath his <hi>Image,</hi> and <hi>Superſcription</hi> upon it; let them look to it, who are not afraid to vilify, and caſt dirt upon the Reaſonable Soul, which was created after the Image of him, who <hi>accepteth not the perſons of Princes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3dly, <hi>It is obſervable, that the original of the Soul was different from that of the Body.</hi> The one was formed out of pre-exiſtent (created) Matter, the Duſt of the Ground, and ſo was a dead, unactive thing, till the other, <hi>viz. the Spirit of Life</hi> (or Lives, as it is in the <hi>Hebrew</hi>) was breathed into it by the Almighty. This was not edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>ex potentiâ materiae,</hi> but rather created immediately, to actuate, and inform the Body which God had prepared for it. This is <hi>Divinae particula aurae,</hi> ſomething nobler than the pureſt Spirits of the Blood, and therefore under no neceſſity of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, or being diſſipated with them. Which will further appear from the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count which <hi>Solomon</hi> gives of man's Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution
<pb facs="tcp:64916:18"/>by Death; <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Then ſhall the duſt return to the earth, as it was, and the ſpirit ſhall return unto God who gave it;</hi> who is elſewhere ſtyled the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> and <hi>the God of the Spirits of all fleſh.</hi> Theſe places do mutually illuſtrate each other, and confirm the Truth which I am inferring from them.</p>
               <p>There are many other places which ſpeak of the Soul as a Subſtance diſtinct from the Body. <hi>Job</hi> 14.22. <hi>His fleſh upon him ſhall have pain, and his ſoul within him ſhall mourn;</hi> though <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> (as cited by our Author, <hi>pag.</hi> 2.) counts it a great <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriety</hi> of ſpeaking, to ſay the Soul is ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Though our outward man periſh, yet the inward man is renewed day by day.</hi> It ſeems then that they do not both periſh together in the <hi>end,</hi> for if ſo, they would both together tend alike to periſhing in the <hi>way.</hi> We find alſo the Soul diſtinguiſhed from the Spirit, Heb. 4.12. <hi>To the dividing aſunder of ſoul and ſpirit;</hi> and elſewhere we find <hi>theſe two</hi> diſtinguiſhed from the Body, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.23. <hi>And I pray God your whole ſpirit, ſoul and body, be preſerved blameleſs,</hi> &amp;c. If you look <hi>narrowly,</hi> and <hi>impartially</hi> into theſe places, perhaps you may find not only a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Intellectual Spirit, and a Body, but alſo the <hi>material</hi> Soul, or Spirits which you
<pb facs="tcp:64916:18"/>talk of, that are the <hi>vinculum unionis</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, and the nearer Inſtruments of the nobler Spirit's Operations. But I proceed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.28. Our Bleſſed Saviour aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us, That they which kill the <hi>Body</hi> are not able to kill the <hi>Soul.</hi> But our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor would perſuade us, That the Soul falls, periſhes, dyes with the Body, <hi>pag.</hi> 1, 14, 15. How theſe will be reconciled, I am utterly at a loſs; <hi>Ipſe viderit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.1, 2, 3. The Apoſtle ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Revelations which had been made to him, <hi>viz.</hi> That he was caught up into Paradiſe, or to the Third Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and heard unſpeakable words which it was not lawful, or poſſible, for a man to utter; tells us withal, twice over, <hi>That whether he was,</hi> at that time, <hi>in the body, or out of the body, he could not tell.</hi> Whence it is plain, that the Apoſtle ſuppoſeth the Soul capable of ſubſiſting, and acting out of the Body, or elſe he would never have queſtioned whether it was not his own caſe. But how eaſily could our Author have ſolved this difficulty, and told the Apoſtle, Sir, You need not queſtion but your Soul was in the Body, <hi>for it cannot act without bodily Organs. It cannot ſee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Eye,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 2. nor <hi>probably do or ſuffer any thing at all,</hi> pag. 3. So true it
<pb facs="tcp:64916:19"/>is, <hi>That vain man would be wiſe,</hi> that is, be accounted ſo, <hi>Job</hi> 11.12. I wonder not that ſome of the Predeceſſors of theſe Philoſophers <hi>encountred</hi> the Apoſtle, and <hi>ſome ſaid, What would this babler ſay?</hi> Acts 18.17, 18.</p>
               <p>I might further add, That the Apoſtle <hi>here</hi> doth not only ſuppoſe that the Soul can ſubſiſt, and act <hi>ſeparate</hi> from the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but that it can act very <hi>nobly</hi> too; which will appear, if we conſider what Objects were like to be preſented to him in the Third Heaven, whither he was caught up, and what deep impreſſions he received from them, retaining the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thoſe things when he was <hi>in</hi> the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which, for ought he knew, were diſcovered to him when he was <hi>out</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21, 22, 23, 24. The Apoſtle tells the <hi>Philippians, that he was in a ſtrait be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two, having a deſire to depart,</hi> (or to be diſſolved) <hi>and to be with Chriſt, which</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is far better; i. e.</hi> it was more for his preſent perſonal advantage. And this <hi>departing</hi> he oppoſeth to <hi>abiding in the fleſh,</hi> which was more needful for them, <hi>viz.</hi> that they might be farther edified by his Miniſtry. Now if the Soul die with the Body, I demand, what doth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle mean <hi>by departing, and being with Chriſt?</hi> Did he not enjoy more communion with
<pb facs="tcp:64916:19"/>Chriſt <hi>before</hi> his death, than he can be ſuppoſed ever to have enjoyed <hi>ſince,</hi> if his Soul and Body periſhed together? And why doth he ſay, <hi>That to dye is gain</hi> (verſe 21.) if by dying he mean ſinking into an unactive ſtate? And why doth he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe departing, and being with Chriſt, to living, or abiding in the fleſh, if his Soul could not live out of the fleſh, nor ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive his Body? Again, I ask, Why the Apoſtle was in ſo great a ſtrait, as not knowing what to chuſe in this matter? Had he ſo little regard to the Honour and Intereſt of his great Maſter, ſo little love to the Service of Chriſt, and the Souls of men, as to queſtion whether he ſhould chuſe to live for the edification of the Church, or fall down into a <hi>dead un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>activity?</hi> Will you ſay, that the Troubles and Perſecutions which he met with made him weary of his Life and Work? The Anſwer is eaſy, Himſelf tells you, <hi>that none of thoſe things moved him; that he fainted not;</hi> yea he calls them <hi>light Afflictions,</hi> and had learnt to <hi>rejoice in Tribulations.</hi> So that in ſhort, you may turn and wind which way you will; either what the Apoſtle ſays here hath no tolerable ſenſe in it, or your Hypotheſis of the Soul's dying with the Body is abſurd, and unchriſtian.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:20"/>A parallel place we have 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, to the 9th, where the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the diſſolution of the <hi>earthly tabernacle;</hi> and moreover, <hi>verſe</hi> 6. <hi>While we are at home in the body, we are abſent from the Lord;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>We are confident, and willing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be abſent from the body, and to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the Lord.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 4. He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares Death to uncloathing. What ſay you to this? Cannot a man live when his Clothes are put off, and laid aſide? even ſo may the Soul when ſeparate from the Body, elſe the Apoſtle's Confidence in this matter was vain. What did you mean to appeal to the Scripture, or ſo much as to name it?</p>
               <p>The ſame Truth further appears in the Parable of the rich Senſualiſt, and <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> Luke 16.19, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whence you may learn the different States of ſeparate Souls after Death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But this is no <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> but a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</hi> and therefore it is abſurd to draw any Arguments from it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I readily grant, that there are many Circumſtances in Parables which muſt not be too far ſtrained, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in this. But yet, I ſay, it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to <hi>inſtruct,</hi> and not to <hi>deceive</hi> them.
<pb facs="tcp:64916:20"/>Let it therefore be conſidered, that either it was the common Opinion amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> (the <hi>Sadducees</hi> excepted, who were a deſpiſed Sect) that the Souls of good men are happy, and of bad men miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, when ſeparate from their Bodies, or it was not their common Opinion. <hi>If not,</hi> it ſeems not a thing worthy the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of our Lord to eſtabliſh his Parable upon an Hypotheſis contrary to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon belief of the <hi>Jews.</hi> For this would be more likely to <hi>prejudice</hi> them againſt his Doctrine, as built upon falſe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Opinions, than to <hi>gain upon them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if it really was their Opinion, that the Souls of men do ſubſiſt, and are hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, or miſerable when ſeparate from their Bodies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then, I ſay, either this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion was true, or falſe; <hi>if true,</hi> it was what I am pleading for; <hi>if falſe,</hi> this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable was like to confirm them in their Error, and ſo you reflect upon him that ſpoke it. I mention not the Conceit of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who will have <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> pointed at in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.5, 6. We read that <hi>Moſes</hi> died, and was buried; and yet long after, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17. we find that <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> appeared upon the Mountain talking with our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, when he was transfigured; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:64916:21"/>ſomething of <hi>Moſes</hi> was alive, and capable of acting, though his Body was buried.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.6. God ſtiles himſelf <hi>the God of Abraham, the God of Iſaac, and the God of Jacob,</hi> long after they were dead. And yet our Lord tells the <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducees,</hi> Matth. 22.32. That <hi>God is not the God of the dead, but of the living; i. e.</hi> their Ruler, Benefactor, and Felicity; a <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> which the Dead are not capable of, as Mr. <hi>B.</hi> obſerves. See his Notes upon the place. Therefore <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> were in ſome ſenſe living, <hi>viz.</hi> as to their Souls, though their Bodies were dead. And beſides, you muſt take notice, that the <hi>Sadducees</hi> denied not only the Reſurrection of the Body, but the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality of the Soul, as Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> obſerves, and that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifieth not only the riſing of the Body, but our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving after this Life, when the Body is dead: And ſo the force of our Saviour's Argument is very diſcernible.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.46. our Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends his ſelf-reſigning Soul into his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's hands, having before told the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent Thief, <hi>To day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe;</hi> and <hi>Stephen</hi> dying, prays, <hi>Lord Jeſus receive my ſpirit.</hi> Pray be ſo kind as to give the World ſome ſatisfactory inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation
<pb facs="tcp:64916:21"/>of thoſe places, and reconcile them to the Notion of the Soul's dying with the Body: For I do aſſure you, moſt Chriſtian Interpreters put another ſenſe upon them; and it would be a piece of Charity to undeceive them, if you know how; and when your hand is in, pray write down that the Apoſtle meant, where he ſpeaks of the <hi>ſpirits of juſt men made perfect,</hi> Heb. 12.23. If by perfection you mean <hi>ſleep, diſſipation, death,</hi> or <hi>periſhing,</hi> you muſt make us a new Dictionary, which may alſo tell us what your Notion of Bleſſedneſs is, that ſo we may know how to interpret thoſe words of St. <hi>John,</hi> Rev. 14.13. <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord</hi>— <hi>and their works to follow,</hi> or rather accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, <hi>them,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Vide Pol. Synopſ.</hi> And alſo what <hi>Solomon</hi> means, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.32. <hi>The righteous hath hope in his death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is eaſy to produce much more Scripture-proof to eſtabliſh the Doctrine of the Soul's Immortality, or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large more upon what hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready offered. But thus much may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for thoſe who are ready to ſubmit to the Rules and Authority of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to be tried by them, and <hi>with open arms</hi> to accept, and embrace the
<pb facs="tcp:64916:22"/>Truth, as our Authour ſpeaks, <hi>pag.</hi> 19. But there is no Truth ſo ſacred, no Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſo clear, which perverſe Wranglers will not ſeek to evade, and wreſt, though they do it to their own deſtruction. What can be more clear againſt the obſtinate <hi>Jews</hi> than that memorable Propheſy, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. <hi>The ſcepter ſhall not depart from Judah, nor a Law-giver from between his feet, until Shiloh come.</hi> And yet they have no leſs than Twenty ſix Anſwers for it. See <hi>Taylor</hi>'s <hi>Liberty of Prophecying, pag.</hi> 80. Thus the late Infamous Mr. <hi>Hobs</hi> every-where abuſeth the Scripture, with a Profanation not inferior to the <hi>denying</hi> of it. And ſo do <hi>thoſe of the Church of Rome, Socinians, Enthuſiaſts,</hi> and others. See <hi>John</hi> 3.20, 21.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64916:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The Immortality of the Soul proved by ſuch Arguments as are drawn from the light of Natural Reaſon, and the common Senſe and Experience of Mankind. <hi>The Firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE come now to the proof of the Immortality of the Soul, by ſuch Arguments as are proper for the convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of thoſe Perſons, who will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Authority of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and they are drawn either from thoſe <hi>Faculties</hi> and <hi>Powers</hi> wherewith the Soul is endued; or from the groſs and dangerous <hi>Abſurdities</hi> that flow from the contrary Opinion. Under each of thoſe general Heads of Argument ſeveral parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars will be neceſſarily comprehended.</p>
               <p>Argum. I. <hi>The noble Faculties, and Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities of the Soul, argue that its Original is higher than our Author is willing to allow of, and that its Nature is immortal.</hi> The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of any Subſtance muſt be known by the <hi>Faculties, Virtues,</hi> or <hi>Powers</hi> radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in it, and the excellency of thoſe Faculties by the <hi>Acts</hi> proceeding from
<pb facs="tcp:64916:23"/>them, which connotes, or takes in the Objects about which thoſe Acts are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant. <hi>Talis eſt cujuſque rei Natura qualis eſt ejus Operatio,</hi> or, if you will, <hi>Operari ſequitur eſſe, the being of things is the root of their working.</hi> As they <hi>are</hi> more or leſs noble, ſo are their Acts; and the Natures of all things are ſuited to the Ends and Uſes for which they are deſign'd by the All-wiſe Contriver. Thus from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences, Operations, and Effects of the Sun, we boldly conclude, that its Nature is more noble than that of a Clod.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>It is manifeſt that the Nature of the Soul is very vigorous and ſprightly.</hi> Its vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, active Power worketh <hi>ad intrà,</hi> both in the Operations of the Intellect, and Will; and <hi>ad extrà,</hi> as excited by the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perium</hi> of the Will. How quick are the flights of our Thoughts into the uttermoſt Regions of the Earth? How ſpeedily do they compaſs Sea, and Land, and, not content with ſuch a Circuit, ſoar aloft, and loſe themſelves in forming Notions of imaginary Spaces beyond the <hi>Coelum Empyraeum</hi> it ſelf, and by and by are got as low as the very Centre of the Earth? And all this in the twinkling of an <hi>Intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual</hi> Eye? With what facility, and brisk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs can it turn it ſelf from one Object
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64916:23"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o another; and inſtead of being weary, delights it ſelf in theſe ſportful Vagaries, which are as agreeable to its active Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as it is for Matter to lie ſtill, in a drooping ſenſeleſs, unactive State? Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that ſome good Philoſophers think that the Soul is conſtantly in action, without which they ſuppoſe the ceſſation of its <hi>Eſſential form</hi> would be inferred.</p>
               <p>And it is a great queſtion, whether the nature of Habits (which has puzled ſo many thinking men) lies not much in ſome unobſerved Acts, which the Soul hath <hi>intrinſecally,</hi> and <hi>in the depth</hi> of it, of which we are not conſcious, till ſome further Acts proceed from them, which take in more of <hi>Corporeity,</hi> and <hi>Animal Spirits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However, we are ſure, that when the uſe and exerciſe of our Senſes are inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by natural Sleep, the Soul is often at work, and its Reaſonings ſometimes as lofty, and ſolid in Dreams, as when we are awake, and, it may be, more. Whence an Ancient Philoſopher thought, that mens dreaming when aſleep, was an intimation that they ſhould live when dead. And the <hi>Peripateticks</hi> (as <hi>Aelian</hi> tells us, <hi>Var. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 3 <hi>cap.</hi> 11.) ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that the Soul was more ſagacious, and its. Apprehenſions more Prophetick in
<pb facs="tcp:64916:24"/>Dreams, than in the day-time when ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with ſerving, and caring for the Body. And the Stoicks, of old, thought, that Sleep was <hi>familiare, &amp; domeſticum Oraculum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However, 'tis evident from all this, that the Nature of the Soul is very active. Hence <hi>Porphyry</hi> argues, <hi>That for the Soul to die, is for life it ſelf to die, or for that which is,</hi> per eſſentiam, <hi>life to ceaſe to be what it is.</hi> And <hi>Cicero Tuſc. quaeſt. lib.</hi> 1.336. <hi>Nulla eſt celeritas quae poſſit cum animi celeritate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendere;</hi> and from this Conſideration, amongſt others, concludes it muſt needs be immortal.</p>
               <p>But there is one thing more under this Head which I muſt not paſs by, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſtrength, and ſolidity of Judgment which is many times obſervable in dying Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, notwithſtanding the languiſhing of their <hi>material Animal Spirits;</hi> now here I demand, If the Soul be nothing elſe but the purer parts of the Blood ſeparated, inflamed, and made lucid in the Brain, how comes it to paſs, that when the Senſes grow dull, and the Spirits low, Reaſon doth not always equally decline with them? If any of thoſe Material Spirits be more <hi>pure,</hi> and <hi>volatile,</hi> and ſo apter to be diſſipated than the reſt, one would think it ſhould be the reaſoning part, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64916:24"/>therefore that the decay ſhould always be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin there. But we find quite contrary, that the Rational workings of the Soul are, many times, rais'd above the uſual pitch, when the Animal Spirits are almoſt diſſipated and gone, or however ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely enfeebled. Which made <hi>Heraclitus</hi> ſay, <hi>That the Soul goes out of the Body as Lightning out of a Cloud, becauſe it is many times cleareſt in its conceptions, when taking its flight from this Priſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This helped to perfect the late Earl of <hi>Rocheſter</hi>'s Perſuaſion of the Soul's Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>When Sickneſs had brought him ſo near Death, and his Spirits were ſo low and ſpent, that he could not move nor ſtir, and did not think he ſhould live an hour; yet he obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that his Reaſon and Judgment were ſo ſtrong and clear, that from hence he was fully perſwaded that Death was not the <hi>Spending</hi> or <hi>Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Soul, but only the <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> of it from Matter. <bibl>See his Life, <hi>page</hi> 20, 21.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And, it may be, that which we call a <hi>Lightning</hi> before Death, ariſeth from ſome ſprightly efforts of the Soul (finding it ſelf looſening from Matter) ſhaking off its Fetters, and haſtening to be quite diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled.
<pb facs="tcp:64916:25"/>But this brings me to a ſecond Particular.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly, <hi>The Underſtanding is a very noble<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Faculty, eager in its purſuits after Knowledge, ſearching into Objects far enough remote from Matter, and above the Sphere of Senſe.</hi> It has a natural Bias and inclination to Truth as its object, and embraceth it with unſpeakable delight when it hath found it. Contemplative Perſons know this to be true, which makes them ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied in their Studies, and pleaſed with any diſcoveries they can make for the advancement of Knowledge. This made divers of the Ancient Philoſophers travel into remote Countries, that they might converſe with Learned Men, and glean up any Fragments of Knowledge where-ever they could find them. So did <hi>Apollonius, Plato, Pythagoras, Thales,</hi> &amp;c. and the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> came from the uttermoſt Parts of the Earth, to hear the Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon. Seneca</hi> thought that Man buried alive who lived without Books. And <hi>Lipſius</hi> thought himſelf on the top of <hi>Olympus,</hi> when he read <hi>Seneca<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ariſtippus</hi> thought a Man had better be a Beggar than unlearned, <hi>Laert. in Ariſt.</hi> 50. And what unaccountable delight had <hi>Julius Scaliger</hi> in <hi>Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ought
<pb facs="tcp:64916:25"/>twelve Verſes in him better than all the <hi>German</hi> Empire? So raviſhing are <hi>intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Pleaſures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Impreſſions from without are made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Organs of Senſe, <hi>various,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the variety of <hi>Objects,</hi> and hence correſpondent <hi>Ideas</hi> are formed in the Imagination, and laid up in the Memory. But there is ſomething higher, which ſports it ſelf with theſe Phantaſms, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds, and divides them at pleaſure, and makes new ones out of them, as of <hi>Centaurs, Syrens,</hi> little Boys with Wings, and what the Painter pleaſeth, which have no pattern <hi>in rerum natura,</hi> to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer them. What is it which, abſtracting from the individuating Circumſtances of ſingular Beings, forms univerſal Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>entia Rationis,</hi> inadequate Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe beings, and ſo rangeth the World of Entities under the ſeveral Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to which they belong, by obſerving wherein they agree or differ from each other, and conſidering their mutual Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies and Reſpects? What is that which withdraws the Imagination from attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Organs of Senſe, inſomuch, that a Perſon intent upon his Studies, is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as if h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in a Dream, though awake, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> not what you ſay to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Time goes on,
<pb facs="tcp:64916:26"/>though the Clock ſtrike near him? What is it that from ſuitable Premiſes infers certain Concluſions, and thus argues it ſelf into a firm aſſent to many things <hi>above</hi> the diſcovery of Senſe, yea and <hi>contrary</hi> to ſenſible appearance? Of which more here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
               <p>And what ſay you to <hi>Mathematical Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations?</hi> how far are they beyond the reach of <hi>Senſe</hi> or <hi>Imagination?</hi> The Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious <hi>Deſcartes,</hi> in his Sixth Meditation <hi>de Primâ Philoſophiâ,</hi> ſets himſelf to examine the difference betwixt Imagination, and pure Intellection, and thus proceeds; <hi>I can imagine a Triangle, as</hi> diſtinctly <hi>as if I ſaw it, and with ſome more difficulty a</hi> Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagone; <hi>but when I come to conſider a Figure with a thouſand, or ten thouſand Angles, I can form no ſuch diſtinct Idea of it in my Imagination, and yet I can eaſily underſtand that ſuch a Figure there may be, as well as either of the other;</hi> and ſo he goes on. Thus you ſee how ſoon the Imagination is jaded, and tired out, but the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing can demonſtrate the <hi>Properties</hi> of thoſe ſeveral Figures, and argue it ſelf into a ſatisfactory aſſurance of many Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Truths, which at firſt ſeem extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, and unreaſonable. And ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e it ſpends upon its own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and deaves Senſe, and Imag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> it
<pb facs="tcp:64916:26"/>and many of the Precepts of Geometry are utterly unimitable in the pureſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that Phanſy can imagine: And yet with what unſpeakable ſatisfaction doth the Mind acquieſce in theſe Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſo <hi>abſtract</hi> from matter, and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petible to it? And when it hath thus by abſtraction (as it were) <hi>unbodied</hi> them, it takes them for its <hi>own,</hi> and hath a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect underſtanding of them, and makes both Senſe and Imagination know their diſtance; and if they will be too buſy, it ſilenceth and controlls them by its Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Power; and purſues its ſearch with ſo much earneſtneſs, that it knows not how to give over. Hence the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Sciences are called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Purifications</hi> of the Reaſonable Soul. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimedes</hi> was ſo intent upon it, that when the City was taken, he obſerved it not; and when the Soldier (that killed him) came into the Room where he was buſy at it, he bids him have a care of diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Figure.</p>
               <p>It were eaſy to enlarge much on this Particular; but I am very confident, that no Mathematician, who ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders what hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, when intent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Demonſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> poſſibly perſuade himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> a piece of folly, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>le Wheat-meal,
<pb facs="tcp:64916:27"/>in two or three days time, ſhould become capable of ſuch Speculations as theſe. It were every jot as irrational, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the <hi>Comedian,</hi> That if the Blood of an Aſs was transfuſed into a Virtuoſo, there would be ſmall difference between the <hi>Emittent</hi> Aſs, and the <hi>Recipient</hi> Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher. <hi>Shadwell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But follow me a little further, and you ſhall ſee yet greater things than theſe. The Underſtanding is not ſatisfied with the knowledge of lower, or leſs impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Truths, but it riſeth up from viſible Effects to the inviſible Cauſes, and Springs of Action, and reſteth not till it come to the <hi>Ens Entium,</hi> the <hi>Cauſe of Cauſes,</hi> the <hi>Fountain of Being,</hi> and ſo contemplates him who is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>One,</hi> and <hi>Truth it ſelf,</hi> as <hi>Plato</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Crit. pag.</hi> 57. It conſiders its Relation to God, its De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence upon him, its Duty to him. It underſtands <hi>moral</hi> Good and Evil, Right and Wrong, Vertue and Vice, which fall not under the Laws of Matter and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It ſtudies the Nature of Spiritual Subſtances, <hi>ad intimas rerum Spiritualium quidditates penetrat, aut penetrare contendit. Scheibler</hi>'s <hi>Metaph. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>b.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g.</hi> 272. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding differ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſenſible Objects, as the I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om
<pb facs="tcp:64916:27"/>Senſe, <hi>Max. Tyr. Diſſert.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 9. We have many abſtracted Notions and Idea's of immaterial things, which depend not on Bodily Figures: And in what Subject can theſe Notions be lodged, but in one that is Immaterial? Therefore, I ſay, <hi>Si renunciatur tanto bono Immortalitatis, &amp;c. If we renounce the Immortality of the Soul,</hi> ſo great a good, <hi>we muſt alſo renounce our</hi> Wit, Reaſon, <hi>and</hi> Mind, <hi>by which we are Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal,</hi> Lud. Viv. de ver. Fidei. Lib. 1. pag. 147.</p>
               <p>And now let the whole Herd of our <hi>Epicurean Noveliſts</hi> (who cry up the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable power of <hi>Matter,</hi> and <hi>Motion</hi>) muſter up their Forces, and fairly deduce from the Principles of their Hypotheſis, a <hi>rational, intelligible</hi> account of thoſe Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Intellect, which are ſo <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> and <hi>abſtract</hi> from Matter. What ſay you? Can Matter and Motion contemplate the Glorious Attributes of God? Can a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Object be apprehended without a Spiritual Act? And can ſuch an Act be produced without a Spiritual Power? And can ſuch a Power be radicated in meer Matter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>r modified, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? Muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> be an Analogy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Object? Can any Eye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h is ſpiritual, and In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho is a Spirit, and
<pb facs="tcp:64916:28"/>Inviſible? Can Matter and Motion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template that Perfection, which excludes all Corporeal Imperfection? Is not this to act <hi>extra Sphaeram?</hi> Does not <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelf (in whoſe ſuppoſed Authority you ſeem to glory) tell you, That the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is made <hi>one</hi> with the Object un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood? which yet muſt be interpreted <hi>cum grano ſalis.</hi> No wonder if thoſe who have groſs material conceptions of their own Souls, be ſuſpected of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> it ſelf, as <hi>Epicurus</hi> was; of whom <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith, he did <hi>nomine poncre, re tollere, Deos, in</hi> word <hi>confeſs, but</hi> in effect <hi>deny a Deity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And why do you not anſwer Dr. <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingfleet</hi>'s Demands, <hi>Origin. Sacr. pag.</hi> 416. <q>Can Atoms diſpute whether there be Atoms or no? And whether the Soul be corporeal or no? Can Atoms frame Syllogiſms in Mood and Figure? Can meer Matter argue <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be Matter, or ſomething elſe?</q>
               </p>
               <p>Or if theſe Queſtions be too hard for you, why do you not accept the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge which <hi>Scaliger, Sennertus,</hi> and others have given you, and tell the World how <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Motion</hi> can produce even <hi>Senſe</hi> it ſelf, which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ior Nature? What poor cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ork do <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretius, Gaſſendus,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e reſt of your Tutors mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to
<pb facs="tcp:64916:28"/>ſolve theſe <hi>Phaenomena</hi> in a <hi>Mechanical way? Nil dat quod non habet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3dly, <hi>The ſelf-determining power of the Will, its Acts and Objects, do further argue that the Soul is of a Spiritual and Immortal Nature.</hi> This is that Faculty which chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, refuſeth, or ſuſpends its Acts, as Objects <hi>appear,</hi> and are <hi>eſtimated</hi> good, or evil, or of doubtful conſideration. This renders a man capable of <hi>moral</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Laws, with their annexed San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Promiſes, Threatnings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Faculty is the firſt Subject of Moral Good or Evil. The whole Frame of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. All Legiſlation, Judgment and Execution, Rewards and Puniſhments de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon it. And as the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purſues <hi>Truth,</hi> ſo doth the Will <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> and if at any time it willeth Evil, it is <hi>ſub ratione boni,</hi> under the <hi>appearance</hi> or notion of Good, in ſome reſpect or other. An inclination to Happineſs is eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to its Nature; neither can it be ſatisfied with <hi>ſenſible, material; corruptible Objects,</hi> but mounts higher, and reacheth forth after <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Divine</hi> things, and can never reſt till it centre upon the <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Good,</hi> the Bleſſed God himſelf. <hi>Feciſti nos ad te, O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>equietum eſt cor noſtrum do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec requieſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> Auguſt. Confeſſ. lib. 1.
<pb facs="tcp:64916:29"/>cap. 1. <hi>Thou haſt made us for Thy ſelf, and our heart is reſtleſs till it reſt in Thee.</hi> So, Lib. 4. cap. 10. <hi>Quaquaversùm ſe vertit Anima hominis, ad dolores figitur alibi, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terquam in Te. Which way ſoever the Soul of man turns, it can meet with nothing but grief, till it reſt in God.</hi>
                  <q>Hi motus animorum, at que haec certamina. —</q>
Now I would ask thoſe Philoſophers (for ſo they yet affect to be called) with whom I have to do, How they will explain the Liberty of the Will by the Laws of <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Motion?</hi> (of which more under another Head.) And if the Soul be nothing elſe but the purer Spirits of the Blood, meer <hi>periſhing matter,</hi> how comes it to paſs that material, corruptible Objects will not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy its Deſires? There is in every thing ſo great a tendency to union with its <hi>like,</hi> that 'tis become even a Proverb, <hi>like to like, ſimile gaudet ſimili,</hi> Earth to Earth, Water to Water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if the Soul be made of corruptible, periſhing Matter, how is it, that it ſo ſtretcheth it ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond its compaſs, and will not reſt in Objects like it ſelf, but muſt needs be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring after Immortality, and will not be ſatisfied with the Sphere which <hi>they</hi> have aſſigned to it, but is for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>rſing with
<pb facs="tcp:64916:29"/>the inviſible World of Spirits, and cannot reſt, but in the Infinite, Eternal Good. <hi>Certiſſimum eſt ſignum, &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <q>It is (ſays one) a moſt certain ſign that the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Soul doth excel all periſhing things, becauſe none of thoſe things can be found which will not in time grow <hi>vile,</hi> and <hi>inſipid</hi> to it: <hi>Alſted.</hi> Its Divine Tendencies and Flights ſpeak its <hi>Extraction</hi> and <hi>Duration</hi> too.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4thly, <hi>The Power which the Soul hath of reflecting upon its own Acts, both as to their Nature and Morality, is a further proof of its Spiritual, Immortal Being.</hi> It not only <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands,</hi> but <hi>knows that it does ſo.</hi> It contemplates and reflects upon its own Contemplation. It can form Arguments, and then examine and weigh the ſtrength of them. It can ſift its own Notions, and conſider what may be objected againſt them, and fortify it ſelf againſt theſe Objections. Thus it improves it ſelf in the knowledge of Truth, and then reflects upon the improvements which it has made. It can retire from its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with external Objects, and take a view of its own eſſential Powers and Virtues. And indeed we cannot know what our Souls are, but by theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, their <hi>circular</hi> and <hi>reflex</hi> Motions, and converſe with themſelves, which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:64916:30"/>can ſteal from them their own Secrets, as a Learned Man obſerves, —<hi>Smith, of the Immortality of the Soul.</hi> And if any doubt of this reflective Power, his very doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is enough to prove it, for he could not doubt, but by Reflection upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what ſay you to the mighty power of Natural Conſcience, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects upon our Acts under a <hi>Moral Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration;</hi> compares them with the Law, <hi>accuſeth</hi> or <hi>excuſeth, raiſeth Storms,</hi> or <hi>ſpeaks Peace,</hi> and ſo is in part an <hi>Executioner,</hi> as well as a <hi>Witneſs,</hi> and a <hi>Judge.</hi> How bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly doth <hi>Tiberius</hi> complain of the laſhes it gave him, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> imforms us? and ſo doth <hi>Suetonius,</hi> and <hi>Dion Caſſius.</hi> The like may be ſaid of <hi>Otho, Jugurtha,</hi> and many more:
<q>
                     <l>— Prima eſt haec ultio, quod ſe</l>
                     <l>Judice nemo nocens abſolvitur.</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Juv.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
Thus you ſee how Conſcience gives Men a foretaſt of what's like to come after, whether they will or no. Inſomuch that the greateſt pleaſures of the Soul, and its moſt piercing troubles, are from Moral Cauſes. And, what have Matter and Motion in them, that can rationally be ſuppoſed <hi>adequate</hi> to ſuch effects as theſe,
<pb facs="tcp:64916:30"/>yea, or ſo much as to the production of a thought? Debate this Point impartially and cloſely with your own Faculties, and (I had almoſt ſaid) think ſo meanly of the Soul if you can.</p>
               <p>Is it poſſible that any Man in his wits ſhould believe, that the Notions of Moral Good and Evil, the remorſe of a <hi>bad</hi> Conſcience, and the joys of a <hi>good</hi> one, ſhould proceed from nothing elſe, but the ſhufflings and cuttings of the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Parts of the Blood up and down the <hi>Cavities</hi> and <hi>Ventricles</hi> of the Brain? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be imagined more abſurd, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be that the World alſo was made by a fortuitous concourſe of Atoms, which is the height of Nonſenſe and Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy.</p>
               <p n="5">5thly, <hi>The Soul hath a power of rectify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe miſtakes to which an over-credulous regard to Senſe and Imagination too often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trays us.</hi> Thus Reaſon boldly concludes, that the Oar is ſtraight, though, when part of it is under Water, it appears crooked, becauſe of the Refraction of Rays through a double Medium of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal Tenuity; and that Snow is white, though when the Eye is affected with bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Humours in the Jaundice, it ſeems yellow; and that the Heads of our <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podes</hi> are as <hi>erect</hi> as our own, whatever
<pb facs="tcp:64916:31"/>our imagination <hi>obſtinately</hi> ſuggeſts to the contrary. Now, if the Mind was of the ſame nature with the corporeal Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, their Judgment would be uniform. Therefore, how much ſoever <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Motion</hi> may be concerned in theſe erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Impreſſions which are made upon our <hi>Senſes</hi> and <hi>Imaginations,</hi> it muſt needs be ſome nobler Principle in us which ſupplies theſe defects, and corrects the Errors which proceed from them. Can Matter and Motion make ſuch groſs mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes, and rectify them when it has done? This is to act above it ſelf, to do and undo, and is altogether unconceiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and incredible to thoſe, who will not be impoſed upon by an empty ſound of words. If you cannot explain the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Senſation it ſelf by meer Matter and Motion, how will you ſolve thoſe <hi>Phaenomena</hi> which tranſcend the power both of Senſe and Imagination? What is that in Man which will not form its judgment of things according to the rude Votes of the Senſes, but conſults ſome clearer Principle within it ſelf? Speak to the, purpoſe or not at all.</p>
               <p n="6">6thly, <hi>The Soul has a Power of reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and controlling the inordinate Efforts of the material Animal Spirits; which argues that it is a Subſtance diſtinct from them.</hi> The
<pb facs="tcp:64916:31"/>frequent Conflicts between <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and the <hi>ſenſitive Appetite,</hi> fully prove, that there is in Man a Power ſuperior to that of Matter and Motion.</p>
               <p>The <hi>material Animal Spirits</hi> are much concerned in the diſorders of <hi>Paſſion</hi> and <hi>Concupiſcence.</hi> But, what is that <hi>Regent Predominant Principle</hi> which condemns and checks theſe unruly Motions of the brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Appetite, and chuſeth ſometimes the moſt diſtaſtful things to Senſe, yea, and can give the Body to be burned for high and weighty Reaſons, notwithſtanding all the Recoils and Tumults of the Material Animal Spirits, and uſeth the Body as its Inſtrument to ſerve its own Will and Pleaſure? What can this be, but the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Intellectual Spirit, which is capable of ſubſiſting without the Body, or elſe would never ſo conſent to its Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction?</p>
               <p>But on the other hand, when the Soul of a Man is ſo immers'd in Senſuality, that it lets looſe the Reins to Luſt and Appetite, and forgets its own. Dignity and Prerogative, we juſtly ſay the <hi>Beast rules, and not the Man.</hi> And I believe it will prove at laſt, that the Soul muſt be accountable to its Maker for ſuch miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>management, and ſo groſs a neglect of its Duty.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:32"/>To conclude this Argument. If both the Senſitive and Intellectual Powers ariſe from no higher a Spring than Matter and Motion, How come theſe Material Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ſo to ſtruggle one with another, and one part of them ſide <hi>with</hi> Reaſon, the other fight <hi>againſt</hi> it? If you think all this is nothing elſe but the ſtriving of the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious Particles of Matter for ſuperiority and pre-eminence, you may think ſo ſtill for me. I am not at leaſure to fight with Shadows.</p>
               <p n="7">7thly, <hi>There is in the Soul a natural ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of its own Immortality;</hi> and by this God rules the World, who <hi>needs not, will not</hi> rule it in a way of deceit. The belief of the Souls capacity of ſubſiſting in a ſtate of Separation from the Body, is ſo apt to inſinuate it ſelf into the minds of Men, and hath been ſo generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and entertain'd in the World, that it may juſtly be reckoned amongſt the <hi>Notitiae Communes,</hi> or natural Notions, which are imprinted upon the minds of Men by the Author of Nature. 'Tis a Notion which hath endured the Teſt of all Ages, and ſtill prevailed. Good Men <hi>believe and rejoyce in it.</hi> Bad Men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſhake off <hi>the fears of it.</hi> Thoſe that are of contrary Factions, Opinions, and Intereſts in other reſpects, are yet agreed
<pb facs="tcp:64916:32"/>in this, That the Soul is Immortal. The illiterate Vulgar, who are guided by the more <hi>ſimple Dictates</hi> of Nature, have more deep impreſſions of this great truth, than ſome of the Learned themſelves, who by their laborious trifling have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputed themſelves into greater Ignorance, and raiſed Devils, which they have not the <hi>Wit</hi> or <hi>Honeſty</hi> to lay again. Not only the <hi>Civilized Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> but the Barbarous <hi>Scythians, Indians,</hi> &amp;c. have believed it: And what <hi>Salmaſius</hi> ſays up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another account, <hi>[de Comâ]</hi> is as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to the matter in hand. <hi>Quanto magis Barbari, tanto felicius faciliuſque Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam Ducem ſequi putantur. Eam detor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, aut ab eâ magis recedunt politiores Gentes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The moſt Eminent of the Philoſophers (who have taken pains to cultivate their Underſtandings, and to reſcue them from the miſtakes which <hi>Education, Example,</hi> or <hi>Inconſiderateneſs</hi> had betrayed them to) have ſtill ſeen Reaſon to ſtand up for this great Truth, except a few ſelf-conceited <hi>Epicure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns</hi> (who have been the ſcorn and by-word of all the reſt) and the <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducees,</hi> whom the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Writers reckon among them. <hi>Cicero</hi> obſerves, that there is in the minds of Men, <hi>Quaſi ſaeculorum quoddam augurium futurorum,</hi> Tuſc. Qu.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64916:33"/>lib. 1.331. <hi>A kind of preſage of a future World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, theſe Perſons who have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to run down the Notion of the Soul's Immortality, have not been able to avoid the force of it in their own Breaſts, nor to ſecure themſelves from the fear of what might befal them in a State of Separation from the Body, finding ſomething within themſelves, which bore witneſs to the Truth, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of their ſtupid Oppoſition. And what <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith of Atheiſts, may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to theſe Men, <hi>viz. That though in the day-time, and in company, they may with ſome ſhew of confidence deny the Immortality of the Soul; yet in the Night, when they are alone,</hi> ſibi dubitant, <hi>they are full of doubts about it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Giant, <hi>Epicurus,</hi> of whom <hi>Lucre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> ſaith, He was the firſt man who durſt fight againſt Heaven, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Natura rerum,</hi> was himſelf as fearful, as any man, of thoſe things which he denied were to be feared, <hi>viz.</hi> Death, and the Deity. As <hi>Cicero</hi> obſerves, <hi>de Natur. Deor. Lib.</hi> 1. and ſo you find him arguing in <hi>Laertius,</hi> That Death is not a thing to be jeſted with, <hi>Vid. Laert. in Epicur.</hi> 297. Whence the Learned Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> obſerves, How hard it is for an <hi>Epicurean</hi> to <hi>ſilence</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:64916:33"/>his Conſcience, after he has <hi>proſtituted</hi> it; for (whatever there be in the Air) there is (ſays he) an Elaſtical power in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that will bear it ſelf up, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the weight that is laid upon it, <hi>Orig. Sacr.</hi> 365.</p>
               <p>And 'tis very obſervable, that our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor himſelf, though <hi>pag.</hi> 15. he ſays poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, <hi>That by Death the man's Faculty of thinking is certainly deſtroyed;</hi> yet elſe where he ſpeaks more dubiouſly, <hi>pag.</hi> 3, 11, 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Minds of ſuch Perſons (ſays my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi>) are always wavering, and unſatisfied, never able to ſmother the in-bred conſciouſneſs of their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, ſo as not to have continual ſuggeſtions of fear and ſcruple.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Have you not heard of ſome ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who durſt not be alone in the Night? of others, who durſt not go to ſleep with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Candle burning by them?</p>
               <p>And it is further obſervable, how de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous men are that their Names ſhould be had in remembrance when they are dead, which is but the <hi>degeneracy</hi> of that nobler Inclination which the Soul has to Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality it ſelf. Thus <hi>Epicurus</hi> appointed in his Laſt Will, that his Birth-day ſhould be celebrated every Year, (<hi>Laert. pag.</hi> 271.) pleaſing himſelf with a vain <hi>ſhadow</hi> of Immortality, while he deſpiſed the <hi>thiag it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:34"/>Now I ask, If the Soul be nothing but ſome of the more ſpirituous parts of the Blood, and muſt die, periſh, or fall with the Body; how comes it to paſs that it hath ſuch forcible Apprehenſions, ſuch an <hi>indelible</hi> Conſciouſneſs of its own Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality? How comes this Notion to be ſo general, as you have heard; if it proceed not from the common Dictate of Reaſon, acting alike in all Mankind, though they know not one another's minds? and if it be from Nature, how can it be vain or falſe?</p>
               <p>How come theſe little Particles in the Brain to dance themſelves into a Notion ſo foreign to their Nature? yea, or ſo much as to ſtart a Queſtion about it? How comes that, which according to our Author's Notion (<hi>pag.</hi> 10.) was no better than Wheat-meal, or Malt the other day, to phanſy it ſelf immortal to day? ſurely it is well improved in a very little time. <hi>Si in nobis nihil eſſet niſi corporeum, &amp; cadu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, unde orta eſſet nobis ea dubitatio, aut omnino cogitatio de aeternis &amp; incorporeis, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis quam belluis? Omnis enim cogitatio (N.B.) aut ab objectis orta eſt, aut interiì<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ex nobis ipſis ſuppullulat,</hi> Valleſius de ſacrà Philoſ. pag. 74. But this brings me to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond General Argument.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64916:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV. Argum. II.</hi> Drawn from the many groſs Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities which follow from the Opinion of the Soul's dying with the Body.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg. II.</hi> THERE is ſuch a monſtrous Train of Abſurdities which follow our Author's Opinion, as renders it altogether incredible. If it were true, nothing but <hi>Truth</hi> could rationally be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred from it. <hi>Ex vero nil niſi verum. There is a concatenation of Truths.</hi> They are linkt one to another, and ſo are their Contraries. But I come to Particulars.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>If our Author's Hypotheſis be true, no man is the ſame this year (not to ſay this Week) that he was the laſt. Individuation, Perſonality,</hi> Rewards, Puniſhments, Rights and Properties, are ſtrangely overthrown.</p>
               <p>The Matter of the Body is in a <hi>continual flux,</hi> daily diſſipated by inſenſible Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (of which ſee Dr. <hi>Gliſſon, Charlton</hi>'s <hi>OEconomia,</hi> and eſpecially <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorii Medicin. Static.</hi>) and ſtill recruited by freſh ſupplies from the nouriſhment we take in: And the like may be ſaid of the Material, Animal Spirits; theſe are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually
<pb facs="tcp:64916:35"/>ſpending, and new ones made of new Blood: So that according to this Notion, our Author hath not the ſame Soul this Week that he had the laſt, nor perhaps the leaſt particle of Matter about him the ſame that it was twenty years ago. If he ſay he was born Heir to any part of his Eſtate, I muſt tell him, he is not the ſame Perſon, either Soul, or Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that was born Seventy years ſince, therefore he may either relinquiſh his Opinion, or his Right to his Eſtate, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he pleaſeth. Some more permanent thing than Matter, and Motion, muſt be fixed on, to make the Man the ſame. If you ſay, That ſome of the more ſolid parts of the Body, as <hi>Bones, Cartilages,</hi> &amp;c. may have remained all the while, and ſo fix the Principle of Individuation there. I anſwer, It's pity the World was not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with ſo improving a Notion ſooner, for we have not yet learned to call the Bones the Man.</p>
               <p>How much better were it to ſay with the <hi>Platoniſts, Anima cujuſque eſt quiſque,</hi> as <hi>Marſilius Ficinus</hi> argues in his Comment upon <hi>Plato</hi>'s <hi>Convivium. Quis uſque adeo demens erit, ut hominis appellationem in nobis firmiſſimam corpori fluenti ſemper, &amp; undique permutato, potius quam animo ſtabiliſſimo, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buat?</hi> pag. mihi 264. And to the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:64916:35"/>purpoſe ſpeaks <hi>Cicero,</hi> Tuſc. Qu. lib. 1. <hi>Cum igitur, noſce te, dicit, hoc dicit, noſce animum tuum, nam corpus quidem quaſi vas eſt, aut aliquod animi receptaculum: Ab ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo tuo quicquid agitur, id agitur à te,</hi> pag. 340. And to this <hi>Deſcartes</hi> agrees, <hi>Meditat. Quart. de primâ Philoſophiâ, Natura cogitans quae in me eſt, vel potius, quae ego ipſe ſum, pag.</hi> 22. So the Scripture ſpeaks of the Soul as the Man, and of the Body as its Cloathing, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. It was a notable Speech of <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <q>A man cannot enter twice into the ſame River, expreſſing thereby the conſtant <hi>flux</hi> of Matter.</q> The Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is eaſy. But I proceed.</p>
               <p>Only one thing more I would add un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Head; If the Soul be only the material Spirits ſeparated from the Blood, and refined in the Brain, and theſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits be daily evaporating, and new ones coming in their room; how comes it to paſs that our Memories are not quite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and confounded by thoſe new Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits which come in to fill up that vacuity which was made by the departure of the old? Can the new Spirits know what the old were, or did, which went before them? why do you not anſwer <hi>Plotinus,</hi> who tells you, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>This new Stranger-like Soul would<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> always be ignorant of what the
<pb facs="tcp:64916:36"/>other before it knew.</hi> And eſpecially tell me whence it is that Old men, after ſo many changes of their <hi>material Spirits,</hi> and ſo vaſt a number of Idea's which have been imprinted upon their Imaginations, will yet better remember ſome <hi>little</hi> Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their Childhood, than many <hi>later</hi> Paſſages of their more manly years, which are better worth remembring?</p>
               <p>To this purpoſe argues Dr. <hi>More.</hi> 
                  <q>The laſt Faculty (ſays he) that I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, is Memory, which is alſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily joined with the reſt in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Percipient; of which not only the fluidity of parts, but alſo their diſſipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, makes the Animal Spirits utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uncapable. For certainly, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, by reaſon of their Subtilty, and Activity, are very diſſipable, and in all likelihood remain not the ſame for the ſpace of a Week together; and yet things that one has not thought of for many years, will come as freſhly into a man's mind, as if they were tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted but yeſterday. <bibl>See his <hi>Immortality of the Soul,</hi> pag. 87.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2dly, <hi>If our Author's Opinion be true, there can be no ſuch thing as Moral Good or Evil among men:</hi> For the natural liberty of the Will is deſtroyed. If there be no ſuperior
<pb facs="tcp:64916:36"/>Principle in Man to correct the Irregula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of the Material Spirits, and their motions, Man is not a capable Subject of being governed by Laws in a moral way; and <hi>where there is no law, there is no tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> The freedom of the Will can never be reconciled <hi>to,</hi> or explicated <hi>by,</hi> the rigid Laws of Matter and Motion; but all our Actions muſt either ariſe from the fortui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous dances and friskings of Atoms up and down the Brain and Nerves, or elſe be neceſſitated by the irreſiſtible impulſe of ſome Superior Cauſe, and ſo there is a fatal determination which ſits upon the Wheels of theſe Corporeal Motions. And thus Mr. <hi>Hobs</hi> will have it, <q>That our Volitions are neceſſitated by Superior or Natural Cauſes, as much as any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in a Clock or Watch; and that it is unconceivable that any Act, or mode of Act, can be without a neceſſitating Efficient Cauſe. Thus he alſo affirms a certain connexion betwixt all our Thoughts, and a neceſſary Fate in all things.</q> If this be true, we muſt no more ſay, that the <hi>Will cannot</hi> be <hi>compelled,</hi> but rather, that it is <hi>always</hi> ſo; and by conſequence, the man that kills another is no more blame-worthy, than the Sword wherewith he kills him, both their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being alike neceſſitated; and the
<pb facs="tcp:64916:37"/>Dog acts philoſophically when he bites the Stone, but conſiders not the Hand that threw it. Neither is it to any more purpoſe to perſuade men to Virtue, than it would be to make a Learned Diſcourſe of Harmony to a Lute, inſtead of putting it in Tune. As you like theſe Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, you ſhall have more of them at another opportunity. If you ſay your Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is not ſo groſs as that of Mr. <hi>Hobs</hi>'s, I anſwer, it had ill hap to be ſo like it. Your words are, (pag. 2.) <q>We ſee in a Muſical Organ every Pipe has its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſound, and function, and the ſame Breath acts them all, and therein ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears a great effect and power of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Motion rightly fabricated and acted by the hand of Artiſts; and what then may not God do with them, and by them, when he pleaſeth?</q> So that if our Material Spirits be inordinate in their motions, you are in a ready way to make God the Author of ſin, by your Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy.</p>
               <p>It were much better to ſay with <hi>Cicero</hi> [<hi>Sentit animus ſe moveri; quod cum ſentit, illud únà ſentit, ſe vi ſuâ, non alienâ, moveri; nec accidere poſſe ut ipſe unquam à ſe deſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; Ex quo efficitur aeternitas, &amp;c.</hi> Tuſc. Qu. lib. 1.341.] ſo be it, we overlook not the Univerſal concourſe of the Firſt
<pb facs="tcp:64916:37"/>Cauſe with his Creatures, but in a way <hi>ſuitable</hi> to their Natures.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly, <hi>If the Hypotheſis which I am writing againſt, be true, no man can rationally believe a Future State of Retribution.</hi> You have heard already how Individuation and Perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity are overthrown by it, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence there can be no juſt room for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and Puniſhments hereafter, becauſe the Perſon when he died had not the ſame Soul that he had a month before; and why ſhould one Soul be <hi>puniſhed</hi> for another's Crimes, and that other <hi>go free?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Author indeed owns the Articles of the Reſurrection, and Future Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ('tis likely to ſerve a turn); but what he builds up with one hand, he pulls down with the other. He ſays, <hi>That Soul and Body, as they fall together, ſo ſhall riſe again together. Whereupon Judgment, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and Puniſhments ſhall enſue, according as men have behaved themſelves in this preſent world,</hi> pag. 6.</p>
               <p>But the difficulty returns upon him; Why ſhould that Soul, which, according to his Hypotheſis, was no better than a little Wheat-flower, Malt, or, it may be, ſome Cordial Julap or other, a few days before the man died, be judged and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for all the Faults which were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb facs="tcp:64916:38"/>long ſince? Will you ſay that all the reſt are paſt by? and that he is only accountable for the Sins of the laſt Week, or ten Days of his Life? This would be to turn the Solemnity of the Reſurrection and Final Judgment into a meer piece of <hi>Pageantry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, the Doctrine of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection cannot be known but by Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Revelation, and therefore 'tis an Article of <hi>meer Belief.</hi> There is much in it above the reach of Natural Reaſon, and therefore I ask, What muſt the poor Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens do, who know not that God has revealed any ſuch thing? Are they obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to believe, and prepare for a Future State, or no? If you ſay they <hi>are not,</hi> they themſelves will contradict you; and ſo will the Scripture too, which makes them inexcuſable for their neglects, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. and that they could not be, if there lay not upon them an obligation to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Duties.</p>
               <p>If you ſay they <hi>are ſo</hi> obliged, you will be ill ſet to prove it according to your Hypotheſis. For if the Soul die with the Body, and the Reſurrection cannot be proved by Natural Reaſon, how ſhall they believe without <hi>Objective Evidence?</hi> 'Tis true, they commonly aſſert a Future State of Retribution, and ground their belief
<pb facs="tcp:64916:38"/>of it upon the Immortality of the Soul, which, if your Opinion be admitted, is an unſound Foundation. Whence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that <hi>Natural</hi> Light taught them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things, than you have learnt from <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural</hi> and <hi>it</hi> together. And whatever uncertain hints may be found in any of their Writings, as to the Reſurrection (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived perhaps by Tradition from the <hi>Jews,</hi> or inſerted afterwards by the pious Frauds (as they call them) of ſome well-mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians) we are ſure they ſpeak ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidly, and diſtinctly concerning the Soul's Immortality.</p>
               <p n="4">4thly, <hi>Our Author's Hypotheſis makes ſuch a ſudden deſcent from the Angelical Spirits, to meer matter and motion, (denying all the active Natures that are between) as is abſurd, and not to be endured:</hi> Such Jumps as theſe are not uſual in Nature, which is wont to act by due and orderly Gradations, and not to take precipitous leaps from one <hi>extream</hi> to another. He would not be thought to deny that there are <hi>Immaterial, Intelligent, Angelical</hi> Spirits, <hi>pag.</hi> 6, 15. And how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable is it to ſuppoſe, that there are no other Spirits, or active Natures, infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to the Angels, and differing in their ſeveral kinds and degrees of <hi>Perfection</hi> and <hi>Virtue</hi> from each other, anſwerable to the
<pb facs="tcp:64916:39"/>ſeveral Operations whereunto they are deſigned by the Author of Nature? But that all the great and wonderful <hi>Phane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena,</hi> which we daily behold, muſt be reduced <hi>to,</hi> and ſolved <hi>by</hi> the ſuppoſed power of Matter and Motion.</p>
               <p>How much doth the Wiſdom of God ſhine forth in that admirable variety which is obſervable in the <hi>viſible Corporeal</hi> World? And are not <hi>ſpiritual</hi> or <hi>active</hi> Natures as noble as Bodies? Why then ſhould there not be a proportionable va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety in the <hi>Spiritual, Inviſible</hi> World? Eſpecially when we obſerve ſuch <hi>Viſtigia</hi> or <hi>Images</hi> of the higher Natures, in thoſe that are lower. Thus there is ſomething in Plants <hi>like</hi> Senſe, and in Bruits <hi>like</hi> Reaſon, and in Men there is ſomewhat which reſembles the Deity. Muſt we therefore ſay, that God and the Creature are all one? Or muſt we confound the inferior Orders of Creatures with thoſe that are Superior, and deny thoſe active Natures which animate the viſible World, and diſtinguiſh one Species of Creatures from another? While we cry up the meer ſound of Matter and Motion. <hi>Dubium quidem nullum eſt immaterialem Mundum eſſentiarum varietate intelligibilium, aequè admirabilem &amp; auguſtum eſſe, atque mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum corporeum videmus; ſed in quo illa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtat
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64916:39"/>Diverſitas nobis indicio certo non per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitur;</hi> ſays a Modern Metaphyſician. <hi>Ritſchel Metaph. pag. mihi</hi> 43. See alſo Mr. <hi>Glanvill</hi>'s <hi>Sadduciſmus Triumphatus,</hi> page 78. Our Author has told you what Dr. <hi>More</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> have ſaid in this matter, but for reaſons beſt known to himſelf, ſays not a word to anſwer their Arguments. And it is no contemptible Obſervation of the <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> which a late Author takes notice of, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>They ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, That the Unity of the World is ſo cloſely combined in all its parts, that between the <hi>Superior</hi> and <hi>Inferior</hi> Species there are <hi>middle</hi> Natures wherein they meet, that no Vacuum might interpoſe in the Series of things. And to Man they give the name of <hi>Horizon,</hi> as uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Superior and Inferior Natures together; in ſome reſpects nearly allied to the Bruits, in others to the Angels.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5thly, <hi>If our Author's Opinion be true, the best Men are most wretchedly deceived and befooled.</hi> The wiſer and holier any Man is, the more firmly he believes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth in the conſideration of the Soul's Immortality. Such will not be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that they ſhall ever be deſerted of that Free, Divine Goodneſs and Grace, which hath ſo often embraced them, but
<pb facs="tcp:64916:40"/>firmly believe that Almighty Love where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they live, to be ſtronger than Death, and more powerful than the Grave. They cannot imagine that their Souls which have been ſo often bleſt with the Irradiations of Divine Light, and the Warmth and Vigour of Divine Love, ſhall ever fall down into a <hi>dead unactive</hi> State. Hence many of them have died trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly, with raiſed expectations of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring immediately into a glorious and bleſſed State. How chearfully <hi>Socrates,</hi> that <hi>Philoſophical Proto-Martyr,</hi> received the Summons of Death, you ſhall hear by and by: <q>
                     <hi>Seneca</hi> tells <hi>Lucilius</hi> with what pleaſure he thought on a future State; and that when the Soul takes a view of the Amplitude and Glory of the heavenly Regions; <hi>contemnit prioris domicilii Anguſtias: It contemns the ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of its former Habitation.</hi>
                  </q> And <hi>Cicero</hi> brings in <hi>Cato</hi> crying out, <q>
                     <hi>O praeclarum diem,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>O excellent, happy day!</hi> When I ſhall go to that Aſſemby of Divine Souls, and depart from this <hi>Rout</hi> and <hi>Confuſion</hi> here below.</q> 
                  <hi>Plotinus</hi> talks Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phically upon this Subject, <hi>Ennead.</hi> 4. <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>ch.</hi> 10. where he tells us, <q>That <hi>purified vertuous</hi> Souls differ but little from An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Eſſences, and <hi>that little</hi> is their preſent Inhabitation in the Body; and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:64916:40"/>if Men were of this divine and raiſed Temper, they would not in any ſort disbelieve the Souls Immortality.</q> More of this kind you may find in <hi>Plato; Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rocles, Epictetus, Antoninus;</hi> not to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Raptures of many dying Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Martyrs, and others, leſt it ſhould be called <hi>Canting,</hi> according to the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of this prophane Generation. And now, what think you? Is it rational to imagine that Men of the moſt unſpotted Integrity, Wiſdom, and Vertue, in all Ages, have ſo wretchedly been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in a matter which ſo nearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd them, while a few <hi>dreaming, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Epicureans</hi> have been in the right? <hi>Credat Judaeus Apella.</hi> If you think that Goodneſs and Purity naturally lead Men to ſuch ſelf-deceiving hopes of Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, which Death will quickly defeat; you confound the Natures of Good and Evil, and contradict your ſelf in the ſame breath. <hi>Ni ita ſe haberet ut animi immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tales eſſent, haud optimi cujuſque animus ad immortalem Gloriam niteretur,</hi> Cic. de ſenect. pag. 202. <hi>Equidem efferor ſtudio patres veſtros quos colui, &amp; delexi, videndi. Ex vitâ iſtá diſcedo, tanquam ex hoſpitio, non tanquam ex domo, commorandi enim Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Diverſorium nobis, non habitandi, dedit.</hi> Ibid.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:41"/>Validiora ſunt Divinorum virorum praeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia quam aliorum,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Plato, Ep. 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <p n="6">6thly, <hi>If this Hypotheſis be true, Nature hath dealt worſe with Mankind, than with the Beaſts themſelves, by leading them into ſuch miſtakes as the inferior Creatures are not obnoxious to.</hi> I have ſhewed you before, how natural it is to the Soul of Man to apprehend it ſelf to be Immortal; and if this be a miſtake, it is ſo far better with the Bruits, which are not miſled by any ſuch fallacious Inſtinct. They are <hi>alive</hi> to the preſent, but <hi>dead</hi> to the future. They may play and ſport themſelves, and enjoy the Objects that are grateful to their Senſes, without being abuſed with the hopes, or diſturbed with the dread of what may befal them in a future State. While poor Mankind are divided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween fruitleſs deſires, and groundleſs fears of what can never happen to them, if the Soul periſh with the Body. The Swan may die ſinging, while the penſive Emperor cries out, <hi>Animula vagula blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dula quae nunc abibis in loca! Poor wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Soul, whither art thou now going?</hi> Unhappy Reaſon! which deals ſo ill with thoſe that poſſeſs and admire it, and worſt with thoſe who take moſt pains to improve it. Thus you muſt agree with
<pb facs="tcp:64916:41"/>
                  <hi>Cotta,</hi> That God did Man a miſchief by making him Rational, <hi>Cic. de Nat. Deor. lib.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p n="7">7thly, <hi>This Hypotheſis cannot ſtand, but upon the ſuppoſition of a continued courſe of Miracles to make it good, which is very <hi>abſurd</hi>
                  </hi> and <hi>unphiloſophical.</hi> Take his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in his own Words, <hi>page</hi> 10. <q>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry days experience ſhews, That Corn ground and made into Bread, is one of the ſtrongeſt ſupports of Life, both for Man and Beaſt; <hi>that</hi> concocted in the Stomach, is converted into Blood in the Liver, purified in the Heart, ſent thence by the Arteries into the Head and Brain, where becoming a Spirit, inflamed and lucid, it acts in all the Organs the powers of Life, Motion, Senſes, and Underſtanding.</q> And this is his material Soul. In like manner, <hi>page</hi> 12. <q>It ſeems one may venture to conclude, that Corn may be converted into a living and rational Activity, as being a proper nouriſhment for Man and Beaſt, and for their Bodies and Souls, one as well as the other; as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo for the Man who is a Contexture of both.</q> To this I anſwer,</p>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:42"/>
                  <item>1ſt, <hi>'Tis obſervable, that his Anatomy and Philoſophy are all of a piece:</hi> In that he aſſigns the Office of <hi>Sanguification</hi> to the Liver; from which Modern Anatomiſts have upon very good grounds diſcharged it.</item>
                  <item>2dly, <hi>If this Opinion hold good; the Graſs in the Fields, and the very Dust and Mire in the Streets which we tread upon, may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeveral refinings become a Rational Soul, and prove as wiſe as our Philoſopher himſelf, and diſcourſe as ſubtily of what it once was, when it lay trodden under foot in the Streets.</hi> That which the other day was no better than Wheat-flower or Meal, may now be making Syllogiſms, reflecting upon its own Acts, contemplating the higheſt Majeſty, aſpiring after a glorious Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality. Theſe things I muſt confeſs ſound a little aukwardly, but he has a ready way to ſolve all, page 18. <hi>With God all things are poſſible; and it ſeems he who made Matter out of nothing, can make any thing out of Matter.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>page.</hi> 14. he enumerates ſeveral Miracles; <hi>As of</hi> Aaron<hi>'s bloſſoming</hi> Rod, <hi>the ſtaying of the Waters of</hi> Jordan, <hi>the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication of Loaves and Fiſhes,</hi> &amp;c. Thus you ſee he is ſo conſcious of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his own Hypotheſis, that he is forced to fly to a miraculous Power to
<pb facs="tcp:64916:42"/>uphold it. This is a ready way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of Nature. But I reply,
<list>
                        <item>1ſt, <hi>Is not the ſame Almighty Power able to uphold the Soul in a State of Subſiſtence ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from the Body?</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2dly, <hi>Are the ordinary works of God in Nature, and his extraordinary miraculous Works to be confounded?</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3dly, <hi>Is it a valid way of arguing from the Power of God, to his Will?</hi> I readily grant, That he can do all things which are Works of Power. He can do all things which his infinite Wiſdom ſees fit to do; he can do all things that he will do. But doth it therefore follow that he will do all things that he can do? Is it not horrid prophaneneſs to proſtitute the Doctrine of the Divine Power, to ſerve the ends of every <hi>trifling</hi> Hypotheſis, falſly called Philoſophy? Do we not know, that ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily God works <hi>upon,</hi> and <hi>by</hi> his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in a way agreeable to the Natures which he has given them? And what is there in a little Wheat-meal ſuitable to the production of Senſe, or Reaſon, or Religion? It is the part of a Philoſopher humbly to contemplate what God hath done, and to admire his Perfections ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning forth in his Works, and not to lay
<pb facs="tcp:64916:43"/>down Hypotheſes contrary to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Senſe and Reaſon of Mankind, and then to tell us that God can, if he pleaſe, make theſe Suppoſitions good. Thus you ſee, that our Author's Philoſophy, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy, and Theology, are all alike ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd; and that he hath made Miracles ſo common, as will render them in a great meaſure uſeleſs for thoſe extraordinary purpoſes whereunto they have moſtly been deſigned; and that he owns his Philoſophy to be weak and impertinent, when he is forced to have recourſe to a ſupernatural miraculous Power to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64916:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Some ſubſervient Conſiderations for the further eſtabliſhment of the Doctrine of the Soul's Immortality.</head>
               <p>BEſides the forementioned Arguments, there are ſeveral other Particulars, which may juſtly render the Opinion of the Soul's dying with the Body odious to all Men, who have either the due uſe of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or any ſenſe of <hi>Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1ſt, <hi>This Opinion is highly injurious to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature, carrying in it a vile Depreſſion of that whole Species, or rank of Beings to which we belong.</hi> What an unnatural thing is it for a Man to abuſe his Reaſon, in vilifying and degrading the reaſonable Nature it ſelf; as if he repented that God had made him a Man, and was am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious to herd himſelf among the more ignoble Animals? <hi>Praeclarum autem neſcio quid adepti ſunt, qui didicerunt ſe, cum tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus mortis veniſſet; totos eſſe peritos,</hi> Cic. Tuſc. lib. 1.339. This is to bid defiance to the Common Intereſt of Humanity, and ſuch a Perſon ſhould be looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a Traytor againſt the <hi>Prerogative</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:44"/>and Dignity of all Mankind. And (which is more) it is contrary to that Obligation and Duty which we owe to the Common Parent and Author of our Beings; an ungrateful contempt of that Power, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Goodneſs, which hath given us ſo excellent a Nature; a caſting Dirt upon the Maſter-piece of the viſible Creation, and ſo a robbing God of that Honour which belongs to him upon the account of ſo noble a Production. Let us therefore be more juſt to our ſelves, more thankful to our Great Creator, than ſo bruitiſhly to abandon our hopes of Immortality, and baſely deſert the Common Intereſt and Honour of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Race.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly, <hi>The whole frame of this unmanly Philoſophy is built upon the most precarious, unſatisfying Principles imaginable.</hi> They beg the Queſtion all along, and then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend they have ſolved the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of Nature. <hi>Cicero</hi> told their Predeceſſors long ago, <hi>That they aſſigned Provinces to Atoms without proof.</hi> And <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> is fain to confeſs that Objection to be true. And Dr. <hi>Willis</hi> himſelf (in whoſe Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity our Philoſopher ſeems ſo much to acquieſce) rejects the <hi>Atomical Hypotheſis,</hi> 
                  <q>becauſe it ſuppoſeth its Principles with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:64916:44"/>proof, and is not ſuited to the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of Natural Appearances: <hi>See his Book, de Fermentatione.</hi>
                  </q> But becauſe theſe are but General Charges, we will deſcend to Particulars, and ſhew briefly what a knack they have at Philoſophizing upon difficult Points.</p>
               <p>If you ask them how the Soul comes to be ſo quick and active in its Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to turn it ſelf with ſuch won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful vivacity and readineſs from one Object to another: <hi>Democritus, Epicurus,</hi> and after them, <hi>Lucretius</hi> will tell you, <hi>That the Atoms prepared for this purpoſe are of a ſmooth Spherical Figure,</hi> (See <hi>Diog. Laert. in Democ. &amp; Epicur. &amp; Lucret. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Natura rerum</hi>) and ſo (you know) they muſt needs be very fit for quick mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. If you deſire an account of Senſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to their Hypotheſis, they will tell you of a <hi>vis Mobilis, Motus ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feri,</hi> and ſomething elſe (which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs they know not what to call) from whence it proceeds.</p>
               <p>If you would have the <hi>Liberty of the Will</hi> explained, they tell you, <hi>It ariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from a Motion of</hi> Declination, <hi>whereby the Atoms always moving downwards by their own weight towards the Center of the World, are carried ſomewhat obliquely towards ſome Point different from it.</hi> And this you
<pb facs="tcp:64916:45"/>muſt know is the <hi>Clinamen Principiorum,</hi> as <hi>Lucretius</hi> calls it. <hi>Ac nos ideo conati ſumus declinationem motuum aſſerere Atomis, ut deduceremus, qui poſſet fortuna humanis. rebus intervenire, ac illud quod in nobis est, ſive Liberum arbitrium, minime pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riret.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a word, if you ask what the Soul is; they can tell you, <q>It is <hi>Effloreſcentia Materiae,</hi> and compare it to the <hi>Spirit of ſweet Oyntment,</hi> or that it is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſome ſort of Spirit, they know not what.</q> 
                  <hi>Nihil enim est apud ipſos quod non Atomorum turba conficiat,</hi> Cic. Tuſc. Quaeſt. lib. 1.</p>
               <p>Such nonſenſical Gibberiſh as this, they call Philoſophy, and pretend to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate the great Works of Nature by it, and would needs (forſooth) be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Wits into the bargain, when they have amuſed their inconſiderate Admirers, by ſuch an empty ſound of unintelligible words.</p>
               <p>But can any <hi>Sober, Impartial</hi> Enquirer be ſatisfied with ſuch Anſwers as theſe? And muſt we let go the Doctrine of the Soul's Immortality, that we may fall down and worſhip that <hi>Image</hi> of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy which theſe Men have ſet up? No, ſurely we ought rather to be affected with a generous reſentment of ſo vile an
<pb facs="tcp:64916:45"/>Indignity done to the Nature of Man, and with juſt abhorrence to oppoſe ſuch wild and impertinent Extravagancies.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly, <hi>Such abſurd Notions as theſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Philoſophy it ſelf to the ſcornful Reproaches of every capricious Enthuſiast.</hi> You take the way to render it contemptible, and to open the Mouth of ſelf-conceited Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance againſt <hi>all</hi> Humane Literature in <hi>General,</hi> becauſe you make ſo bad an uſe of a <hi>very ſmall Part</hi> of it. There is nothing more common than for confident Ignorance to get into the Chair, and to paſs Sentence without hearing what may be ſaid on the other ſide, and ſo Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall be condemned as an airy Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, and thoſe that want it will be ready to run it down, leſt they ſhould be run down themſelves for <hi>want of it.</hi> I know the beſt things are liable to the greateſt abuſes; but ſome <hi>cannot,</hi> ſome <hi>will not</hi> diſtinguiſh between the uſe, and the <hi>abuſe</hi> of them. You ſhall meet with ſome that will tell you, That not only <hi>yours,</hi> but <hi>all other</hi> Philoſophy is vain; and if an impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Stander-by ask them how they prove it, They will alledge the vanity of yours, and infer an Univerſal Concluſion from a particular Inſtance. This (ſay they) is your Philoſophy, which teacheth us,
<pb facs="tcp:64916:46"/>that we have every Week a new Soul, and that at length Soul and Body dye to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. But if theſe Reflections fall into the hands of any ſuch Perſons, I muſt take the liberty to tell them, That they do not argue fairly in the Caſe; neither muſt they ſuppoſe that all Philoſophers are <hi>Vertiginous,</hi> becauſe (perhaps) in ſome the Material Spirits in the Brain have a <hi>Circular</hi> Motion. Neither is Philoſophy to be worſe thought of, for the phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick Dreſſes which theſe Men put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
               <p n="4">4thly, <hi>This impious Hypotheſis opens a Door to Atheiſm, Infidelity, and all manner of Licentiouſneſs.</hi> Our knowledge of the Spirits above us, muſt ariſe from the knowledge of our own Souls. Hence the firſt part of Wiſdom is truly to know our ſelves, that ſo we may underſtand our <hi>Duty, Intereſt,</hi> and <hi>End.</hi> And it is in our own Souls, as in a Glaſs, that we muſt behold the <hi>Image</hi> of God, which ſhould lead us to its great <hi>Original;</hi> and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why we know God no better, is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are ſo ignorant of our ſelves. Hence the Doctrine of the Soul is the moſt uſeful part of Natural Philoſophy, and ſo nearly connected with Divinity, that it may juſtly be reckoned a part of it alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:46"/>Therefore they who can once perſuade themſelves, that all thoſe noble Operations of the Soul (whereof we have been ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) proceed from no higher a Principle than <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>motion,</hi> are in a ready way to deny the Deity; or however, to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain very groſs and unwarrantable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of it, as the <hi>Epicureans</hi> did; and to conclude with them, that the World was made by a <hi>fortuitous concourſe of Atoms,</hi> and that God regards not the Actions and Affairs of Mankind, nor is either pleaſed with Virtue, or diſpleaſed at its contrary, as <hi>Lucretius,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Omnis enim per ſe Divûm Natura neceſſe eſt,</l>
                  <l>Immortali aevo ſumma cum pace fruatur,</l>
                  <l>Semota à noſtris rebus, ſejunctaque longe,</l>
                  <l>Nec bene promeritis capitur, nec tangitur irâ.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And ſo ſaid his Maſter <hi>Epicurus,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>The Bleſſed and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Being hath neither any buſineſs of his own, nor creates any to others; and is neither angry nor pleaſed with any man,</hi> Laert. in Epicur. <hi>A Notion more befitting</hi> Sardana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palus <hi>than a Deity,</hi> as <hi>Max. Tyr.</hi> obſerves. No wonder that Ill men are fond of ſuch Opinions as theſe, which ſo much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend their Wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:47"/>And as for Death, they ſay it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to us, becauſe all Good and Evil lies in <hi>Senſe,</hi> of which Death is the priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And ſuch Apprehenſions as theſe muſt make our Lives pleaſant to us, and take away the deſire of Immortality, <hi>Laer. ibid.</hi> And further, They would perſuade us, that the Fears of Puniſhment after Death ariſe only from <hi>Old Wives Fables, Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, the Immortality of the Soul is ſo clearly held forth in the Goſpel, that to deny the <hi>one,</hi> is implicitly to deny the other. And he who pretends to evade the Evidence produced out of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> (beſides the <hi>Old</hi>) for the proof of this Truth, is in a <hi>proximate diſpoſition</hi> to diſown all the great Fundamentals of Chriſtianity, which are eſtabliſh'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame <hi>Authority.</hi> And verily it is a groſs reproach to our Holy Religion, when Perſons, that profeſs it, maintain ſuch bruitiſh Principles as <hi>Socrates, Plato, Seneca,</hi> and abundance more of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens would have been aſhamed of. Which makes a great Divine ſuppoſe, <hi>That in this Age it is one of the Devil's chief Deſigns to aſſault Chriſtianity by falſe Philoſophy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And pray conſider, What can ſuch Opinions, or any that border upon them, lead men to, but Senſuality, and Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:64916:47"/>though (I verily believe) you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign not ſo? Are any men more likely to live as Brutes, than ſuch who think they ſhall die alike? You may tell them of a Reſurrection, and Future Judgment as long as you will, 'tis ten to one but they reply, <hi>as the tree falls, ſo it lies;</hi> and if once they can ſo far ſtifle Reaſon, as to disbelieve the Doctrine of the Soul's Immortality, after ſo much Natural, and Supernatural Evidence for it; I do not ſee why they may not, far more plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, deny the Article of the Reſurrection, and then they will let looſe the Reins to <hi>Luſt,</hi> and <hi>Appetite,</hi> and become the Plagues of Humane Society. And indeed 'tis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, that many of thoſe who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain theſe beaſtly Opinions, commonly live up to them, and are not of the beſt Reputation in point of their Morals. And 'tis no thanks to their corrupt Principles, if they be not all alike <hi>ſcandalouſly vicious,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.32. <hi>Let us eat and drink, for to morrow we die.</hi> A Proverb familiar among the <hi>Epicureans,</hi> or a reflection upon them in their own Language, as <hi>Grotius,</hi> and others obſerve. And therefore I muſt ſay, That thoſe Perſons who propagate ſuch <hi>Conceits,</hi> do diſcourage Virtue, but incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage Vice and Wickedneſs, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the publick Peace, Tranquility,
<pb facs="tcp:64916:48"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:64916:48"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:49"/>and Felicity of Mankind: And let them tell us, if they can, what good purpoſe can be pretended for the eſtabliſhment of ſuch an Hypotheſis, which can in the leaſt compenſate for thoſe Miſchievous Effects and Influences upon the Lives of men, which it has a manifeſt tendency to produce. Let the matter be well weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on both ſides.</p>
               <p>Indeed 'tis not to be wondred at, that <hi>wicked</hi> men ſhould put the <hi>Evil day</hi> as far from them as they can; even as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils would not be tormented before the time. But that any <hi>good</hi> man (except un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of Melancholy, or Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation) ſhould be fond of ſuch Opinions as theſe, is hardly to be ſuppoſed. What? Shall we fear to be made happy too ſoon? Shall a dead unactivity be preferr'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Communion with God in a ſtate of ſinleſs Perfection? <hi>But thoſe that are after the fleſh ſavour not the things of the ſpirit,</hi> Rom. 8.5. A <hi>Turkiſh Paradiſe</hi> ſeems more ſuitable to the humour of ſuch Perſons, than the <hi>heavenly Jeruſalem.</hi> And their pleading againſt a more <hi>ſpeedy</hi> admiſſion thither, argues their unfitneſs to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <hi>at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:64916:49"/>5thly, <hi>Our Author's Hypotheſis is directly contrary to the avowed Doctrine of the Church of England.</hi> Which I the rather mention, becauſe he profeſſeth himſelf to be a Member of that Church, and looks upon <hi>thoſe that diſſent from it as miſtaken perſons, pag.</hi> 17. Need I prove that the Church of <hi>England</hi> aſſerts the Doctrine of the Soul's Immortality? See the Order for the Burial of the Dead, where, among many other Expreſſions to the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, you find theſe words. <hi>Almighty God, with whom do live the Spirits of them that depart hence in the Lord, and with whom the Souls of the Faithful, after they are delivered from the burthen of the Fleſh, are in joy and felicity,</hi> &amp;c. Nothing can be more expreſs for the Immortality of the Soul, and its ſeparate ſubſiſtence. Now, I ſay, no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, who believes that the Soul dies with the Body, can declare his unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent to, or heartily join with that Church in this part of the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Office which I have mentioned. And as for thoſe whom he calls Diſſenting Brethren, if our Author's Opinion be true, they ought to diſſent from that Church more than they do.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:50"/>In a word, he will find it hard to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion any point of difference between <hi>ſober</hi> Diſſenters, and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſo important as that wherein he himſelf dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from them; <hi>or which tends ſo much to induce or encourage to an ill Practice, or Courſe of Life.</hi> See more of this in the Book of <hi>Homilies,</hi> Sermon the 9th, <hi>againſt the fear of Death.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:64916:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The Teſtimony of the Ancient Philoſophers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd for a further confirmation of this great Truth.</head>
               <p>THough the Perſons, with whom I have now to do, are commonly ſo full of themſelves, and overfond of their own Conceptions, that the Sentiments or Authorities of others are not much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded by them; yet ſince our Author has thought meet to mention the names of <hi>Ariſtotle, Dicaearchus,</hi> and <hi>Pliny,</hi> as ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to be of his Opinion, I muſt ſay ſomething to confront what is alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from them, that his Reader may not be amuſed with a <hi>meer ſhew</hi> of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</p>
               <p>This Point was often weighed in the Schools of the Philoſophers, the <hi>Academy, Peripatum, Stoa,</hi> &amp;c. They thought it worth their moſt ſerious enquiry, becauſe the common Intereſt of Mankind was ſo nearly concerned in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pherecydes</hi> is mentioned by <hi>Cicero</hi> (Tuſc. Quaeſt. lib. 1.) as one of the firſt of the Ancient Philoſophers, <hi>upon record,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the Doctrine of the Soul's Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality,
<pb facs="tcp:64916:51"/>(though he doubts not but others were of the ſame Opinion before him.) And <hi>Pythagoras</hi> was ſo taken with his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes about it, that thereupon he turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Philoſopher, who was before an <hi>Ath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leta,</hi> as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> obſerves, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 3. <hi>ad Volluſianum.</hi> But now (ſays he) we all ſee <hi>Aſſyrium Amomum vulgò naſcitur,</hi> refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thoſe words of <hi>Virgil</hi> to the Doctrine of the Soul's Immortality, brought from <hi>Syria,</hi> or <hi>Aſſyria</hi> into <hi>Greece</hi> by <hi>Pherecydes, Vid. Menag. Not. in Diog. Laert. pag.</hi> 41.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pythagoras</hi> was of the ſame mind with his Maſter; and the name of the <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goreans</hi> was ſo famous for many Ages af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that none elſe ſeemed learned but they, as <hi>Cicero</hi> obſerves, <hi>ubi ſupra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Philoſophers were wont to call the higher Region of the Soul <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the lower <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, The one the <hi>Divine,</hi> the other the <hi>beaſtly part.</hi> 'Tis reported of <hi>Plato,</hi> that he travelled into <hi>Italy</hi> to converſe with them; and how well he and they agreed in this Point, you ſhall ſee more by and by.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thales</hi> was of the ſame mind, as may be ſeen in <hi>Laertius.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>I mention not <hi>Zoroaſter,</hi> nor the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the <hi>Magi</hi> in <hi>Chaldaea,</hi> who were his Followers, of which the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> take
<pb facs="tcp:64916:51"/>notice; nor yet what is wont to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged from <hi>Hermes Triſmegiſtus,</hi> becauſe theſe Fragments of Antiquity are by ſome reckoned <hi>ſuppoſitious,</hi> by others, at leaſt, <hi>dubious.</hi> But give me leave however to add what a great Philoſopher of our own ſays,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>So if what's conſonant to <hi>Plato</hi>'s School,</l>
                  <l>(Which well agrees with Learned <hi>Pythagore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Triſmegiſt, and th' Antique Roll</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Chaldee</hi> Wiſdom, all which time has tore;</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Plato,</hi> and deep <hi>Plotin</hi> do reſtore)</l>
                  <l>Which is my ſcope, I ſing out luſtily.</l>
                  <l>If any twitten me for ſuch ſtrange lore,</l>
                  <l>And me all blameleſs brand with infamy.</l>
                  <l>God purge that man from fault of foul malignity.</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> More<hi>'s Pſychozoia, pag. 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> alſo, in his Book <hi>de Anima,</hi> ſuppoſeth that <hi>Plato</hi> derived his Sentiments from the Writings of <hi>Triſmegiſt</hi> in <hi>Egypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Come we therefore to that <hi>Divine Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher,</hi> and his Maſter <hi>Socrates,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whom we have more certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and in compariſon of them, and their Followers, <hi>Cicero</hi> looks upon all other Philophers as <hi>Plebeian</hi> (Tuſc. Quaeſt. lib. 1.341.) And brings in his greateſt Encomiums of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> with a <hi>(Platonem ſemper excipio)</hi> pag. 226. And St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:52"/>agrees with him in it. <hi>Auguſtinus Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem caeteris Philoſophis Gentium longè lateque praefert,</hi> ſays <hi>Lipſius Manuduct. ad Stoicam Philoſoph. pag.</hi> 19. But we will firſt begin with <hi>Socrates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What this Great Man thought, may be learned from his Admirer, and Diſciple, <hi>Plato,</hi> who in his <hi>Phaedo,</hi> and elſewhere, brings him in ſtrongly diſputing for, and aſſerting the Soul's Immortality. Where he ſhews, <hi>That as Death is the ſeparation of Soul and Body; ſo the Soul can ſubſiſt of it ſelf, when ſo ſeparate,</hi> pag. mihi 84. <hi>And that the readieſt way to attain to knowledge,</hi> in this life, <hi>is to abſtract our minds as much as poſſibly we can from commerce with the Body, till God ſet us free from it, and then we ſhall have a more pure and ſincere under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Truth,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>à corporis inſipientâ liberati,</hi> as <hi>Ficinus</hi> renders it, <hi>pag.</hi> 89. He derides the Childiſh fears of thoſe who think the Soul is diſſipated when the Body dies, as if they apprehended it ſhould be blown away, eſpecially if they dye when the Wind is high, <hi>pag.</hi> 110. <hi>'Tis impoſſible,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that the Soul ſhould periſh by Death, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that can die which is immortal,</hi> pag. 164. And ſmiles at his Friend <hi>Crito</hi> for asking him how he would be buried. <hi>I cannot,</hi> ſays he, <hi>perſuade thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, <hi>that I, who
<pb facs="tcp:64916:52"/>now diſpute, am</hi> Socrates, <hi>but he thinks that Carcaſs, which he ſhall ſee</hi> by and by, <hi>is I: But I tell you, I ſhall go to a bleſſed State af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I have drunk this poiſon, and this I ſpeak to comfort both you, and my ſelf. Do not ſay, when you ſee my</hi> Body <hi>laid out, burnt, or buried, that</hi> it <hi>is</hi> Socrates. Thus that Venerable Old man conquered the Fears of Death by the hopes of a Bleſſed Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality; and drank the fatal Potion without any <hi>obſervable</hi> diſturbance of Mind, or change of Countenance, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for an happy paſſage out of this Life into a better. But I muſt not tranſlate the whole Dialogue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plato</hi> ſpeaks often of the puniſhments of Wicked men after Death, and tells us in his <hi>Timaeus,</hi> That <hi>the Soul of a good man ſhall be kindly received by his Creator, but the Soul of a wicked man ſhall be caſt into Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The truth is, the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> have impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Doctrine of the Soul's Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity better than many of our own Writers (notwithſtanding their greater helps) have done; though ſometimes they ſpeak too high, as if they would even deify the Soul, as do ſome of the <hi>Stoicks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plotinus</hi> diſcourſeth excellently upon this Subject, and ſhews, that if we would ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly view the Soul in its own <hi>naked eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence;</hi> we ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> doubt of its Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.
<pb facs="tcp:64916:53"/>
                  <q>Let a man (ſays he) contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate himſelf in his own <hi>pure,</hi> and <hi>truly Intellectual Nature,</hi> diveſting it of all that is alien to it, and he will certainly know that it is immortal. He will then obſerve, that his Underſtanding is not properly directed to things <hi>ſenſible,</hi> and <hi>mortal,</hi> but by an <hi>eternal Virtue</hi> doth contemplate <hi>Eternal,</hi> and <hi>Intelligible Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> and becomes, as it were, an <hi>Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible lucid World</hi> to it ſelf.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And again he tells us, <q>That by how much the Soul is more abſtracted from the Senſes, by ſo much it reaſons bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; ſo that when it ſhall be wholly ſeparate from the Body, it will know <hi>intuitively,</hi> without elaborate Ratioci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations: That now it deliberates when it doubts, it doubts when 'tis hindred by the Body, but will neither doubt nor deliberate when free from the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but will comprehend the Truth without any heſitation. <bibl>See his <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neads,</hi> and elſewhere.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maximus Tyrius,</hi> Diſſertat. 41. handles that Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>Whether the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of the Soul or Body be more grievous; and tells us, That degenerate Souls are buried in their Bodies like In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſects in their Holes, and are in love with thoſe lurking Places<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 495.</bibl>
                  </q> And
<pb facs="tcp:64916:53"/>withal, <q>That the health of the Body is but <hi>uncertain,</hi> and <hi>temporary,</hi> that of the Soul <hi>ſolid</hi> and <hi>immortal,</hi> 
                     <bibl>pag. 491.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>It were eaſy to mention more of the <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> who all, to a man, maintain the Immortality of the Soul. But I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Stoicks</hi> ſay, That the Souls of Good men ſeparated from their Bodies are <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes,</hi> as <hi>Laertius</hi> informs us in <hi>Zenon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſays, That <hi>they</hi> call all ſeparate Souls Heroes <hi>promiſcuouſly,</hi> and ſo diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh Heroes into <hi>good</hi> and <hi>bad.</hi> De placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Philoſophorum, lib. 1. cap. 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epictetus</hi> calls the Soul of man <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, near a-kin to God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antoninus</hi> ſtyles the Soul, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And in his 9th Book, Sect. 39. — <hi>Wilt thou ſay to thy mind, thou art dead, or become like a Beaſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaks too high. <hi>Quid aliud vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas, &amp;c. What will you call the Soul but a</hi> Deity <hi>dwelling in an Humane Body?</hi> And perhaps ſuch boldneſs was one Original of Heathen Idolatry. And elſewhere —<hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ſi propriam ejus Originem aſpexeris, &amp;c. The Soul, if you conſider its true Original, deſcends from that heavenly Spirit.</hi> Surſum Animum, &amp;c. <hi>Its beginnings call it</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
<pb facs="tcp:64916:54"/>
                  <hi>there Eternal Reſt remains for it.</hi> And comforting <hi>Martia</hi> concerning her dead Son, <hi>Ipſe quidem aeternus, he is Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and in a better State now, than he was before. The Body is the Priſon of the Soul. The Soul it ſelf is ſacred, and eternal. Happy is thy Son, O Martia, who being dead, knows ſuch things as theſe.</hi> — <hi>Nec eſt Ratio aliud quam in corpus pars Divini Spiritùs merſa.</hi> Idem.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſays, That the Providence of God, and the Immortality of the Soul, are ſo connected, that the one neceſſarily follows the other; <hi>de ſerâ Numinis vindictâ.</hi> And therefore, by the way, <hi>Epicurus</hi> made <hi>thorough-work</hi> in denying both.</p>
               <p>Come we now to <hi>Cicero,</hi> a <hi>moderate, middle-way Philoſopher.</hi> He diſputes at large for the Immortality of the Soul, in the Firſt Book of his <hi>Tuſc. Quaeſt. de contemnen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dâ Morte,</hi> as alſo in his Dialogue <hi>de Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctute, &amp;c.</hi> I will cite ſome Paſſages out of him, to the ſhame of thoſe Chriſtians who ſtand in need of ſuch Inſtructions from an Heathen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tu cum tibi, ſive Deus, &amp;c. Wilt thou (when God, or Nature hath given thee a Soul, than which nothing is more excellent and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine) ſo debaſe thy ſelf as to ſuppoſe that there is no difference between thee and a Beaſt?</hi> Cic. Paradox. pag. 217.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:54"/>
                  <hi>Ii vivunt qui,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Theſe Men live who are eſcaped from the Priſon of the Body, but that which you call Life is Death,</hi> De Somn. Scip. 233. <hi>Haec Coeleſtia ſemper ſpectato, illa Humana contemnito,</hi> Ibid. <hi>Reckon with thy ſelf that thou art not Mortal, but only thy Body; the</hi> Mind <hi>is the Man, and not that</hi> Bodily Figure <hi>which you can point as with your Finger,</hi> Ibid.</p>
               <p>And to the ſame purpoſe he brings in that of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> mention'd by <hi>Xenophon:</hi> I could never perſwade my ſelf that our Souls live <hi>in</hi> the Body, and dye when they go <hi>out</hi> of it. <hi>Nec vero tum animum eſſe inſipientem cum ex inſipienti corpore eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſſet, ſed cum omni admiſtione corporis libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus, purus &amp; integer eſſe caepiſſet, tum eſſe Sapientem.</hi> This is purely <hi>Platonick, De Senect.</hi> 211.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Except God deliver you from this Priſon of the Body, you can never come to Heaven.</hi> Idem.</p>
               <p>And elſewhere he argues, from the Worſhip which was paid to their departed <hi>Heroes, That the Souls of all Men are</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, <hi>but the Souls of good Men</hi> Divine, de Legib.</p>
               <p>Alſo Tuſc. lib. 1. <hi>Ipſi illi Majorum Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium Dii, qui habentur, hinc à nobis perfecti in Coelum reperientur,</hi> pag. 329.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:55"/>And ſo infinitely fond is he of this Opinion, that he thus concludes, <hi>de Senect. pag.</hi> 213. <hi>Quod ſi in hoc erro,</hi> &amp;c. If in this I be miſtaken, that I believe the Souls of Men immortal, I am willingly miſtaken. Nor will I ſuffer this Error, in which I am delighted, to be extorted from me as long as I live. But if after Death I ſhall have no Senſe, as ſome <hi>diminutive</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers think, I fear not leſt thoſe dead Philoſophers ſhould deride my Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</p>
               <p>In a word, both <hi>Cicero, Seneca,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> and <hi>Stoicks,</hi> ſpeak of the Soul, as if it were an <hi>Incarnate Deity.</hi> That it has many bright <hi>Reſemblances</hi> of God ſtampt upon it. <hi>Deum te ſcito eſſe,</hi> Somn. Scip. Becauſe as the Great God rules the World, ſo thy Soul rules and governs thy Body, as an inferior kind of Deity.</p>
               <p>It muſt indeed be acknowledged, that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſpeaks ſometimes dubiouſly, and is not conſiſtent with himſelf in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But his greateſt Admirers have ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally believ'd it. And ſome of them take it ill that any ſhould queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Maſter was of the ſame mind.</p>
               <p>However the Authority of that Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher needs not much to move us, ſince
<pb facs="tcp:64916:55"/>he is alſo inconſiſtent with himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Deity, as <hi>Lactant.</hi> obſerves. And again, <hi>Ariſtoteles Deum nec coluit, nec curavit.</hi> See more to the ſame purpoſe in <hi>Lipſ. Manuduct. ad Stoic. Philoſ. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs there are not wanting, even in him, ſome fair acknowledgments of this great Truth in his <hi>lucid Intervals.</hi> He confeſſeth the Soul is ſomething di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the Elements, and makes it to be <hi>quintam quandam Naturam.</hi> And the like they ſpeak concerning the matter of the Heavens, which yet the <hi>Peripate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> look not upon as corruptible.</p>
               <p>In his Book, <hi>de Generatione Animal. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, that the Rational or Intellectual Soul only enter from without, as being only of a nature purely Divine; with whoſe Actions, the Actions of this groſs Body have no Communication. Here he ſpeaks like an Orthodox Scholar of his excellent Maſter <hi>Plato,</hi> to whoſe footſteps the cloſer he keeps, the leſs he ever wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from the Truth. <hi>Dr.</hi> More <hi>Immort. Soul, page</hi> 115.</p>
               <p>Elſewhere he ſays, That the mind is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an impaſſible thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Xenocrates</hi> is fully of the ſame mind, That all Souls are Immortal, and that he
<pb facs="tcp:64916:56"/>who lives piouſly and holily on Earth, ſhall certainly be bleſſed in a future State, and ſhall enjoy more <hi>pure</hi> pleaſures, than he was capable of in this Priſon of the Body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antiſthenes,</hi> from whom were derived both the <hi>Cynicks</hi> and <hi>Stoicks,</hi> tells the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians,</hi> glorying, That they ſprung from the Earth; that they were no more noble than Snails and Locuſts. He exhorts to Piety and Juſtice, as the way to Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality. — <hi>Ejuſmodi ſibi viaticum dicebat comparare oportere, quod Naufragium faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enti ſimul enatare poſſet.</hi> And amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other things, he wrote <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> concerning the <hi>Inviſible State, Laert. in Antiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I mention not the <hi>Gymnoſophiſts, Brach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, Druids,</hi> &amp;c. What the Poets, both <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> held in this matter, is obvious even to School-Boys. The <hi>Ely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian Fields, the Infernal Judges, the Torments of Hell,</hi> whereof they ſpeak, are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Atteſtations to this great Truth.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee how generally the belief of the Immortality of the Soul obtain'd among the Ancient <hi>Ethnicks;</hi> and ſhall any one who profeſſeth to believe the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, deny it? Who would not ſay, <hi>Sit anima mea cum Philoſophis:</hi> I mean, rather than with ſuch Chriſtians as theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:56"/>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Some of the Philoſophers whom you mention, as <hi>Cicero, Seneca,</hi> and even <hi>Socrates</hi> himſelf, ſpeak ſometimes doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully concerning the Immortality of the Soul.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> So much the more reaſon have we to be thankful for that clearer light, by which <hi>Life and Immortality</hi> are ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet before us. But yet you muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, it was only a <hi>certainty</hi> which theſe Philoſophers profeſſed to want, and not a <hi>probability,</hi> or Opinion that it was true. As for <hi>Cicero,</hi> he ſays he dares ſwear the Soul is Divine, <hi>Tuſc. lib.</hi> 1.343. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> often aſſerts its Immortality. And ſo did <hi>Socrates,</hi> when he had to do with ſuch as were capable of receiving and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding that Doctrine, as has been already proved. And beſides, ſuch was the modeſty of that Philoſopher, that he was not wont to be poſitive in his Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but ſtill, upon all occaſions, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his Ignorance.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Epicureans, Cicero</hi> tell us, That all Learned Men contemned them. And <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſays, <hi>Quod ipſi Philoſophi Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Porcum nominaverunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> declares, That <hi>Lucretius</hi> wrote his Poems in the <hi>Intervals of Madneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your Friend, <hi>Dicaearchus,</hi> is particularly <hi>derided</hi> by <hi>Cicero</hi> himſelf, <hi>Tuſc.</hi> 335.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:57"/>I might eaſily mention many more of the Sayings of Ancient Philoſophers, which further hold forth their belief of the Soul's Immortality.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> was ſo intent upon his Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical Contemplations, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded not the Affairs of the Publick; and when one asked him. — <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>Have you no care of your Country? Yes,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>the greateſt care of all,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> — Pointing towards Heaven, <hi>Laert. pag.</hi> 34.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thraſeas</hi> ſaid, <hi>Nero</hi> might kill him, but could not deſtroy him. And the like ſaid <hi>Socrates</hi> long before, concerning his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anaxarchus</hi> told the Tyrant, <hi>You may break in pieces the Priſon of</hi> Anaxarchus, himſelf <hi>you cannot hurt,</hi> Laert. 252.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epicarmus,</hi> as cited by <hi>Clemens Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinus,</hi> ſays, <hi>If thou be a good Man, Death cannot hurt thee. Thy Spirit will live happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64916:57"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Our Author's Objections conſidered and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</head>
               <p>THAT our Philoſopher may not think himſelf ſlighted, I am obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, in civility, to take ſome notice of his Objections, (ſuch as they are) though ſufficiently anſwered in what hath been already ſaid.</p>
               <p>Object. 1. <hi>The Brutes act ſenſibly and knowingly by a</hi> Material <hi>Spirit;</hi> ergo, <hi>Man may perform all his Natural Functions by the means of a like Spirit,</hi> page 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. As for the Nature of <hi>Matter,</hi> I ſhall ſhew you by and by, how little it is underſtood by the wiſeſt of you all; and that while you are talking ſo confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently concerning it, you do but wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle in the dark about you know not what.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I cannot but obſerve, how poorly you ſhift off the moſt difficult part of your Work. In the firſt Page we are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countered with a daring Aſſertion, <hi>viz. That the Soul falls with the Body.</hi> But if we ſeek for proof, (as 'tis all the reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:64916:58"/>in the world we ſhould) there is ſcarce ſo much as a <hi>ſhadow</hi> of it. — <hi>Parturiunt Montes.</hi>— Not one of the Arguments which have been uſed both by Ancient and Modern Philoſophers, and Divines, is anſwered. Perhaps they were not worth taking notice of by ſo tranſcendent a Genius. Did you expect that your <hi>bare Word</hi> muſt paſs for an <hi>Anſwer?</hi> or that any Man of Brains would be amuſed with two or three obſcure Quotations out of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Pliny?</hi> You were not born ſoon enough, thus to impoſe upon Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. <hi>Ipſe dixit</hi> is quite out of doors.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As for the Souls of Brutes, you ſay, they are Material, and take it for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that they are Mortal; from whence you would infer that the Soul of Man is ſo too. But have you well conſidered the Anſwers which have been given to this Objection by many great Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers? <hi>If not,</hi> you are not fit to write about theſe Controverſies. <hi>If you have,</hi> you ought to give ſome ſatisfactory Reply, and not to put it off by ſaying, Dr. <hi>W.</hi> thinks that ſuch Arguers deſerve not an Anſwer. This is but a mean way of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophizing.</p>
               <p>Some of the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> aſſign to the Brutes Souls <hi>Immaterial,</hi> Beings <hi>diverſe</hi> from the Body. And the <hi>Peripateticks</hi> ſay, They
<pb facs="tcp:64916:58"/>have <hi>Subſtantial Forms</hi> diſtinct from Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And <hi>Porphyry</hi> is peremptory for their Immortality. Beſides what is ſaid of an <hi>Anima mundi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But however theſe Controverſies be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, I think 'tis eaſy to demonſtrate, that the Souls of Brutes are much more noble than the Material Spirits of their Blood. But the Immortality of our own Souls depends not upon ſuch <hi>Speculations</hi> as theſe. We need not run to the <hi>Brutes</hi> for Arguments. Let them do ſo, whoſe Principles require it.</p>
               <p>If you think you can fairly anſwer the Reaſons which I have given from Scripture and Natural Light in this Point; and when you have ſo done, undertake to prove, (I do not ſay meerly to aſſert) That the Souls of Brutes are <hi>Material</hi> and <hi>Mortal,</hi> and by conſequence that the Souls of Men are ſo too: Begin when you pleaſe, I hope I ſhall not be unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for you. But till then, I am not obliged to incumber my Defence of the Soul's Immortality with <hi>needleſs</hi> Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Though it ſhould be granted, That the Souls of Brutes are both Material and Mortal, we are ſtill ſure that the <hi>Humane Soul</hi> is much more excellent than <hi>they;</hi> as appears by thoſe Operations in us,
<pb facs="tcp:64916:59"/>which are not deſcernible in them. I think it is ill done of thoſe Philoſophers, who <hi>debaſe</hi> or <hi>deny</hi> the Senſitive Faculties of Beaſts, and make them <hi>meer Machines;</hi> and I deny not, that there is ſomething in them which looks <hi>like</hi> Reaſon. But, what then? Theſe higher Operations of the Souls of Men, which have a more <hi>immediate</hi> and <hi>direct</hi> reference to Immortality, are ſuch as we ſee no appearance of in the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Creatures. They <hi>know not God,</hi> they <hi>love him</hi> not; they have no <hi>apprehenſions of a Future State,</hi> no ſenſe of <hi>Moral</hi> Good or Evil, as Man hath; and this is enough to diſtinguiſh <hi>us</hi> from <hi>them,</hi> and to ſhew, that our Natures are made for higher Ends than theirs; as the Poet, ſpeaking of Religion, ſays,
<q>
                     <l>—Seperat haec nos,</l>
                     <l>A Grege Brutorum,—</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore to argue from the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of the Souls of Brutes, againſt the Immortality of the Souls of Men, is (eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way) to <hi>beg the Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. And thus again, you carry the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy into the dark, (as the manner of <hi>ſuch</hi> Philoſophers is) and plead <hi>Uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> againſt thoſe things which are <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> not knowing the <hi>premiſes</hi> while you
<pb facs="tcp:64916:59"/>will needs hold the <hi>Concluſion,</hi> and ſo abuſe your Reaſon, and loſe the <hi>Truth</hi> and your Labour both together. This method may indeed ſerve the ends of <hi>perverſe Wranglers,</hi> but is not the way to make any man wiſer.</p>
               <p>There is a great deal obſervable both in the Souls of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Brutes,</hi> which the beſt Philoſophers do not comprehend. Muſt we therefore deny what's plain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are not agreed about more <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote</hi> Difficulties? This is the way to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce <hi>Scepticiſm,</hi> and unthankfully to reject what God <hi>hath</hi> made known to us, becauſe he hath not laid open all the reſt.</p>
               <p>The words of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe <hi>de Animâ,</hi> are very remarkable in the preſent Caſe. <hi>Quis enim revelabit quod Deus texit? unde ſciſcitandum eſt?</hi> — <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat per Deum neſcire, quia non revelaverit, quam per hominem ſcire, quia ipſe praeſumpſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> pag. mihi. 342.</p>
               <p>Your Maſters have not yet ſatisfied the Learned World, in any Account they have given of <hi>Senſitive perception</hi> and <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite,</hi> by reducing them to the Laws of <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Motion.</hi> You muſt lay your Foundation better before you build ſo much upon it. But <hi>Cicero,</hi> and <hi>Laertius</hi> tell us, That the <hi>Epicureans</hi> abandoned
<pb facs="tcp:64916:60"/>Logick, and ſo do their <hi>Abettors.</hi> If <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing</hi> would ſerve inſtead of <hi>proving,</hi> there would be no great difference between an <hi>Ideot,</hi> and a <hi>Philoſopher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obj. 2. <hi>But Thinking, Arguing,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>which you aſcribe to the Soul, belong to the whole</hi> Compoſitum, <hi>or</hi> contexture <hi>of Soul and Body, which is the efficient proper cauſe of them,</hi> pag. 2, 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> According to your own Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis, each part of the <hi>Compoſitum</hi> is not alike concerned in theſe Acts, but (<hi>eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially</hi>) the <hi>Animal Spirits,</hi> and the <hi>Brain,</hi> which you ſuppoſe to be a <hi>materia cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiva;</hi> but theſe are not the <hi>whole Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> ſo that you muſt firſt reconcile your Philoſophy to it ſelf, and then anſwer what I have ſaid, againſt the Capacity of theſe Material, Corruptible Spirits, for the production of ſuch Acts, before this Objection be at all valuable.</p>
               <p>They very uſe which the Soul now makes of <hi>Corporeal Organs</hi> and <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> plainly evinces, That it doth exert ſome Action wherein they aſſiſt it not; for it ſuppoſeth an operation <hi>upon</hi> them ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent to any operation <hi>by</hi> them — When therefore the Soul makes uſe of a bodily Organ, its Action upon it muſt
<pb facs="tcp:64916:60"/>needs, at laſt, be without the miniſtry of any Organ, unleſs you multiply to it Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy upon Body <hi>in infinitum,</hi> as a Reverend Author obſerves, <hi>Bleſſedneſs of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> pag. 205.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nullam vim, virtutem, aut aptitudinem ad ipſum intelligendi aut volendi actum,</hi> purum, formalem in ſe, <hi>à ſpiritibus aut à ſenſu ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus recipit. Quomodo enim inferius, &amp; vilius &amp; paſſivum, virtutem activam nobilem Naturae ſuperiori, praeſtantiori, &amp; activae communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care poteſt,</hi> Method. Theol. part. 1.162.</p>
               <p>Obj. 3. <hi>Matter and Motion may do much, as appears by a Muſical Organ in the hand of a good Artiſt,</hi> page 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Inſtrument is not conſcious of the Harmony produced by it, as the Soul is of its own Acts; and therefore your Similitude is far from running upon all four.</p>
               <p>Obj. 4. <hi>Matter has a ſelf-moving Power; for, if it be reduced to a fine Powder, part of it will riſe up into the Air like a thin Cloud,</hi> pag. 7. 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Air is a fluid body, in which thoſe little Particles are moved, as Sticks or Straws are in the Water, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>its</hi> motion, and not by a ſelf-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Power of their <hi>own.</hi> Though, as
<pb facs="tcp:64916:61"/>our Author (not obſerving how he almoſt confutes himſelf) tells you in the very next words, that they are apt to be <hi>moved</hi> with every little breath. I believe indeed they are very ſuſceptible of impreſſions from <hi>without,</hi> but have no ſelf-moving power <hi>within</hi> them. If the Duſt in the Streets fly into you Eyes, will you therefore ſay it has a ſelf-moving power? ſtop it but cloſe up in a Bottle where Wind and Air can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſturb it, and I will be bound for its good behaviour.</p>
               <p>As for the nature of <hi>Fire,</hi> you have <hi>light</hi> and <hi>heat,</hi> as well as <hi>motion,</hi> to give an account of, which I fancy will put you hard to it.</p>
               <p>Neither know you whence the Wind comes, nor whither it goes, nor what it is that puts it in motion; and ſo we are not at all edified by your Aſſertion concerning it.</p>
               <p>Obj. 5. <hi>The Spirit of the</hi> Egyptian, <hi>whom</hi> David <hi>found at</hi> Ziklag <hi>in the field famiſhed, came to him again after they had given him Fruit and Water,</hi> pag. 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> No wonder that his <hi>Material, Animal Spirits</hi> were refreſh'd by ſuitable Nouriſhment; but that proves not that he had no <hi>nobler Principle</hi> in him: Neither do
<pb facs="tcp:64916:61"/>I deny that theſe Spirits are the <hi>immediate Inſtruments</hi> of the Soul's Operations in its ſtate of union with the Body: But this is only <hi>ad modum,</hi> not <hi>ad formam actus;</hi> and therefore to ſay the Soul cannot <hi>ſubſiſt</hi> nor <hi>act</hi> in a ſtate of Separation from them, is an Argument <hi>à Bactdo ad Angulum:</hi> And yet it is no wonder, if it leave the Body, when theſe Spirits are no longer fit to be a <hi>vinculum</hi> of <hi>vital</hi> union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them.</p>
               <p>Obj. 6. <hi>It cannot be conceived how the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate Soul ſhould think without the Brain, ſee without an Eye,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Infant in the Womb hath no conception of theſe Actions which it ſhall perform when it is come into the World, and grown up to maturity. The Caſes are much alike.</p>
               <p>To conclude, Except we better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood what the Soul <hi>is,</hi> and how it <hi>acts</hi> while united to the Body, 'tis meer fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs to deny its. Capacity of a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Subſiſtence, becauſe we underſtand not what will be the <hi>mode</hi> of its Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in that State. But ſome men love to argue <hi>ab ignoto ad ignotius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:62"/>
                  <hi>Mihi quidem naturam animi intuenti, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to difficilior occurrit cogitatio, multoque ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurior qualis animus in corpore ſit, tanquam alienae domi, quam qualis, cum exierit, &amp; in liberum coelum, quaſi in domum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, venerit.</hi> Cic. Tuſc. Quaeſt. lib. 1. pag. 339.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64916:62"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of Materiality, or Immateriality, as they are aſcribed to the Soul.</head>
               <p>THAT which our Author ſeems moſt to truſt to, in the preſent Controverſy, is the ſuppoſed <hi>Materiality</hi> of the Soul; and this it is which he thinks gives him ſo great an advantage againſt his Adverſary, that (as the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſome is) he <hi>triumphs before the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory;</hi> and yet all this Duſt which he raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about Matter, is an eaſily diſſipated, as the Apoſtle <hi>ſhook off the Viper from his hand;</hi> which will appear by the following Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Many great Philoſophers and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines have earneſtly contended, that the Soul is <hi>immaterial,</hi> and have laid great ſtreſs upon this for the proof of its <hi>Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.</hi> The Reaſons which they offer ſhould have been well weighed, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by our Author, before he had ſet up for a new Diſcoverer. 'Tis an end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs piece of work to write againſt thoſe perſons who will take no notice of what has been ſaid before.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:63"/>How little alliance is there between a <hi>Thought,</hi> and any <hi>bodily</hi> thing? The more ſtrictly you conſider this, the more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon you will ſee to conceive of the Soul as a ſubſtance diſtinct <hi>from,</hi> and far more noble <hi>than</hi> Matter.</p>
               <p>The Notions which we have of a <hi>Mind, i. e.</hi> ſomething within us that <hi>thinks, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends, reaſons, diſcourſes, wills, nills, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, denies, doubts,</hi> &amp;c. are mightily dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from any Notions which we can faſten upon a <hi>Body.</hi> And yet our Author thinks that Corn may be converted into a rational activity, <hi>pag.</hi> 12. But to that I have ſaid enough already.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly, <hi>Others ſay, that the Soul is material, and yet are as great Aſſerters of its Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity as the former.</hi> Many of the Ancient Fathers of the Church were of this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in his Treatiſe <hi>de Amimâ,</hi> diſputes hotly for it. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſays, that the Soul, if compared to God, is corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real; and ſo doth <hi>Damaſcene.</hi> See many more in the <hi>Appendix to the Reaſons of the Chriſtian Religion,</hi> where you will find that they took the Angels themſelves for more ſublime purer Bodies. And the Learned <hi>Zanchy</hi> agrees with them in his Treatiſe <hi>de Angelis,</hi> chap. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:63"/>Neither will it follow that the Soul is <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>al,</hi> if it ſhould be acknowledged <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial. Ariſtotle</hi> himſelf ſuppoſes it to be a certain Quinteſſence diſtinct from the four Elements, analogous to the matter of the Heavens, which yet the <hi>Peripateticks</hi> ſuppoſe incorruptible. And it can never be proved that ſo <hi>ſimple</hi> and <hi>pure</hi> a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance as the Soul is, hath any natural tendency to diſſolution, or ſeparation of parts, but on the other hand the nobleſt Natures incline moſt to union; neither is it to be feared leſt God ſhould annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late or deſtroy it, ſince he has given it a <hi>Nature</hi> fitted for Immortality, which ſhews that he has deſign'd it thereto.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quid multa? Sic mihi perſuaſi, ſic ſentio. Cum ſimplex animi Natura ſit, neque habeat in ſe quicquam admiſtum, diſpar ſui, &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimile, non poſſe cum dividi; quod ſi non poſſit, non poſſe interire,</hi> Cic. de Senect. pag. 210.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly, <hi>The Nature of Matter is not ſo well underſtood, as that the determination of the preſent Controverſy ſhou'd be ſuppoſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon it.</hi> The <hi>Accidents</hi> and <hi>Modes</hi> of Matter are obvious to our Senſes, but how little know we of its <hi>intimate Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:64916:64"/>
                  <hi>Senſus infra Naturae opera ſubſiſtunt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> que intima illius penetrant, ſed in ext<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> ſemper facie verſantur,</hi> Lud. Viv. de Ver. Fid. 151.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rerum omnium verae germanaeque Eſſentiae ipſae per ſe non cognoſcuntur. A nobis abditae latent. In penitiſſimis cujuſque rei, quò mens noſtra, in hujus corporis mole &amp; tenebris vitae, non penetrat. Idem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to the ſame purpoſe Dr. <hi>More, Antid. againſt Atheiſm,</hi> pag. 15. <hi>As for the very</hi> Eſſence, <hi>or</hi> bare <hi>Subſtance of any thing whatſoever, he is a very Novice in Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that does not acknowledge</hi> that <hi>utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known. But for the Eſſential, and inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Properties, they are as intelligible and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable in a Spirit, as in any other Subject whatſoever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſhall we in the midſt of all this darkneſs talk confidently about <hi>materia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> and <hi>immateriality,</hi> and diſpute our ſelves into Atheiſm or Sadduciſm, by wrangling about we know not what? Can you tell whether Matter be diviſible <hi>in infinitum,</hi> or no? Take which ſide of the Queſtion you pleaſe, (and the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>mentally</hi> or <hi>really</hi> diviſible into the bargain) and make your beſt of it. If it be not infinitely diviſible, then eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of Matter is not Matter, as not
<pb facs="tcp:64916:64"/>having extenſion, or trinal dimenſion. If i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, then a Grain of Muſtard-ſeed may be divided into as many parts as a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. And ſhall the Immortality of the Soul be ſuppoſed to ſtand upon ſo lubri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous a Foundation as this is? No ſuch matter. Anſwer <hi>honeſtly</hi> and <hi>fairly</hi> the Arguments which I have produced from <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or elſe tell us plainly which of <hi>theſe two</hi> you renounce, but do not think to ſhift it off by quibbling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the word immaterial, unleſs you bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtood what Matter is. For this would be to run into the dark, that you might not be ſeen to bluſh, while you talk againſt Light it ſelf.</p>
               <p>The formal Vertues of Spirits are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter known to us by their Acts, than their Subſtances, yea and better, perhaps, than the naked Eſſence of Matter it ſelf is. Some great Philoſophers have affirmed that the Soul is more knowable than the Body. See <hi>Deſcart. princ. Philoſ. pag.</hi> 3. and his <hi>Meditat. de prima Philoſ. pag.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>To conclude, The ſubſtance of our Souls differs ſo much from any <hi>corporeal</hi> thing that we are acquainted with, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t may well enough be called <hi>immaterial;</hi> though we know not wherein the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Spirits from the fineſt Matter
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:64916:65"/>conſiſts, excepting their <hi>formal Vertues,</hi> and <hi>unſpeakable Purity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mihi quidem ſufficit, dum aliorum auſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus nihil oppono, nec contradico, ex virtute formali in ſubſtantiâ puriſſimâ fundatâ (ſine compoſitione) Spiritum à materiâ paſſivâ di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguere: Qui plus praeſtare poteſt praeſtet.</hi> Method. Theol. par. 1.142.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:64916:65"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Directions to ſuch as are in ſuſpenſe as to the Immortality of the Soul, ſhewing how they may arrive at a certainty in that matter.</head>
               <p>THough I have already ſaid ſo much as I think may ſuffice to ſatisfy ſuch Perſons as are willing to do their own Souls right, yet all are not alike diſpoſed for the reception of <hi>plain Evidence</hi> when ſet before them. <hi>Recipitur ad modum recipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis;</hi> and therefore it will not be alien to the Deſign which I have in hand, to lay down ſome Directions which will tend to make all that hath been already ſpoken, more effectual. And they are ſuch as theſe.</p>
               <p>Direct. 1. <hi>Be impartial in your Enquiries about this matter, and take ſpecial care that your Underſtandings be not byaſſed by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of your Luſts, which will diſpoſe you to hate even Reaſon it ſelf, and to ſhut your eyes againſt the Light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socrates,</hi> diſcourſing concerning the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality of the Soul, warns his Hearers to take care that they be not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>haters
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:64916:66"/>of Reaſon,</hi> than which a greater miſchief could not befall them, <hi>Phoedo, pag.</hi> 133.</p>
               <p>Atheiſtical Inclinations in mens <hi>Wills</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> do commonly ſet their <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings</hi> on work to frame Principles ſuited thereto, and to defend and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thoſe Principles; and a Mind thus depraved, is like a Corrupt Judge, who will hear nothing againſt the Party that has bribed him. When the Soul has ſo far degraded it ſelf, as to become a Slave to the Senſual Appetite, the conſciouſneſs of its own guilt makes it willing to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it ſelf no nobler a Subſtance than thoſe Material Spirits which have led it captive all the while, that ſo it may die with the Body, and not be called to an account for its unnatural ſelf-abaſement. <hi>Alii deliciis immerſi ac voluptatibus omnia cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perent cum illis paritèr concidere, hoc eſt, cum corpore, nec eſſe ullum Judicem qui vitae hujus rationem à nobis repoſceret,</hi> Lud. Viv. de Ver. Fid. lib. 1.145.</p>
               <p>It is worth your while to examine, whether ſomething of this nature be not the Spring and Fountain of theſe <hi>brutiſh Principles;</hi> and if ſo, you have reaſon to ſuſpect them, as proceeding from ſo <hi>vile</hi> an Original.</p>
               <p>It is alſo poſſible, that ſome thinking Perſons of a ſober converſation, may
<pb facs="tcp:64916:66"/>have an <hi>Ingenium Haereticum,</hi> and affect ſingularity in Opinions to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more taken notice of, and admired by ſuch who have not Wit enough to detect their Sophiſtry. But <hi>ordinarily</hi> 'tis Mens love to their Luſts and ſenſual Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, their neglect of God and Religion, their wilful deſpiſing the Concerns<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Intereſts of a future State, which diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them to <hi>wiſh</hi> their Souls were Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, for fear of what may come after, and then to believe (though not without a great deal of wavering and heſitation) that they are ſo. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith <hi>Hierocles.</hi> A wicked Man would not have his Soul to be Immortal, leſt he ſhould be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd for his wickedneſs, yet he antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pates the Sentence of his Judg, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it to Death before-hand. <hi>Malunt extingui quam ad ſupplicia reparari,</hi> Minut. Felix.</p>
               <p>Direct. 2. <hi>Be not overfond of your preſent Conceits.</hi> It becomes you to ſuppoſe that you may be miſtaken, becauſe many (as wiſe Men) have been ſo before you. He knows little of the weakneſs of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Underſtandings, not of the unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able depths of the Works of God, who ſees not how neceſſary a qualification
<pb facs="tcp:64916:67"/>
                  <hi>Modeſty,</hi> and a promptitude to ſuſpect his own Judgment, muſt needs be in a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher. And though this muſt not be ſo far ſtrained as to make us turn <hi>Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> yet it ought to reſtrain us from an over-forwardneſs to vent <hi>uncouth</hi> Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and from paſſing an haſty judgment on things, before we have well weighed what may be ſaid on both ſides. Theſe things which appear <hi>difficult</hi> to you, may perhaps be <hi>eaſy</hi> to another; and thoſe things which you look upon as <hi>Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations,</hi> to a more diſcerning Perſon will, it may be, appear no better than <hi>Dreams;</hi> and Self-conceit will make you ſlight the weightieſt Reaſons which are brought to awake and undeceive you. Some of you value your ſelves upon the account of a natural quickneſs of Wit, with ſome acquired <hi>Scraps</hi> of Philoſophy; but take care that this do not make you ſet too high an eſteem upon your <hi>little crude</hi> Notions, which a ſmall time may diſcover to be meer trifles, and Death will terribly confute for ever.</p>
               <p>Direct. 3. <hi>Let your Diligence and Seriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in theſe Studies be anſwerable to the weight and conſequence of thoſe Truths you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after.</hi> 'Tis a matter that nearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you, to know whether the Soul be
<pb facs="tcp:64916:67"/>Immortal or no. If after all the pains you have taken to make your ſelf believe, that the Soul dieth with the Body, you ſhould at laſt find your ſelf miſtaken; where are you then? What will you do when Death hath drawn aſide this Vail of Ignorance, and placed you in the Society of wretched Spirits, forſaken of God, and paſt all hopes of recovery? Will not this be a dreadful diſappointment? If I ſaw a Man cut a little too deep when he was pairing his Nails, perhaps I might laugh at him for his raſhneſs; but if I ſee him attempting to Stab himſelf, that's no laughing matter, and I am guilty of Murther, if I do not endeavour to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it; and therefore I ſay again, <hi>be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</hi> Let me tell you from a Perſon of as <hi>comprehenſive</hi> a <hi>Genius,</hi> and as high a Station as the beſt and greateſt of you all, (the great Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi>) <q>That the Soul is a ſerious Thing, and muſt be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſad <hi>here</hi> for a moment, or ſad for <hi>ever.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis an eaſy matter to get ſome crude, undigeſted <hi>Notions,</hi> and <hi>Terms of Art</hi> to play withal; but ſolid and ſatisfactory Knowledge muſt be the fruit of Induſtry; and hard impartial Study: And you have reaſon enough to queſtion all thoſe Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions which are the Off-ſpring of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking
<pb facs="tcp:64916:68"/>ſloathfulneſs, though none are uſually more confident than ſuch Triflers, who like drunken Perſons boaſt of their Wit to the increaſe of their ſhame. The beſt way to know that the Soul is Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, is to keep its nobleſt Faculties in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due Exerciſe, and then they will ſpeak for themſelves.</p>
               <p>Direct. 4. <hi>See that your Ends be right in theſe Studies,</hi> i. e. <hi>ſuitable to the tendency of thoſe Truths you ſearch into.</hi> Study the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Humane Nature, that you may walk as becomes <hi>Men,</hi> worthy the Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of that Rational Immortal Spirit which God hath given you. Right ends will help you in the uſe of means; but if you ſtudy theſe things meerly to pleaſe your Phanſy, this is but a more refined ſort of Senſuality, and then 'tis no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if you miſs of the Truth, nor indeed any great matter whether you find it or no, for any great good it's like to do you.</p>
               <p>An honeſt manly Deſign in theſe Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, will prepare you for the entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Truth. Indeed 'tis a noble Employment to enquire into the Works of God, and eſpecially into our own Souls, that we may know him, and love him better, and diſcharge our Duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:64916:68"/>him more faithfully; and in ſo doing, we may humbly expect ſome ſuch <hi>Afflatum divini Numinis;</hi> (as our Author ſpeaks, <hi>page</hi> 15.) which may enlighten our Underſtandings, and lead us into thoſe Truths which we ſeek after. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe 'tis to ſmall purpoſe to talk of the Immortality of the Soul to ſuch Perſons, who are reſolved to gratify their Luſts, though they loſe their Reputations and Souls too in the Adventure. Thus <hi>Bias</hi> the Philoſopher, being asked by ſome <hi>vain Fellows,</hi> What that Piety he talked of meant? Anſwered, <hi>It was to no purpoſe to ſpeak to a Man of thoſe things which he never intended to practiſe.</hi> See <hi>Laert.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>Direct. 5. <hi>Proceed orderly in your Studies; and do not begin at the wrong end.</hi> Lay down the moſt plain and certain Truths firſt, and ſo aſcend gradually to thoſe that are more difficult. Try thoſe things that are <hi>uncertain, by</hi> (and do not plead them <hi>againſt</hi>) thoſe that are <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> unleſs you have a mind to bewilder your ſelves, and to know <hi>nothing,</hi> becauſe you cannot know <hi>all.</hi> There are many Queſtions concerning the <hi>Origine of the Soul, its Union with the Body, its moving of it, and Direction of the Spirits, its diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb facs="tcp:64916:69"/>Mode of Operation</hi> when it ſhall be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from the Body, its <hi>Reunion with</hi> the Body at the Reſurrection, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which will puzzle you when you have done your beſt, and <hi>peradventure yea, peradventure no,</hi> is very often the wiſeſt Anſwer you can give to them: To ſuch matters the ſayings of <hi>Xenophon</hi> in <hi>Varro,</hi> is pertinent, <hi>Hominis eſt haec opinari, Dei ſcire. God only knows them, and we conjecture.</hi> But muſt we therefore renounce or undervalue that Knowledge which is attainable? What if I know not how the Child is formed in the Womb, (after all that Dr. <hi>Needham</hi> hath ſaid, <hi>de formato Foetu</hi>) muſt I therefore deny that the Child is formed there at all? This were ridiculous. You may eaſily apply it. Remember that which is greater, cannot be comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that which is leſs. <hi>The Soul fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd in the Body, is in ſome reſpect leſs and weaker than it ſelf;</hi> as <hi>Dupleſſis</hi> obſerves. Shall we quarrel with the Almighty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath hidden ſome of the Secrets of his Workmanſhip from us? Or (like froward Children) caſt away what is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us, becauſe we may not have all we would deſire, though never ſo unfit for us. <hi>Plurimorum enim infelicium ingeniorum inde orta eſt ruina, quod dum nota &amp; neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaria plane negligunt, ant ſenſualitate &amp; viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum
<pb facs="tcp:64916:69"/>mole obruunt, &amp; abſconditis inutilibus enixè ſtudent, idque ingenio ſuperbiente, cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginis ſuae non ſatis conſcio, quando fruſtrà ſe non patefacta quaeſiviſſe comperiunt; fati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gati &amp; deſperantes, de certis etiam, &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſariis dubitant, &amp; ipſam animorum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitatem negant. In tanta ſcilicet mala ſtultos, perverſus ſtudiorum ordo praecipitat.</hi> Method. Theol. Part 1. pag. 155.</p>
               <p>In order therefore to your ſatisfaction in this Point, give me leave to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to you the following Method.</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt, <hi>Digest well thoſe Arguments which demonſtrate the Being and Perfections of the Deity.</hi> That there is a God, and that the Souls of Men are Immortal, are Truths ſo nearly link'd together, that he who denies the one, may juſtly be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of a <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> to deny the other. <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Sadduciſm</hi> ſpring from the ſame Root, and muſt both be attacqued together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The inviſible Things of God are clearly ſeen by the things that are made, even his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Power and Godhead.</hi> What think you? Can there be an <hi>Effect</hi> without a <hi>Cauſe?</hi> Could this glorious Fabrick of Heaven and Earth be rear'd <hi>by Chance?</hi> Could the Sun, Moon, and Stars, have any Light, but <hi>from the Father of Lights?</hi> Could the
<pb facs="tcp:64916:70"/>Earth be <hi>hung upon nothing,</hi> but by him <hi>who upholdeth all things by the Word of his Power?</hi> Is it not demonſtrable that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing muſt needs have been Eternal? If you ſhould ſuppoſe a time or ſpace (call it what you will) in which there was nothing, will it not neceſſarily follow that there never could have been any thing, becauſe nothing could have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd nothing?</p>
               <p>Moreover, there can be no excellency in the <hi>Effect,</hi> which is not ſome way or other in the <hi>Cauſe;</hi> and therefore, ſince ſo much <hi>Power, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> ſhines forth in the <hi>Greatneſs, Order,</hi> and <hi>Uſefulneſs</hi> of the ſeveral Parts of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and their Aptitude and Tendency to the Beauty, and Perfection of the whole; and ſo much that is unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the meaneſt Creature; and ſince in the Enumeration of Cauſes, 'tis abſurd to run <hi>in Infinitum,</hi> you muſt needs come up to a <hi>first Cauſe, Eternal,</hi> and of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible Perfection,</hi> who has more Excellency than all <hi>ſubordinate</hi> Cauſes put together; for they have none but what he gave them, and it is not poſſible any Creature ſhould be ſo perfect as he that made it.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:70"/>2dly, <hi>Study well the Doctrine of Divine Providence, and conſider what full and clear Evidence we have, that the World is order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and govern'd by it. Epicurus</hi> denied, That God was the Creator of the World. <hi>Eximendum imprimis est à ſollicitudine, ac labore Mundi extruendi Divinum Numen,</hi> Gaſſend. Syntag. Philoſ. Epicur. 72. And upon the ſame account he denied Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. <hi>Non enim cum felicitate congruunt negotia, ſollicitudines, irae, gratiae,</hi> &amp;c. 78. The like you have in <hi>Laert. pag.</hi> 285. In <hi>Epicur. &amp; pag.</hi> 300. And <hi>Lucretius</hi> treads in the ſame Steps. Now, this is, in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, to deny the Being and Perfections of the Deity, or to meaſure his Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by our Imperfection, and to leave both the Creation and Government of the World to blind Chance, or to that empty <hi>Nothing,</hi> which they call <hi>Nature.</hi> And yet they ſpeak contemptibly of Fortune too, though they ſay the World was made by Chance, <hi>Gaſſend. Syntag.</hi> 49, 50. So ill do the Principles of this Philoſophy hang together. How much better is it to ſay with <hi>Cicero, Deo nil praeſtantius, ab eo igitur neceſſe eſt mundum regi.</hi> De Natur. Deor. And again, <hi>Whoever doubts of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, may as well doubt, whether the Sun ſhine or no,</hi> Ibid. 'Tis all one to a Being
<pb facs="tcp:64916:71"/>of Infinite Perfection, to regard the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Actions of every Creature, as if he had but one to mind. God has not made a World greater than himſelf, and it is diſhonourable to him to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that he is only an unconcerned Spectator of the Affairs and Tranſactions of his Creatures. Beſides, 'tis Nonſenſe to think that the Creatures can either <hi>Subſiſt</hi> or <hi>Act</hi> without him. His Name is <hi>I A M,</hi> and all created Beings compared with him, are but <hi>Non-Entities,</hi> as <hi>Plato</hi> obſerves, <hi>Id ſolum eſſe quod eſt aeternum, &amp; immutabile, caetera potius non eſſe, quam eſſe.</hi> In Timaeo.</p>
               <p>And 'tis obſervable how Nature it ſelf prompts us to look unto him for relief and help in Exigences, and to lift up Hands and Eyes to Heaven when we <hi>know not what to do.</hi> Thus it bears witneſs to the Divine Providence.</p>
               <p>And the Checks of Conſcience for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Sins, in like manner evince, That there is an All-ſeeing Eye upon us. And ſo Natural Light prepares for Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly, <hi>See that your Souls be poſſest with awful Apprehenſions of ſo great a Majeſty.</hi> This or nothing will make you ſerious, and reſtrain your Thoughts from thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:64916:71"/>maſterleſs Vagaries, in which Irreligious Philoſophers are wont to indulge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their own Deſtruction. Dare you take his Name in vain? Or vilify his Works to his diſhonour? Doth not <hi>his Excellency make you afraid, and his dread fall upon you?</hi> Look up to the Heavens which are higher than you. The Sun in its Meridian brightneſs, is but a ſhadow of him who is LIGHT, and in whom there is no Darkneſs at all. Millions of Angels continually adore him: The whole Hoſt of Heaven is at his beck; ſhould he give Commiſſion but to one of his Angels to deſtroy ten thouſand ſuch as you, how quickly would it be done? His Power is Omnipotent: His Wiſdom Infinite. <hi>Who would ſet Thorns and Briars in array againſt him? He would paſs through them, and conſume them. How much better is it to lay hold of his Strength, that you may be at peace with him? Be not deceived, God is not mocked.</hi> You may flatter and befool your ſelves for a while, but what will you do in the end thereof? When your mournful Friends ſtand about you, and your Phyſicians give you up, as paſt hope of recovery? How diſmal will the thoughts of Eternity then be? How ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely will Conſcience pay you home for all the <hi>Tricks</hi> and <hi>Abuſes</hi> you have put
<pb facs="tcp:64916:72"/>upon it? And whither will you fly to avoid it? Do you think your <hi>dreaming Philoſophy</hi> will then ſtand you in ſtead? Will it ſecure you from the amazing Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of what is like to come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Or will you not rather curſe the Day that ever you became acquainted with theſe brutiſh Principles? Well, if none of theſe things move you, <hi>The Lord have mercy on you,</hi> for all good Men are deeply affected with them. However re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you were fairly warned of your danger.</p>
               <p n="4">4thly, <hi>Abſtract your Minds as much as poſſibly you can from things Corporeal, that you may converſe more intimately with your own Souls.</hi> Diveſt your Spirits of all that's foreign to them, that you may better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their <hi>naked</hi> Beauty and Perfection. Let ſenſible Objects keep their diſtance, and ſuffer not any tumultuous Paſſions to interrupt your more calm, retired thoughts, or to raiſe Miſts before you. And then you will quickly find, that the more deeply you contemplate the nobleſt Acts of your own Souls, the greater evidence will appear of their Spiritual, Immortal Nature. <q>All thoſe Diſcourſes, which have been written of the Soul's Heral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry, will not blazon it ſo well as it ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:64916:72"/>will do, as a Learned Man obſerves. When we turn our Eye in upon it, 'twill ſoon tell us its <hi>Royal Pedigree</hi> and <hi>Noble Extraction,</hi> by thoſe Sacred Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roglyphicks which it bears upon it ſelf. <bibl>
                        <hi>Smith</hi>'s <hi>Diſcourſes,</hi> page 66.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Many Philoſophers have ſpoken well of this Abſtraction of our Minds, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring into our ſelves; but none more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely than the <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> and <hi>Plotinus</hi> in particular.</p>
               <p>This made them ſay, That Philoſophy is <hi>Mortis Meditatio;</hi> becauſe that as in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> Death the Soul is actually ſeparated from the Body, ſo in theſe Philoſophical Contemplations we muſt abſtract it from coporeal Commerce as much as we can. And though this ſaying is commonly (and particularly by <hi>Plutarch</hi>) aſcribed to <hi>Plato,</hi> yet St. <hi>Jerom</hi> tells us <hi>Pythagoras</hi> was the firſt Man who ſaid, <hi>Philoſophiam eſſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditationem Mortis quotidie de carcere corporis nitentem educere Animae libertatem.</hi> See <hi>Lyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſii Manuduc. ad Stoic. Philoſ.</hi> And this (ſays <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi>) <hi>Pythagoras</hi> meant by the five years ſilence which he enjoyned his Diſciples. <hi>Ut ſcilicet à rebus ſenſilibus averſi nudâ mente,</hi> &amp;c. However <hi>Plato</hi> diſcourſeth excellently about it: See his <hi>Phaedo,</hi> where he brings in <hi>Socrates</hi> telling his Friends, <q>That of all Men
<pb facs="tcp:64916:73"/>Philoſophers ſhould not be unwilling to dye, who have been endeavouring all their lives long to abſtract themſelves from their Bodies as much as they can. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>atque ad ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam ſe convertere.</hi> And ſhould they therefore be unwilling to be ſet free from thoſe Bodies which have been ſuch an hinderance to them in their ſearches after Truth?</q> And thus he ſums up the matter, <hi>page</hi> 89. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <q>If while we are in the Body, we can diſcern nothing purely, it muſt either follow that we ſhall never attain to knowledge, or that we ſhall do it after Death; for <hi>then,</hi> and not <hi>before,</hi> the Soul will ſubſiſt without the Body, and while we live here, the leſs commerce we have with <hi>it,</hi> the nearer approaches we make to knowledge.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> being asked what good he had got by Philoſophy? Anſwer'd, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, He learnt by it to converſe with himſelf, <hi>Laert.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelf owns the neceſſity of this Abſtraction, and makes it the pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Priviledge of ſome Men, more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted than others from Corporeal Commerce, to improve their Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings in the ſteddy Contemplation of Truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:64916:73"/>And ſo doth <hi>Cicero</hi> in thoſe excellent Words, <hi>Magni eſt ingénii revocare mentem à ſenſibus, &amp; cogitationem à conſuetudine ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducere,</hi> Tuſe. Quaeſt. lib. 1.333. and again 350.</p>
               <p>And to the ſame purpoſe ſpeaks <hi>Van Helmont, page</hi> 342. though in a Dialect almoſt peculiar to himſelf.</p>
               <p>And ſo <hi>Deſcatres</hi> (how ingeniouſly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he talks elſewhere of Matter and Motion) when he comes to conſider his own Soul, thus he begins, (See <hi>Meditat.</hi> 3. <hi>de prim. Philoſ.) Claudam nunc oculos, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res obturabo, avocabo omnes ſenſus, meque ſolum alloquendo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Wonder not that I inſiſt ſo largely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this, for the Life of <hi>Philoſophy</hi> (I had almoſt ſaid of <hi>Religion</hi> too) conſiſts in it.</p>
               <p>But when all is done, thoſe Perſons who have long ſuffered their Minds to be immerſt in things Corporeal, muſt take a great deal of pains before they can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate them from thoſe <hi>unhappy Complica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> which have betrayed them to ſo many miſtakes, and kept them ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of their more noble Faculties and Powers.</p>
               <p n="5">5thly, <hi>So live, that you may not be afraid of the Doctrine of the Soul's Immortality.</hi> I have ſhewed you already, that the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb facs="tcp:64916:74"/>of men's Luſts will ſtrangely biaſs their Judgments, and therefore keep the <hi>Senſitive Appetite</hi> at an under: Yield not to its <hi>extravagant</hi> demands. Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom it to be frequently controlled, and let it feel that you have ſomething no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler than Material Spirits within you. The Soul never more forgets its own Dignity, than when it ſuffers Senſe and Appetite to turn <hi>Dictators,</hi> and carry all before them. This diſpoſeth it to terrene and ſordid Conceptions concerning it ſelf. Vicious <hi>Inclinations</hi> are the Root of corrupt <hi>Principles:</hi> Men will hardly love thoſe Doctrines <hi>which Propheſy no good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them, but evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the other hand, If you ſo live that your Conſciences cannot upbraid you with an Atheiſtical Contempt or Forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of him that made you: If you contemplate his Excellencies, and delight in him as the chiefeſt <hi>Good,</hi> and pay that Homage which is due to him in your Religious Worſhip and Attendances upon him, ſuch Exerciſes as theſe will ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you, that your Souls are no ſuch Earthly <hi>Material</hi> Things, as you are ready to imagine. The thoughts of a glorious Immortality will be refreſhing to you, and you will have ſome Anticipations of it in the ſerenity of a vertuous Mind,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:64916:74"/>and the teſtimony of a good Conſcience. You will quickly ſee that Vice and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs <hi>debaſe</hi> the Soul, and that Goodneſs and Piety are things too noble to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected ſo meanly as in a few corruptible, periſhing, material Spirits. If your Souls have once the Image of the Divine Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs imprinted upon them, it will diſpoſe you to diſcern and acknowledg that <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Image of the Spiritual, Immortal Deity, which is antecedent to the other, becauſe there muſt be an agreeableneſs between the Faculty and the Object, and ſuch Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Qualities muſt be ſeated in a Subject ſuitable to them.</p>
               <p n="6">6thly, <hi>Take notice of that certain and full evidence, which we have of a world of Spirits.</hi> How near many of them are to us, and how oft concerning themſelves about us. The Books which have been written about <hi>Witchcrafts, Poſſeſſions, Apparitions,</hi> &amp;c. do all prove, That there are multitudes of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Spirits, which ſeek the Ruin and Deſtruction of Mankind, and carry on a Warfare againſt the Intereſt of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> in the World. They know well enough that the Souls of Men are Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, elfe they would not take ſo much pains to deſtroy them. I need not name the Authors who Treat of thoſe things,
<pb facs="tcp:64916:75"/>
                  <hi>Fernelius, Wierus, Glanvill, More, Baxter,</hi> and many more.</p>
               <p>And on the other hand, <hi>Ambroſe, Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, Zanchy,</hi> &amp;c. will ſhew you, That there are <hi>benign</hi> Spirits, which guard and watch over good Men, and Miniſter for them. If you disbelieve all the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies which theſe Learned Perſons have given in the Caſe, you forfeit your own <hi>Credit,</hi> and cannot reaſonably expect that any Man ſhould believe you.</p>
               <p>As to the Matter of Apparitions, even about Monuments and Sepulchres, <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> makes mention of them. <hi>Phaedo</hi> 117. <q>and ſuppoſeth them to be the Souls of bad Men in a State of puniſhment for the wickedneſs of their Lives, <bibl>118.</bibl>
                  </q> and <hi>Cicero</hi> in his <hi>Tuſc. Quaeſt.</hi> takes notice of ſuch Apparations, <hi>Viſis quibuſdam ſaepe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vebantur, hiſque maxime nocturnis, ut vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur, ii qui vita exceſſerant, vivere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> makes mention of one <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadius,</hi> a Phyſician, and an excellent Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Philoſopher, and withal very chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Poor, who falling into doubt concerning the Immortality of the Soul, was inſtructed concerning it in a Dream by a conſpicuous young Man that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The famous Story</hi> of <hi>Evagrius</hi> the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher, who appear'd to <hi>Syneſius</hi> the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb facs="tcp:64916:75"/>after his Death, you may find in <hi>Baronius</hi>'s Annals, <hi>ad Annum</hi> 412. where he alſo relates the Story of <hi>Michael Mercatus</hi> and <hi>Marſilius Ficinus,</hi> intimate Friends, and both addicted to the <hi>Platonick</hi> Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy. Who after many Debates about the Immortality of the Soul, and a Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture State, mutually agreed, That whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſoever of them died firſt, ſhould, if the Laws of the Inviſible World would admit of it, appear to the Survivor, and give him an account of theſe things. <hi>Thus,</hi> ſays <hi>Baronius, they ſwore to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Not long after</hi> Marſilius <hi>dies; and appears to his Friend, and tells him, thoſe things were true, which the Chriſtian Faith taught concerning the Immortality of the Soul.</hi> This <hi>Baronius</hi> ſays he had from the Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the fore-mentiond <hi>Mercatus.</hi> And the ſame is reported by many other Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>A like account you have of the Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition of Major <hi>George Sydenham</hi> to Capt. <hi>William Dyke,</hi> (who had made ſuch an agreement as the former) telling him, That <hi>there was a God, and a very juſt and terrible one, and that</hi> (if he did not turn over a new Leaf) <hi>he will find it ſo.</hi> See <hi>Glanvill</hi>'s <hi>Sadduc. Triumph.</hi> 408. But thoſe that regard not the Sacred Records, will not be convinc'd, <hi>tho one come to them from the load.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:76"/>However, ſuch paſſages as theſe have been believed by wiſe Men in all Ages, and by Perſons as capable of diſcerning <hi>Truth,</hi> and diſtinguiſhing it from <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures,</hi> as any of the <hi>Pretenders</hi> of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Generation, who care not for hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any news from the <hi>Inviſible World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7thly, If your Genius incline you to Philoſophy, you may eaſily find nobler things than <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Motion</hi> to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain your ſelves with, if you will but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the Writings of <hi>Plato, Plotinus, Epicte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Cicero, Seneca, Antonine,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But above all, if you believe that God regards the Affairs and Actions of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, then look unto him for <hi>Direction</hi> and <hi>Light</hi> in this matter, and he that ſo ſeeks after the Truth will hardly miſs of it in its more weighty and important In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64916:76"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Directions to ſuch as believe the Immortality of the Soul, ſhewing how they ought to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove ſo important a Doctrine.</head>
               <p>THUS far I have proved that the Soul is Immortal, and laid down ſome Directions for thoſe that heſitate in the Matter, in order to their better receiving of the proof that has been given. But ſince there are many who profeſs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this great Truth, and yet live as if they believ'd it not, and ſo encourage thoſe of the contrary Opinion, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them in their Impiety; I muſt not let go this point, till I have drawn ſome <hi>more</hi> practical Inferences from it, which if thoſe that believe it would live up to, 'twould conduce more effectually to the Conviction of the Irreligious ſort of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, than the moſt accurate Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are like to do. There is ſomewhat in an holy Life which commands Awe and Reverence from the worſt of Men. Thus <hi>Herod</hi> feared <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he was a juſt Man and an holy, <hi>Mark</hi> 6.20. Good <hi>Examples</hi> many times prove more powerful, than either <hi>Doctrines</hi> or <hi>Precepts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:77"/>What will it avail any Man to <hi>believe</hi> well, and to <hi>live</hi> ill; to be <hi>Orthodox</hi> in his judgment, and <hi>Scandalous</hi> in his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; to own the Dignity of Humane Nature, and yet live as if Man was only a more ſubtil kind of a Beaſt to rule the reſt?</p>
               <p>To this purpoſe you have a very obſervable paſſage in the Preface to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Reaſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>I oft think what one told me, That an Infidel anſwer'd him, when he asked him, How he could quiet his Conſcience in ſuch a deſperate State? ſaith he, I rather wonder how you can quiet your Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in ſuch a common careleſs courſe of life, believing as you do? If I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd ſuch things as you do, I ſhould think no care, and diligence, and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs could be enough.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And the late E. of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> told an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate Acquaintance of his, <q>There was nothing that gave him, and many others, a more ſecret encouragement in their ill ways, than that thoſe who pretended to believe, lived ſo that they could not be thought to be in earneſt, when they ſaid it. <bibl>(See his Life by Dr. <hi>Burnet pag.</hi> 120).</bibl>
                  </q> For he was ſure Religion was either a meer Contrivance, or the moſt important thing that could be: So that if he once
<pb facs="tcp:64916:77"/>believed, he would ſet himſelf in great earneſt to live ſuitably to it. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore that you may not deſtroy your <hi>own</hi> Souls, and contribute ſo much to the ruin of <hi>others,</hi> even while you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to believe the Immortality of the Soul; take theſe following Directions:</p>
               <p>Direct. 1. <hi>If you believe that the Soul is Immortal, let it be your great care to ſecure your Eternal Intereſt.</hi> If there was no more than a bare <hi>probability</hi> that the Souls of Men muſt be for ever either happy or miſerable, it would yet be a point of the higheſt Wiſdom to take the <hi>ſafeſt ſide,</hi> and to prepare for Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as much as poſſible. But when there is ſo full evidence, both Natural and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural, as puts the caſe beyond pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, and makes it <hi>certain,</hi> it muſt needs be the moſt ſtupendious folly to neglect the Intereſt of our Souls, which are daily haſting to their Eternal State. <q>If the Soul be Immortal (ſays <hi>Socrates</hi>) we had need to take care of it, and the danger is dreadful if we neglect it, <bibl>
                        <hi>Phaedo,</hi> 167.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And here let me ask you, Do you not know that the Life of Man is ſhort and uncertain? That the deceitful pleaſures of the Fleſh will ſoon be at an end; and
<pb facs="tcp:64916:78"/>that the more delightful your accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations are here below, the more unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ('tis likely) you will be to leave them? —<hi>Haec ſunt quae faciunt invitos mori.</hi> And can you chuſe but fear what will follow after Death? Do you not know that the time of this preſent Life is given us to prepare for another? And what are you in purſuit of, that can juſtify ſo ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid a neglect of your greateſt concerns, or that will make amends for the loſs of your Immortal Souls? Have you not ſometimes thoughts of repenting hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Why, in ſo thinking you implicitly own the Neceſſity of Repentance; and is it not the height of madneſs to delay the doing of that which muſt be <hi>done,</hi> or you are <hi>undone</hi> and loſt for ever?</p>
               <p>In a word: Are you not doing violence to your own Conſciences all this while, and putting away far from you that which moſt nearly concerns you? Be perſuaded therefore at length with a manly Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>to lay aſide every weight, and the Sins that do ſo eaſily beſet you, and run with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the Race that is ſet before you.</hi> And if you be ſo reſolved, you may proceed as follows:</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt. <hi>Labour to underſtand what it is that muſt make your Souls happy, if ever they be ſo.</hi> You may know by the acts of
<pb facs="tcp:64916:78"/>your <hi>Underſtandings</hi> and <hi>Wills,</hi> as before deſcribed, what Felicity and Perfection your Souls are <hi>fundamentally</hi> capacitated for: Nothing but the higheſt Truth, and the chiefeſt Good can ſatisfy them. You may divert them for a while with variety of lower Objects, but they quickly grow weary, and run from one thing to another; which may ſhew you that they are not yet got to their Centre. You may charm them with the Delights of <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite,</hi> and ſome more <hi>refined Speculations</hi> too; and yet you do but degrade them all the while, and ſo they will tell you, if you take them apart, and freely converſe with them. Suffer them to act according to their nobler Tendencies, and you will ſoon find them converſing with the World of Spirits, to which they are ſo nearly allyed; and reaching forth towards Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality as a thing ſuitable to their <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and deſign'd for them by <hi>its</hi> Author. They will be looking to their great. Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, and he will meet them with the <hi>Attractive Influences of his Grace.</hi> This is the way to ennoble them indeed: This is ſomething worthy the Nature of a Man. Theſe are delights which you may juſtify, while the ſordid pleaſures of the Fleſh leave a ſting behind 'em.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:79"/>The Life which I am exhorting you to, hath ſomething in it not only <hi>manly,</hi> and <hi>rational,</hi> but alſo <hi>Divine, viz.</hi> To exerciſe your ſelves in contemplating and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Perfections of the Deity, till cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent impreſſions be wrought upon your own Spirits, <hi>transforming them into the ſame image from glory to glory,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.18. And when once you have learnt to reliſh theſe <hi>ſpiritual, intellectual</hi> Pleaſures, you will look down with a generous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain upon thoſe <hi>Husks</hi> which you were once fond of. You will ſcorn thoſe <hi>empty Notions,</hi> which before you were in love with, and have a clear teſtimony of your Immortality within your ſelves. You will deteſt being ſo prophane as to ſell your Birth-right for a morſel of unſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, tranſitory Pleaſures. You will then be fully convinced that true Holineſs (which conſiſts in ſeparating our ſelves from that which is common, and unclean, that we may be devoted to the Love and Service of God) is perfective of Humane Nature, and <hi>eſſentially</hi> neceſſary to its Happineſs; and that it is a perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction for an <hi>unholy</hi> Soul to be truly bleſſed, becauſe nothing but knowing, and delighting in God, can make us ſo, and in theſe conſiſts our Holineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:79"/>And what is there that can juſtly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend you in ſuch a Life as this? Can you be better, or more honourably employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Do not even the worſt of men, when they come to die, wiſh they had thus lived? and the beſt bewail that they have fallen ſo much ſhort? <hi>Lord, pardon mine Omiſſions</hi> (ſaid Biſhop <hi>Uſher.</hi>) Can you be too diligent and ſerious in the Service of him who hath done all the good that ever <hi>was</hi> done for you? and muſt do all that ever <hi>ſhall</hi> be done to make you happy? He needs not you: The loſs is your own, if you turn your backs upon him. Conſider how much patience he hath already exerciſed towards you. O do not ſlight the offers of his Mercy and Grace, and then think to complain of him as unmerciful in deſtroying you. Thus did that <hi>wicked and ſlothful ſervant,</hi> Matth. 25.24.</p>
               <p>I know indeed <hi>that the carnal mind is enmity againſt God,</hi> and prejudiced againſt theſe things which lead towards him; but I know alſo that this is the <hi>diſeaſe</hi> of Corrupt Nature, which, where-ever it is, muſt be cur'd, or the Party is ruin'd for ever.</p>
               <p>Neither is it ſitting ſtill, and complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that will cure it, much leſs pleading it as an excuſe againſt our Duty. A wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs
<pb facs="tcp:64916:80"/>to be healed, is in this Caſe a great ſtep towards it. But I proceed.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly, <hi>Humble your ſelves for the groſs ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glects you have hitherto been guilty of.</hi> What have you done ſince you came into the World that's worthy the Nature and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities of a man? Have you not been making proviſion for the <hi>fleſh</hi> to fulfil the Luſts thereof, while the <hi>Immortal Spirit</hi> has been almoſt ſtarved for want of its proper Food, <hi>viz. Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Vertue. Naſcitur enim ex prudentiâ ſapere, ex tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiâ ſobrium eſſe, &amp; pietate Deum colere. Hae ſunt cibi animae propiè, quae idonea eſt ad ſugendum, &amp;c.</hi> Philo Judaeus. 127.</p>
               <p>Is it a light matter that you have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed ſo noble a Nature all this while, and at once <hi>ſacrilegiouſly</hi> robbed God of that Honour which was due to him from the Rational Creature, and <hi>unnaturally</hi> ſet your Souls to ſale for every trifle? What if he (whoſe you are, whether you ſerve him or no) ſhould demand of you an account, what you have done with his Creature, how you came to proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute <hi>your</hi> Souls (which are more <hi>his</hi>) at ſo vile a rate? What if he had long ſince, in the midſt of your carnal Security, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led you out of that Fleſh in which you breathe, and ſent you into a Place where
<pb facs="tcp:64916:80"/>the Immortality of the Soul, the weight of Divine Wrath, and the evil of Sin, are better known? Are you not aſhamed to live as if you were <hi>meer Impertinences</hi> in the Creation? while the Inferior Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures round about you anſwer the Ends of their reſpective Beings. Can you ſuppoſe that you were born for no higher purpoſes, than to <hi>eat, drink, ſleep, ſport, talk, and make an appearance for a while up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Stage of the World,</hi> and then go off with <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> as if you had very well perform'd your part?</p>
               <p>If you would be aſhamed to own ſuch monſtrous Conceits as theſe, live not as if you did own them.</p>
               <p>Conſider ſeriouſly (for you can think, and think again about matters that leſs concern you) how wretchedly you have been befool'd, and led Captive all this while by the great Deceiver, who has carried on his deſign againſt you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board (though you obſerv'd him not;) and when you are paſt hope, will readily let you know, that you have <hi>loſt,</hi> and he has <hi>got</hi> the <hi>game.</hi> Let me conclude this Head with the words of a moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Poet,</p>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:81"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In cooler thoughts conſider what you've done,</l>
                     <l>And think that each of you hath kill'd a man,</l>
                     <l>Stabbing with murd'rous hands</l>
                     <l>That noble Reaſon by which Mortals are</l>
                     <l>Moſt like their Maker, and do bear</l>
                     <l>Their great Creator's Superſcription.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Think laſtly on the World's great Doom,</l>
                     <l>When guilty Souls muſt to an Audit come;</l>
                     <l>A far more heavy reckoning than e're You met with here,</l>
                     <l>More true by far, and yet far more ſevere.</l>
                     <l>Think on all this, and think on't ſoberly,</l>
                     <l>And then perhaps you'll ſay, as well as I,</l>
                     <l>Your mirth is madneſs, Wine a poiſon fell,</l>
                     <l>Your Paradiſe is Bedlam, if not Hell.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p n="3">3dly, <hi>Trifle no longer, leſt death overtake you unprepared for it. Now is the accepted time. Now is the day of ſalvation. Seek the Lord while he may be found. Call upon him while he is near.</hi> Which words, though encouraging to true Penitents, yet carry in them an <hi>awful</hi> intimation of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of being ſpeedy in our Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and that becauſe the time is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when God will not be found, when <hi>they ſhall call, and he will not anſwer,</hi> Prov. 1.28.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:81"/>The longer you delay, the more will your Guilt be increaſed, the habits of Sin ſtrengthened, the Spirit of God griev'd; beſide the hazard you run of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing <hi>in the mean time</hi> before you are aware. And if hereafter you ſhould be awaken'd to think of repenting, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring for another World, 'tis ten to one, but he who hath abus'd you ſo long, will then tempt you to believe it is too late. Methinks the Conſideration of Eternal Miſery ſhould even overwhelm you, and make you tremble at that Juſtice which you can neither <hi>reſiſt</hi> nor <hi>eſcape.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bear with this plainneſs. Your Caſe makes it neceſſary. If Complements and ſmooth words would ſerve the turn, you ſhould have them. But alas! while I am writing, and you reading, Time is run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning on, and Eternity is almoſt upon us, though we too little conſider it.</p>
               <p>How little a part of Time can you call your own? The time <hi>paſt</hi> is no longer yours. Of the time <hi>to come</hi> you are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly uncertain. And as for the <hi>preſent</hi> time, the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 'tis gone while you are naming it, and Philoſophers are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> greed to call it a part of time, becauſe of its indiviſibility. What ſhall I ſay? O that I knew but how to perſuade you; how joyfully would I do it, though I loſt
<pb facs="tcp:64916:82"/>Eſtate, Liberty, yea, or Life it ſelf in the Action. But 'tis ſad to think that I ſhould leave you under greater guilt than I found you. The Lord pity you, and teach you to pity your ſelves.</p>
               <p>And here I will take liberty to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the words of a Reverend Perſon, ſo well ſuited to the preſent Occaſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The State of the Caſe ſpeaks it ſelf, that there is no ſitting ſtill here. This is no Condition, Soul, to be reſted in, unleſs thou be provided to encounter the Terrors of Eternal Darkneſs, and endure the Tortures of Everlaſting Burnings. And yet am I not unap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive how great a difficulty a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Heart will make of it to beſtir it ſelf in order to any redreſs of ſo deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a Caſe. — They eſteem our ſtrongeſt Reaſonings (as <hi>Leviathan</hi> does Iron and Braſs) but as <hi>Straw,</hi> and <hi>rotten Wood,</hi> and laugh at Divine Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings as <hi>he</hi> doth at the ſhaking of the Spear. Yea, and when we have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd them, yet we have done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; though we have got their <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> and <hi>Conſciences</hi> on our ſide, and their own, their <hi>Luſts only</hi> reluctate and carry all. <bibl>Mr. <hi>How's Bleſſedneſs of the Righteous,</hi> pag. 344, &amp;c.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:82"/>4thly, <hi>Underſtand aright wherein the Life and Power of Religion doth conſiſt.</hi> 1 Cor. 4.20. <hi>The Kingdom of God is not in word, but in power.</hi> We read of Perſons that <hi>have a name to live, and yet are dead, Rev.</hi> 3.1. And, among the Monſters of the laſt Times, ſome are mention'd that have <hi>a form of godlineſs, but deny the power thereof,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.5. And now let us en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſeriouſly what this power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is.</p>
               <p>It cannot be ſuppoſed to conſiſt mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in an adherence to this or that Party. Nay, it is ſo far from conſiſting <hi>in</hi> this, that 'tis ſcarce conſiſtent <hi>with</hi> a dividing, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious, uncharitable Frame and Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Siding into Parties, judging and deſpiſing one another, and crying out, —<hi>Who is on my ſide, who?</hi> hath long been the ſhame of Chriſtians, and one of the greateſt Obſtructions to the Intereſt of our common Lord. This Temper began early to ſhew it ſelf, even among the Diſciples themſelves, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.38, 39. —<hi>Maſter, we ſaw one caſting out devils in thy name, and he followed not us; and we forbad him,</hi> &amp;c. From a like Diſpoſition you find <hi>ver.</hi> 34. they had been diſputing among themſelves <hi>who ſhould be the greateſt;</hi> and when our Lord queſtion'd them
<pb facs="tcp:64916:83"/>about it, <hi>ver.</hi> 33. they were afraid to tell what they had been talking of.</p>
               <p>How quickly ſhall we all be aſham'd of our childiſh Wranglings? Is this <hi>to become as little Children</hi> in a Scripture ſenſe? Is this to demonſtrate that we are his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>by loving one another?</hi> Or is it not rather to proclaim to the World, <hi>that we know not what manner of Spirit we are of?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Apology, <hi>cap.</hi> 39. <hi>pag.</hi> 47. glories in that Love and Unity which was among thoſe <hi>Primitive</hi> Chriſtians, and which the Heathens obſerv'd, crying out with Aſtoniſhment.— <hi>Vide ut invicem ſe diligant, &amp; pro alterutro mori ſunt parati. See how they love one another, and are ready to dye one for another.</hi> Hence he takes oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſharply (as his manner is) to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid the Heathens, that <hi>they hated one another, and were more ready to deſtroy one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Learned <hi>Grotius</hi> mentioning this paſſage of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> makes the following Reflection upon it.— <q>
                     <hi>Quid nunc illi dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, &amp;c.</hi> What would thoſe Chriſtians now ſay, if they ſaw our times? If they ſaw not merely <hi>ſharp Contentions;</hi> but even <hi>cruel Wars</hi> amongſt Chriſtians; <hi>&amp; quas ob reculas?</hi> for what trifles? If they heard all other marks of the Church
<pb facs="tcp:64916:83"/>brought in with a great deal of clamour, rather than that (<hi>viz.</hi> Loving one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) which was aſſign'd by its Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Neither can the power of Godlineſs be ſuppoſed to conſiſt in a cuſtomary Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon the publick Worſhip of God. <hi>Herod heard John gladly, and did many things. The Phariſees made long Prayers, and Faſted often.</hi> And the Prophet ſpeaks of ſome, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31, 32. who <hi>came and ſat before him as God's people; yea, they</hi> would hear his words, but not do them. With their <hi>Mouth they have ſhew'd much love, while their Heart run after their Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover a Man may be able to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe very well of Religion; may be very juſt in his dealings; very charitable to the poor; quiet and peaceable among his Neighbours, free from groſs and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous pollutions; be no <hi>Extortioner, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, unjuſt Perſon,</hi> Luk. 18.11. and yet be a ſtranger to the Life and Power of Chriſtianity all the while. I know this will go ill down with thoſe who have built their hopes of Salvation upon no better grounds than theſe. But there is no <hi>helping</hi> them without <hi>undeceiving</hi> them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:64916:84"/>In a word therefore, theſe following places of Scripture (if you be willing to learn) will ſhew you wherein the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Religion conſiſts.</p>
               <p>Luk. 13.24. <hi>Strive to enter in at the ſtrait gate: for many, I ſay unto you, will ſeek to enter in, and ſhall not be able.</hi> Matt. 22.37, 38. <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, and with all thy mind. This is the firſt, and great commandment.</hi> Chap. 10.37. <hi>He that loveth father or mother more than me, is not worthy of me:</hi> or, as <hi>Luke</hi> has it, <hi>cannot be my diſciple.</hi> Rom. 8.9. <hi>Now if any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his.</hi> 2 Cor. 5.17. <hi>Therefore if any man be in Chriſt, he is a new creature.</hi> Eph. 2.10. <hi>For we are his workmanſhip, created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works which God has before ordained that we ſhould walk in them.</hi> Tit. 2.14. —<hi>Who gave himſelf for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and purify unto himſelf a peculiar people, zealous of good works.</hi> Col. 1.2. <hi>Giving thanks unto the father which hath made us meet to be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the inheritance of the ſaints in light.</hi> 2 Cor. 5.5. <hi>Now he that has wrought us for the ſelf-ſame thing, is God, who alſo has given unto us the earneſt of the ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:84"/>Think not that I have here pickt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a few places of Scripture meerly to ſerve a turn; I tell you the whole Strain of the Goſpel runs this way; and <hi>if it be hid, its hid to them that are loſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if this Goſpel be true, certainly the Nature of Chriſtianity is little <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood,</hi> or <hi>conſidered,</hi> by multitudes that yet affect to be called Chriſtians. 'Tis no ſuch eaſy matter to be a Chriſtian indeed, as too many are apt to imagine. <hi>Running, Striving, Wreſtling, taking the Kingdom of Heaven by Violence,</hi> do all imply that we have many difficulties to conflict withal, and muſt either be in <hi>good Earneſt,</hi> or elſe loſe all our labour.</p>
               <p>'Tis further obſervable, that there muſt be a mighty change wrought upon us by the Spirit of God, elſe Chriſt will never own us as his Members.</p>
               <p>And 'tis as clear, that this great change conſiſts in turning our Hearts from the <hi>love of the Creature,</hi> to the <hi>Predominant love of God, and Holineſs.</hi> This is the <hi>Life,</hi> the <hi>Soul</hi> of the new Nature, which muſt animate all our other Graces, and be in us a continual Spring of holy Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
               <p>In a word; In this conſiſts our fitneſs for Heaven; and without it Heaven would not be <hi>Heaven</hi> to us, were it poſſible we
<pb facs="tcp:64916:85"/>could be admitted thither. Theſe things are ſo plain, that I need not further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large upon them, unleſs it be to bring them nearer to your own caſe, and help you to try your ſelves by them.</p>
               <p>Let us therefore ponder the matter a little. Can that Man be ſaid to make Religion his buſineſs, who will not be perſuaded ſoberly to exerciſe his Reaſon about it? Nor ſo much as to put the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to himſelf, — <hi>What was I Created and Redeemed for? What ſhall I do to be ſaved?</hi> Degenerate Souls! To what end was your Reaſon given you? Was it, think you, only to enable you the better to <hi>care,</hi> and <hi>plod,</hi> and <hi>provide</hi> for the Fleſh? Alas! that you ſhould know your ſelves no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter!</p>
               <p>Can that Man be ſuppoſed to love God with all his <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Soul,</hi> who cares not how little he <hi>thinks</hi> upon him? has no delight in his Service, but is glad when 'tis over? No Zeal for his Honour and Glory in the world; no concern when his Name is blaſphem'd and prophaned by the ungodly? who allows himſelf in a courſe of wilful Rebellion againſt him, and will not be perſuaded to renounce his Luſts, nor to ſet up the Worſhip of God in his <hi>Family</hi> and <hi>Cloſet,</hi> how plainly ſoever the Scripture enjoins it. In a word; who
<pb facs="tcp:64916:85"/>could be willing enough to continue on Earth for ever, might he but enjoy Fleſhly <hi>proſperity, fulneſs,</hi> and <hi>eaſe,</hi> though he ſhould never know more of God, nor love him better than now he doth, which is next to none at all.</p>
               <p>And what ſhall we ſay of thoſe who turn Religion into matter of ridicule and contempt? whoſe heart riſeth againſt any thing that's ſerious? They ſet their Wits at work to put <hi>Nick-names</hi> upon it, and yet the Wretches have the front to uſurp the Chriſtian name. <hi>Prodigious Inſolence!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is that man regenerate, think you, who, if you ask him what Regeneration means? what it is to be a <hi>new Creature?</hi> to be <hi>led by the Spirit of God?</hi> cannot anſwer you three words of ſenſe about it? nay; perhaps, knows not that there are any ſuch <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions</hi> in the Bible.</p>
               <p>Or can it be imagin'd, that a Perſon whoſe heart is ſet upon the world, and has no reliſh, nor ſavour of better things, but is quite out of his Element when imploy'd in any thing that has a nearer Relation, and tendency towards Heaven; can ſuch an one (I ſay) be imagin'd <hi>meet for that Inheritance,</hi> or to have <hi>any treaſure there,</hi> where his <hi>heart is not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could wiſh to know what Notion ſuch Men have of Heaven; What think you?
<pb facs="tcp:64916:86"/>How are the Saints and Angels employ'd there? Do they love God or no? Are they not wrapt up in admiring his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies and Perfections? and filled with continual Emanations, and Influences of Light and Love from him, and even transformed by that bleſſed Intuition? While the impure Spirits of the wicked are doom'd to a blacker Region, and plac'd in the Society of the Devils that deceived them. And can you believe two States ſo vaſtly different hereafter, and yet not conſider that there muſt be ſome ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able preparation while we are <hi>here?</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the very diſpoſition of our minds which may point out to us whither we are going? And ſince your Eternal Happineſs lies upon it, is it not worth your while to enquire, whether your Spirits are formed to any ſuch temper, as comports with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Heaven which has been ſet before you, and which you muſt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to allow of, unleſs you will renounce both <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Scripture?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet I deny not but the beſt of Men may have many Infirmities; <hi>Who can underſtand his errors? If we ſay we have no Sin, we deceive our ſelves.</hi> But ſtill you muſt obſerve, the ſinful weakneſſes of good Men are matter of continual grief to them: They watch and pray, and ſtrive
<pb facs="tcp:64916:86"/>againſt them, and heartily deſire to be rid of them, and long for that bleſſed State, in which they ſhall be <hi>perfectly</hi> ſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24.</p>
               <p>But on the other hand, wicked men love their Luſts; plead for them, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to extenuate them, cannot endure to think of parting with them, would rather have them <hi>gratified</hi> than <hi>mortified</hi> (as <hi>Auſtin</hi> confeſſeth of himſelf before his Converſion): ſo that they are under the power of <hi>Sin,</hi> and Strangers to that Life of Grace which would make them ſee and feel the evil of <hi>it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However, this conſideration ſhould make religious perſons the more circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, becauſe others are ſo apt to take encouragement from their failings.</p>
               <p>Theſe are no <hi>Singularities</hi> of Opinion, nor <hi>Fanatick, Enthuſiaſtical</hi> Notions, but words of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Soberneſs,</hi> in which all <hi>judicious</hi> good Chriſtians (of what deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination ſoever) are fully agreed. Would to God the ſerious conſideration of them, and a ſuitable practice, did more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally obtain among us, and then we ſhould quickly ſee our little differences vaniſhing as ſmoak, and the Churches of God in theſe Nations become <hi>a praiſe in the whole earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:87"/>
                  <hi>5thly,</hi> Study carefully the <hi>Reaſons of the Chriſtian Religion,</hi> as they are excellently ſet forth in a Book which bears that Title; where I dare be confident to affirm <hi>(rin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentibus licet viri celeberrimi adverſariis)</hi> you will find ſuch a complication of <hi>Learning, Perſpicuity,</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> as all the <hi>Atheiſts, Infidels, Sadducees,</hi> and <hi>Epicureans</hi> in the world, will never be able to withſtand.</p>
               <p>The light of Reaſon indeed, well em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, may help you far in diſcovering your <hi>Nature, Faculties, Duty, Intereſt,</hi> and <hi>End.</hi> But when you have done your beſt; many things will remain (appertaining to theſe already mention'd), as to which you will ſtill be in the dark, without the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>ſupernatural Revelation.</hi> For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, How the nature of man came to be ſo univerſally vitiated, and depraved; as we certainly find it is, and the <hi>Pagans</hi> themſelves have often acknowledged: How Divine Juſtice may be ſatisfied, and yet offending Sinners pardon'd, and receiv'd into favour: How humane Nature muſt be purified, reſtor'd, and fitted again for its proper <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>end. Quae quidem Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>io,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Porphyry</hi>) <hi>omni homini adeo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaria eſt, ut fieri non peſſit quin Deus univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem aliquam purgandi humani generis rationem procuràrit.</hi> This indeed is high; but you muſt
<pb facs="tcp:64916:87"/>remember he was a Philoſopher, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>of the ſacred Succeſſion,</hi> out of the School of <hi>Ammonius</hi> at <hi>Alexandria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that of <hi>Plato</hi> is yet more wonderful. <hi>Alcib.</hi> 2. <hi>Sect.</hi> 11. where he brings in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> inſtructing <hi>Alcibiades</hi> concerning Prayer: And after he had ſhew'd how little we know what's fit for our ſelves, and how dangerous it is to pray for things unſuitable for us, at laſt tells him, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>'Tis neceſſary that you wait, till ONE come, who will teach you how to behave your ſelf both towards God and man. When will that be (ſays <hi>Alcibiades</hi>), and who ſhall this Teacher be? For I would gladly know him whoever he is. 'Tis he, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Socrates,</hi> who careth for thee. But to me it ſeems that, as <hi>Homer</hi> tells us, <hi>Minerva</hi> took away the miſt from the eyes of <hi>Diomedes</hi> that he might diſcern God from man: So the darkneſs muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from thy mind. <q>At that day, ſays <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> will I make Offerings, and it will come e're long; let him take off the miſt from mine eyes, or what elſe he pleaſes, for I am prepared to omit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which he ſhall command (who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he be) ſo that I may be made better.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:88"/>The poor Heathens were ſenſible of the need of ſupernatural Revelation, which made them ſo fond of their <hi>Oracles,</hi> and of the <hi>Books of the Sybills,</hi> and the <hi>ſeveral ways of Divination</hi> that obtain'd among them: And thoſe of them who had great affairs in hand ſtill pretended to take in the ſpecial help of ſome ſuppoſed Deity, or other. Thus <hi>Numa</hi> makes ſhew of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting with the Nymph <hi>Egeria; Lycurgus, Minos; Solon</hi> with <hi>Jove:</hi> And the like is reported of that great Man <hi>Scipio Africanus: Caligula</hi> with <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux;</hi> and after all, <hi>Mahomet</hi> pretends to receive his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from the Angel <hi>Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Look therefore into all the pretences that have been made to ſupernatural Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, and ſee if you can find any, which may ſtand in the leaſt competition with theſe ſacred Records which we have in the holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Fragments of Zoroaſter,</hi> the <hi>Chaldaean Oracles,</hi> the <hi>Books of the Sybills,</hi> the <hi>Alchoran of Mahomet,</hi> will all appear <hi>uncertain,</hi> or <hi>frivolous</hi> if compared with the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt. Never was any Doctrine ſo ſuited to the raiſing of mens minds above this Earth, and fitting them for Glory and Immortality, as the Chriſtian Doctrine is. Our <hi>way</hi> and our <hi>end</hi> are here plainly ſet before us: And the very <hi>deſign</hi> and <hi>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:88"/>of the Goſpel may tell you its Author.</p>
               <p>It could not be the Invention of wicked men, or Devils, for it every where de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims againſt Sin, yea, even theſe <hi>inward</hi> Corruptions, which are not diſcernible to the eyes of men.</p>
               <p>It could not be a meer contrivance of good men or Angels, for they would never have dared to arrogate to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a <hi>Divine Authority,</hi> or to father their Writings upon God; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt needs be from him who hath own'd it with <hi>Succeſs,</hi> confirm'd it by <hi>Miracles,</hi> and preſerv'd it in deſpite of the ſubtilty and malignity of its ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to this day, and ſtill makes it <hi>his power to the Salvation</hi> of Sinners. The better any man is, the nearer he comes up to the Rules of Chriſtianity; and had the Goſpel been a <hi>lye,</hi> or <hi>device of deceivers,</hi> the <hi>God of Truth</hi> would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have made it an Inſtrument of ſo much good in the world, as he hath done.</p>
               <p>Direct. 2. <hi>If you believe that the Soul is Immortal, be not over-fond of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi> Keep it under; bring it into ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; uſe it as a Servant to the Soul, that both the <hi>one,</hi> and the <hi>other</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:89"/>may be fitter for the Service of him that made them. Keep it not ſo <hi>high</hi> as to make it Maſterleſs, nor ſo <hi>low</hi> as to unfit it for duty. <hi>A Servant when he ruleth is</hi> one of the things which the <hi>Earth cannot bear:</hi> The Body is a good <hi>Servant,</hi> if well managed, but a bad <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi> Keep your Minds as much as you can above the power of <hi>Corporeal Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> Let not the Objects of <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Appetite</hi> prevail too much upon you. <hi>Theſe two</hi> will quickly plead preſcription, and put in for Sovereignty, if too much indulged: They have ever been diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to rebel, ſince our Firſt Parents gave them that fatal advantage; and the ſway they bear over their degenerate Poſterity carries in it the <hi>mark,</hi> and <hi>brand</hi> of that firſt Apoſtacy. 'Tis this which threatens our ruin a <hi>ſecond</hi> time: And ſhall we ſplit upon the ſame Rock again, after ſo dreadful a warning? Suſpect all thoſe pleaſures in which the <hi>Body</hi> is much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, leſt the Spirit be debaſed by them, and begin to put too high a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue upon them, and ſo contract a <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene, ſenſual</hi> diſpoſition, and diſreliſh thoſe noble delights which are perfective of its Nature. Make not your Priſon too ſtrong: Think how quickly this Fleſh muſt be laid aſide as <hi>uſeleſs</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:64916:89"/>
                  <hi>offenſive.</hi> Why then will you cheriſh it, and make an Idol of it, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if you thought you muſt never leave it? What relief will it be to your miſerable Souls to remember, <hi>that in this Life you had your good things?</hi> Or if it were reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſuppoſe, (as ſome have done) that the Souls of the wicked hover about the places of their Bodies Interment, what ſatisfaction would it be to ſuch a Soul to think, Here lies Duſt, which while I ſtudied to pamper, I forgot, and loſt my ſelf? A <hi>cutting Reflection</hi> to a deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late forlorn Spirit, ſtript of all thoſe Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities which before inveigled it, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of thoſe Virtuous Principles, which would have enabled it, to mount aloft into a <hi>purer</hi> Region.</p>
               <p>It is therefore a great point of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to ſit looſe to the accommodations of this preſent Life: And if at any time we find our Minds diſpoſed (as they are too apt to be) to an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>great pleaſure in our worldly enjoyments, 'tis fit that we remember, <hi>this is not our home;</hi> our higheſt Intereſts are <hi>above;</hi> and the Relation which we bear to the <hi>world of Spirits,</hi> whither we are going, ſhould make us look more <hi>ſhily</hi> upon theſe temporary, periſhing things, as <hi>fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:90"/>and <hi>extrinſick</hi> to us, and no way ſuitable for the Immortal Spirit to reſt in: And if the leaſt thought ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate it ſelf,—That <hi>it is good for us to be here;</hi> we ought to reject it with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, and turn our Minds to nobler Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, till the powerful ſenſe of them hath awak'd us out of our dream, and ſhew'd us the <hi>vanity</hi> and <hi>emptineſs</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>Neither ſhould we be over-much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd at any croſſes or diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which may meet us in our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage through this world. Do not give them the way; ſuffer them not to come too <hi>near</hi> you, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Epictet. Enchir. Cap. 10. <hi>It is not the things themſelves which trouble men, but their Conceits and Opinions about them:</hi> At leaſt they grow heavier by <hi>weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and ſo we create, and multiply troubles upon our ſelves, by our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xiety and ſollicitude about theſe things, which to a <hi>calm ſerene</hi> temper, would have been but <hi>light afflictions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are your Circumſtances low and mean in the world?</hi> you are leſs in danger of growing in love <hi>with</hi> it, and ſo being enſnared and undone <hi>by</hi> it: Beſides, Nature is content with a <hi>little,</hi> though mens Luſts are <hi>inſatiable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:90"/>
                  <hi>Are Friends and Relations unkind, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh, unfaithful, or otherwiſe unſuitable to you?</hi> Who bad you over-value them, or promiſe your ſelves too much from them, or repoſe too great confidence in them? you may thank your ſelves in this caſe (as in moſt others) if you be <hi>anſwer'd according to your Idols.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is your Body afflicted with pain, ſickneſs, or languiſhing?</hi> you knew it was <hi>mortal</hi> before, and to what purpoſe have you liv'd all this while, if not to prepare for <hi>ſuch a time</hi> as this?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are you vilify'd and reproach'd by men (as it oft falls out) for keeping cloſe to your Duty?</hi> You ought no more to ſtop at it, than a man, in a race for his Life, ſhould be daunted at the <hi>braying of an Aſs,</hi> or the <hi>gagling of Wild-geeſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Life on Earth is but a <hi>dream:</hi> It paſſeth away <hi>as a viſion of the night:</hi> Men are ſtartled at <hi>phanſied</hi> dangers, but not duly apprehenſive of <hi>real</hi> ones. 'Tis not amiſs ſometimes to ſuppoſe (as <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilius Ficinus</hi> directs) <hi>forſitan haec non vera ſunt, forſitan in praeſentiâ ſomniamus;</hi> and as there is more of <hi>truth</hi> in ſuch a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, than moſt men conſider; ſo it will prevent our being over-much <hi>lifted
<pb facs="tcp:64916:91"/>up</hi> with proſperity, or <hi>dejected</hi> with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, ſince they are both alike parts of a <hi>dream,</hi> and the inviſible World of <hi>reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> is ſo very near us, whither, when we are once arrived, we ſhall think as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptibly of the far greateſt part of the Tranſactions of this world, as men are wont to do of their dreams, after they are well awake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb facs="tcp:64916:91"/>
               <head>The CONCLUSION.</head>
               <p>THUS I have endeavoured to prove, That the Soul is Immortal; and laid open the <hi>Abſurd</hi> and <hi>Miſchievous</hi> Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of the oppoſite <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> and withal I have ſhewed what improvement ought to be made of ſo important a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. A great deal more might have been ſaid on this occaſion, but what ſome will think too <hi>little,</hi> others will think <hi>too much;</hi> and therefore, to prevent miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings on both hands,</p>
               <p>I ſhall only add Two or Three parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars more.</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt. <hi>If any ſay, That I have undertaken a needleſs piece of work, and that ſuch a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe deſerved not to be anſwer'd but with ſcorn and contempt: I muſt tell them, That the degeneracy of this</hi> Atheiſtical <hi>Age, is a</hi> ſad, <hi>but</hi> ſufficient <hi>Apology for what I have done.</hi> It can <hi>never</hi> be unſeaſonable to put men in mind of a Future State, much leſs <hi>now:</hi> And though I look upon our Author's Cauſe to be <hi>ſtark naught,</hi> yet his manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:64916:92"/>of it (perhaps) is not ſo contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible as ſome may think: However, I am ſure the <hi>effects</hi> of it upon others are not <hi>ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2dly, <hi>Others, it may be, will think I have been too ſevere in the Remarks which I have made, conſidering the Quality of the perſon with whom I have to do:</hi> To which I anſwer, I hope they will not accuſe me of any <hi>rude perſonal</hi> Reflections; and as for his Opinion, to <hi>anſwer</hi> it, is to <hi>expoſe</hi> it. He has publickly debaſed all Mankind, and himſelf among the reſt, and therefore ought not to think much at any rational endeavours to right both <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the figure he bears in the world makes an anſwer ſo much the more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. When a perſon of conſiderable Note, a ſober Life, and one that has the reputation of a ſtudious thinking man, ſhall vent ſuch Opinions as theſe, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is like to ſpread ſo much further. <hi>Nullis Aconita bibuntur Fictilibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Omne animi vitium tanto conſpectius in ſe</l>
                  <l>Crimen habet, quanto Major, qui peccat habetur.</l>
               </q>
               <p n="3">3dly, <hi>Some perhaps will object, That I have not laid ſtreſs enough upon the</hi> Immateriality <hi>of the Soul in the preſent Controverſy.</hi> I would have ſuch to conſider, that <hi>over-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64916:92"/>is <hi>undoing;</hi> and to argue <hi>à minus notis,</hi> is not the way to <hi>defend</hi> the Truth, but to open the Mouths of its Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. If I have proved that the Soul is no ſuch <hi>periſhing, corruptible</hi> Matter, as our Author ſuppoſeth, this is what I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took; and if the uſe of the word <hi>Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial</hi> will pleaſe him, let him take it, for me, ſo long as he draws no <hi>bruitiſh Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion</hi> from it: And as for thoſe that have more refined Notions of <hi>Immaterial</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, I envy not their improvements; let them rejoice in their greater Light, provided they take not up with <hi>Arbitrary Conceits</hi> inſtead of <hi>ſolid Knowledge;</hi> nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure more plain, and certain Truths, by pretending to know theſe things, which, to a Soul in Fleſh are <hi>hardly,</hi> if <hi>at all,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible, how true ſoever.</p>
               <p>It ſeems clear to me, that our Author hath over-ſhot himſelf, by pretending to prove the Soul <hi>Mortal,</hi> becauſe he fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied it was hard to prove it <hi>immaterial,</hi> and this he thought gave him the advantage; but (to uſe his own phraſe <hi>pag.</hi> 12.) I judge <hi>he hath taken a wrong Sow by the ear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And tho' I deſire not to contend with any man, yet if <hi>he himſelf,</hi> or any of thoſe who have eſpouſed his Sentiments, ſhall think it convenient to Anſwer what I have written, they may expect a Reply if
<pb facs="tcp:64916:93" rendition="simple:additions"/>they deſerve it. For, as on the one hand, I think not my ſelf obliged to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low any one, who impertinently rambles from the matter, and ſeeks ſorry little <hi>Shifts</hi> and <hi>Evaſions,</hi> to avoid the force of plain evidence: So on the other hand, I think it worth my while, to allot a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable part of my remaining Life (if juſt occaſion be given me) to the Defence of the Soul's Immortality, and the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning down of theſe unmanly Notions, which ought to be <hi>exploded and hiſs'd out of the World</hi> by the meaneſt of Human Race.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
